<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<entry xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>What does free mean for libraries</title>
  <link href="/entries/2009/07/blogging/"/>
  <summary>Blogging is out, and the new trend is to tweet in
  Twitters. Syndication is out as well, since Google steals your content and
  you cannot make money on journalism. How can we survive when all media are
  free?</summary>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

      <p>Chris Anderson's book has finally appeared. The new one,
      <em>Free</em>, much discussed already before it was printed, and, off
      course, much hyped in the Wired magazin.</p>

      <p>How is this related to the situation for libraries? Well... I'd say:
      in just about any way you may imagine. However, let me start at an
      entirely different angle. Blog and wiki software were at the time
      the first easy ways to really take advantage of the new medium based on
      hypertext, a simple protocol and a global network. Through additions
      such as syndication and pings (notifications that new content have
      appeared) and automatic cross-linking (based on pings) to enable
      discussions across blogs, it goes beyond hypertext.</p>

      <p>This gave us basically new medium which using HTTP transaction
      creates human interaction.</p>

      <p>When a blog really takes off, the traffic generated is enough for
      letting the ads pay your rent and buy milk for your kids. Obviously some
      quality is required or it won't take off in the first place. That is
      what gives the attention needed for the transactions to take place.</p>

      <p>Blogging is cheap. You write about what's around you that you
      know. You benefit from from the transaction and attention economy which
      feeds the Internet. Syndication, aggregation, mashups and harvesting
      will move you're content around, and you'll mostly benefit from it.</p>

      <p>On the other hand, much of the user's navigation will take place
      elsewhere, and many user's will not be exposed to your ads but Google's.
      This lead to Jakob Nielsen's out-cry where he labelled them as <a
      href="http://www.useit.com/alertbox/search_engines.html">leeches</a>
      already a few years ago.</p>

      <p><a href="http://www.nybooks.com/authors/71">Michael Massing</a>
      discusses this and other issues in a <a
      href="http://www.nybooks.com/articles/22960">recent article</a> in The
      New York Review of Books. He quotes David Simon's statement in a
      testimony in front of the US Senate:</p>
      
      <blockquote>[Internet] <em>leeches...reporting from mainstream news
      publications, whereupon aggregating websites and bloggers contribute
      little more than repetition, commentary and froth. Meanwhile, readers
      acquire news from the aggregators and abandon its point of origin—namely
      the newspapers themselves. In short, the parasite is slowly killing the
      host.</em></blockquote>

      <p>There is a problem deep in this statement. It assumes that there
      would be no news without the traditional media. Since the traditional
      media are on the decline, We can be almost certain that this is not the
      case. Massing continues:</p>

      <blockquote>... <em>such statements seem as outdated as they are
      defensive. Over the past few months alone, a remarkable amount of
      original, exciting, and creative (if also chaotic and maddening)
      material has appeared on the Internet. The practice of journalism, far
      from being leeched by the Web, is being reinvented there, with a variety
      of fascinating experiments in the gathering, presentation, and delivery
      of news. And unless the editors and executives at our top papers begin
      to take note, they will hasten their own demise.</em></blockquote>

      <p>Do we really need these big media institutions? What use do we have
      for Reuters, CNN, AFP etc. They are good to have, but I'd say we could
      do without them. For example, the notion that we cannot get proper
      information from distant places without having expensive foreign
      correspondents travelling there seems extremely arrogant to me, on the
      verge of being racist.</p>

      <p>This is not to say that we don't need journalism. Indeed we do. But
      as Massing states, it is currently reinventing itself on the Internet. A
      new one which has adapted itself to the medium. One which is part of the
      transaction &amp; interaction based technology and economy.</p>

      <p>Now, let us return to <em>The Library</em>.</p>

      <p>The business model <em>The Library</em> is based upon the idea that
      it will save money to share media. It started with scholars sharing
      papyrus scrolls two thousand years ago. Continued with libraries within
      monastic societies during the middle age, where books were extremely
      valuable assets. Then, today, we're licensing electronic material... The
      marginal cost for producing one additional copy is <em>zero</em>. Hence
      in the end, the price will end up to be really cheap.</p>

      <p>Who will fund the acquisition of free resources. The library as we
      know it is as dependent on that we can save money by sharing valuable
      information objects. A collection of codices for the monastic society,
      or a campus license for electronic journals.</p>

    </div>
  </content>
  <dc:date>2009</dc:date>
  <category label="media" term="Media"/>
  <category label="thelibrary" term="The Library"/>
  <category label="internet" term="Internet"/>
  <updated>2009-07-31T18:30:14+01:00</updated>
  <published>2009-07-31T07:48:53+01:00</published>
  <!-- $Id$ -->
  <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/07/blogging/</id>
</entry>
