<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>Sigfrid Lundberg's Stuff</title>
  <id>http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/files.atom</id>
  <link rel="self" href="https://feeds.feedburner.com/SigfridLundbergsStuff?format=xml"/>
  <updated>2006-06-08T00:03:00+01:00</updated>
  <!--
      $Revision$, last modified $Date$
      $Id$
  -->
  <entry>
    <title>NWI — En nordisk söktjänst för World Wide Web</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Anders Ardö</name>
    </author>
    <link href="/1996/nwi/press_release.html"/>
    <summary>Ett konsortium av nordiska forskningsbibliotek och nätverksorgan
    presenterar Nordiskt Webindex, en nordisk söktjänst utvecklad i norden för
    en nordisk publik. I dag finns en experimentell tjänst offentligt
    tillgänglig på nätet på URL http://nwi.ub2.lu.se.</summary>
    <category term="Web indexing" label="webindexing"/>
    <category term="Harvesting" label="harvesting"/>
    <dc:date>1996</dc:date>
    <updated>2006-06-08T00:03:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>https://sigfrid-lundberg.se/1996/nwi/nwi.pdf</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>A proposal for metadata formats for use in the Swedish Enviro-Net</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <link href="/1997/SMN_metadata/smn_metadata.pdf"/>
    <summary>This paper outlines a combination of the Dublin Core metadata
    embedded in HTML metadata tags and the GILS Z39.50 profile used for
    information retrieval. It is a combination would solve the distributed
    indexing, search and retrieval problems within a network of environmental
    authorities. The Swedish Enviro-Net lived for a few years at the end of
    1990ties.</summary>
    <category term="Web indexing" label="webindexing"/>
    <category term="Metadata" label="metadata"/>
    <category term="Z39.50" label="z3950"/>
    <dc:date>1997</dc:date>
    <updated>2006-06-08T00:04:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>https://sigfrid-lundberg.se/1997/SMN_metadata/smn_metadata.pdf</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Kulturnät Sverige</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <link href="/1997/kultur_naet_sverige/"/>
    <summary>En recension av IT i kulturens tjänst, SOU 1997:14 som i mina
    ögon vid den tidpunkten var en fullständigt överflödig utredning. Här
    fanns alla möjligheter att börja arbeta för en konvergens när det gäller
    beskrivningsstandard och protokoll för informationsretrieval mellan olika
    grenar av kultursektorn. En tjock bok som ledde fram till en numera
    nerlagd ämnesportal.</summary>
    <dc:date>1997</dc:date>
    <updated>2009-06-08T00:05:00+01:00</updated>
    <category term="Digital collections" label="digitalcollections"/>
    <category term="Reviews" label="reviews"/>
    <id>https://sigfrid-lundberg.se/1997/kultur_naet_sverige/</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Kulturarw3 archiving format</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg, Lund University</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Allan Arvidson, The Royal Library</name>
    </author>
    <link href="/1998/KulturArw3/archive-format-1.rtf"/>
    <summary>This note describes a file format intended for the joint storage of
    objects retrieved from the World Wide Web and various kinds of meta
    information on those objects. The information includes the HTTP response
    header but may also contain information needed for version control etc
    within the archive. Kulturarw3 project proposes an archiving record format
    based on open standards, namely that objects are stored as HTTP MIME
    multpart/mixed messages (cf. RFC2068 and RFC1521 respectively).</summary>
    <dc:date>1997</dc:date>
    <updated>2006-06-08T00:07:00+01:00</updated>
    <category term="Digital preservation" label="preservation"/>
    <category term="Harvesting" label="harvesting"/>
    <id>https://sigfrid-lundberg.se/1998/KulturArw3/archive-format-1.rtf</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>NWI II, An Enhanced Nordic Web index: Final report</title>
    <author><name>Anders Ardö</name></author>
    <author><name>Allan Arvidson</name></author>
    <author><name>Sebastian Hammer</name></author>
    <author><name>Kenneth Holmlund</name></author>
    <author><name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name></author>
    <link href="/1998/nwi2/"/>
    <summary>The Nordic Web Index (NWI) project is a collaborative effort
    across the Nordic countries, aiming at providing a free Worldwide Web
    search service to the general public in the countries involved. NWI has
    been fruitful for several reasons: First and foremost we are today
    providing access to databases covering the WWW in four of the Nordic
    countries and, as of September 1998, five service points in six languages
    Denmark, Finland, Sweden, Norway and Iceland.</summary>
    <category term="Web indexing" label="webindexing"/>
    <category term="Harvesting" label="harvesting"/>
    <category term="Metadata" label="metadata"/>
    <category term="Z39.50" label="z3950"/>
    <dc:date>1998</dc:date>
    <updated>2006-06-08T00:08:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>https://sigfrid-lundberg.se/1998/nwi2/</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>En arkitektur för ett distribuerat system för spridning av
    forskningsinformation</title>
    <link href="/1998/safari/cris.pdf"/>
    <summary>Arkitekturen för ett nätverk av tjänster för spridning av
    forskningsinformation beskrivs. Nätverket tillåter distribuerat underhåll
    av såväl data som metadata. Till nätverket kan anslutas såväl
    bibliografiska databaser som helt WWWbaserade metadataberikade
    tjänster. Metadataproduktionen följer standarden Dublin Core. De förra
    typerna av tjänster inkorporeras i nätverket genom interoperabilitet på
    sökprotokollsnivå, medan metadata och fulltext från de senare göres
    sökbara genom en WWWrobot.  Kommunikation inom nätverket utnyttjar
    standardiserade Internet protokoll som HTTP, och för
    informationsåtervinning Z39.50</summary>
    <category term="Web indexing" label="webindexing"/>
    <category term="Harvesting" label="harvesting"/>
    <category term="Metadata" label="metadata"/>
    <category term="Z39.50" label="z3950"/>
    <dc:date>1998</dc:date>
    <updated>2006-06-08T00:10:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>https://sigfrid-lundberg.se/1998/safari/cris.pdf</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>A regional distributed WWW search and indexing service - the DESIRE
    way</title>
    <link href="/1998/www7/"/>
    <summary>In an attempt to implement a regional search engine we have
    created an open, metadata aware system for distributed, collaborative
    WWW-indexing. The system has three main components: a harvester (for
    collecting information), a database (for making the collection
    searchable), and a user interface (for making the information
    available). All components can be distributed across networked computers,
    thus supporting scalability. The system is metadata aware and thus allows
    searches on several fields including title, document author, and
    URL. Nordic Web Index (NWI) is an application using this system to create
    a regional Nordic web-indexing service. NWI is built using five
    collaborating service points within the Nordic countries. The NWI
    databases can be used to build additional services. Services today include
    special metadata databases, multimedia databases, and statistics about the
    Nordic Web.</summary>
    <category term="Web indexing" label="webindexing"/>
    <category term="Harvesting" label="harvesting"/>
    <category term="Metadata" label="metadata"/>
    <category term="Z39.50" label="z3950"/>
    <dc:date>1998</dc:date>
    <updated>2008-06-08T00:10:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>https://sigfrid-lundberg.se/1998/www7/</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Noble Art of Being Indexed or the Webmaster's Guide to
    Harvesting Robots</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Lars Nooden</name>
    </author>
    <link href="/1999/web_masters_guide/"/>
    <summary>As the title indicates, this is a note on how to be indexed by
    search engines. It is obsolete. Please note that it does not contain
    anything about search engine optimization in the modern evil
    sense. Instead it pinpoints what harvesting robots did understand, and what
    they didn't at the turn of the last century.</summary>
    <category term="Web indexing" label="webindexing"/>
    <category term="Metadata" label="metadata"/>
    <category term="Structural web design" label="structuralwebdesign"/>
    <dc:date>1999</dc:date>
    <updated>2006-06-09T00:11:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>https://sigfrid-lundberg.se/1999/web_masters_guide/</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Metadata harvesting</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <link href="/2000/delft/"/>
    <summary>This is unfortunately unpublished, but it presents most one of
    the most extensive datasets on the content of HTML embedded metadata which
    I collected while working with the Nordic Webindex.</summary>
    <category term="Web indexing" label="webindexing"/>
    <category term="Harvesting" label="harvesting"/>
    <category term="Metadata" label="metadata"/>
    <category term="Z39.50" label="z3950"/>
    <dc:date>2000</dc:date>
    <updated>2006-06-09T15:11:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>https://sigfrid-lundberg.se/2000/delft/</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Technical description of the Studera.Nu search engine Harvesting
    policies, maintenance and software used</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <link href="/2001/studera.nu/documentation/studera.pdf"/>
    <summary>This is a description of the Studera.NU search engine in the very
    first version. The search engine carries focused information, all of which is
    indexed manually by content providers. The indexing information is
    embedded into web pages using meta tags, and the service is built using a
    harvesting robot.  This article documents the functions of the search
    engine Studera.NU, its robot, search software etc. It aims at providing
    necessary background information both for staff involved in system
    management and future developers. A second aim is to give pinpoint areas
    for future developments of the service.</summary>
    <category term="Web indexing" label="webindexing"/>
    <category term="Harvesting" label="harvesting"/>
    <category term="Metadata" label="metadata"/>
    <dc:date>2001</dc:date>
    <updated>2009-06-09T00:18:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>https://sigfrid-lundberg.se/2001/studera.nu/documentation/studera.pdf</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Lecture notes: S:t Laurentius Digital Manuscript Library</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <link href="/2002/DRH2002/toc.html"/>
    <summary>In this lecture, I discussed the
    experiences gained by the development of a specific service, which, using
    a collection of detailed XML descriptions, provides its users access to a
    collection of digitized medieval manuscripts.  Secondly, I discussed the
    database used from the point of view of both retrieval of the intellectual
    content (the texts) of these manuscripts and of the retrieval of the
    manuscripts as unique entities. Finally, I turned to the possibilities for
    searching a collection of complex XML documents using a full text
    retrieval engine used together with the Z39.50 information retrieval
    protocol.</summary>
    <dc:date>2002</dc:date>
    <category term="XML processing" label="xmlprocessing"/>
    <category term="Metadata" label="metadata"/>
    <category term="Digital humanities" label="ehumanities"/>
    <category term="Digitization" label="digitization"/>
    <updated>2009-06-11T00:06:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>https://sigfrid-lundberg.se/2002/DRH2002/toc.html</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>S:t Laurentius Digital Manuscript Library: An excursion along the
    border between resource discovery and resource description</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <link href="/2002/Laurentius/laurentius.pdf"/>
    <summary>This note has three aims. First it discusses the experiences
    gained by the development of a specific service, which, using a collection
    of detailed XML descriptions, provides its users access to a collection
    of digitized medieval manuscripts.  Secondly, it discusses the database
    used from the point of view of both retrieval of the intellectual content
    (the texts) of these manuscripts and of the retrieval of the manuscripts
    as unique entities. Finally, it explores the possibilities for searching
    a collection of complex XML documents using a full text retrieval engine
    used together with the Z39.50 information retrieval protocol.</summary>
    <dc:date>2002</dc:date>
    <category term="XML processing" label="xmlprocessing"/>
    <category term="Text encoding" label="textencoding"/>
    <category term="Metadata" label="metadata"/>
    <category term="Digital humanities" label="ehumanities"/>
    <category term="Digitization" label="digitization"/>
    <updated>2009-06-11T00:19:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>https://sigfrid-lundberg.se/2002/Laurentius/laurentius.pdf</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Förslag till policy för digitaliseringsprojekt inom Lunds
    Universitets Bibliotek</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <link href="/2002/DigitaliseringsPolicy/digitaliserings_policy.pdf"/>
    <summary>Digital arkivering är att bereda serverplats för information om
    oss, vår tid och vår historia för våra barn och deras efterkommande. Detta
    dokument beskriver förutsättningarna för digitalisering, lagring och
    arkivering samt elektronisk publicering av olika samlingar inom Lunds
    universitet och dess bibliotek. Särskild vikt läggs vid att utveckla en
    nansieringsmodell för lagring, tillgängliggörande och bevarande.</summary>
    <dc:date>2002</dc:date>
    <category term="Digitization" label="digitization"/>
    <category term="Digital collections" label="digitalcollections"/>
    <updated>2009-06-11T00:18:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>https://sigfrid-lundberg.se/2002/DigitaliseringsPolicy/digitaliserings_policy.pdf</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Metadata model in Scripta Academica Lundensis</title>
    <author>
      <name>Colm Doyle</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Jörgen Eriksson</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Sara Kjellberg</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Tomas Schönthal</name>
    </author>
    <link href="/2002/Scripta/"/>
    <summary>This document specifies the metadata once used in the Lund university
    dissertation database.</summary>
    <category term="Digital collections" label="digitalcollections"/>
    <category term="XML processing" label="xmlprocessing"/>
    <category term="Metadata" label="metadata"/>
    <dc:date>2002</dc:date>
    <updated>2009-06-12T00:20:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>https://sigfrid-lundberg.se/2002/Scripta/</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>XML -- en mjuk start för biblioteksfolk Mitt ständigt ofärdiga
    undervisningsmaterial (...och en del annat)</title>
    <link href="/2003/XMLforLibrarians/"/>

    <summary>Denna text syftar till att ge en överblick över vissa områden av
    det digitala biblioteksområdet vilka är stadda i snabb utveckling. En
    utveckling som i hög grad katalyseras av utvecklingen av olika
    tillämpningar av eXtensible Markup Language, XML, som i år fyller fem år.
    Utöver användningen av XML inom det digitala biblioteksväsendet ges en
    överblick över modernt tänkande när det gäller metadata, hur XML kan
    tänkas påverka hur vi tar del av, och hanterar elektroniska texter både i
    form av digitalt bevarande och publicering av t ex
    forskningsrapporter.</summary>

    <category term="XML processing" label="xmlprocessing"/>
    <category term="Text encoding" label="textencoding"/>
    <category term="Metadata" label="metadata"/>
    <dc:date>2002</dc:date>
    <updated>2006-06-11T00:21:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>https://sigfrid-lundberg.se/2003/XMLforLibrarians/</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Implementering av OAI-PMH i ett bibliotekssystem -- Några ord på
    vägen</title>
    <link href="/2003/axiell-oai/oai-opac.pdf"/>
    <summary>Syftet med denna text är att ge lite kött på benen om vad OAI-PMH
    är, vad det kan användas till och hur det skulle kunna integreras i ett
    bibliotekssystem. Det är inte en ersättning för andra dokument utan skall
    ses som några ord på vägen för organisationer som planerar att eller är i
    färd med att implementera OAI-PMH. Texten skrevs på uppdrag av
    https://www.axiell.com/se/ </summary>
    <updated>2009-06-09T08:08:00+01:00</updated>
    <dc:date>2003</dc:date>
    <category term="Harvesting" label="harvesting"/>
    <category term="Metadata" label="metadata"/>
    <category term="Library catalogues" label="opac"/>
    <id>https://sigfrid-lundberg.se/2003/axiell-oai/oai-opac.pdf</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Teknisk samverkan mellan svenska ämnesportaler - Test och
    utvärdering av portalprogramvaran TKL</title>
    <author>
      <name>Colm Doyle</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Jörgen Eriksson</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Tomas Schönthal</name>
    </author>
    <summary>En utvärdering av digital library produkten Keystone DLS (TKL)</summary>
    <link href="/2003/def-test/"/>
    <updated>2009-06-09T08:23:00+01:00</updated>
    <dc:date>2003</dc:date>
    <category term="Digital collections" label="digitalcollections"/>
    <category term="Metadata" label="metadata"/>
    <category term="Reviews" label="reviews"/>
    <category term="XML processing" label="xmlprocessing"/>
    <id>https://sigfrid-lundberg.se/2003/def-test/</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Vad är ett PEK?</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <summary>Här rapporterar jag en konvergent språklig utveckling mellan
    forskare och internerna på Långholmen. I båda kategorierna används ordet
    "pek" för att beskriva en kommunikation, bland akademiker var det på
    1980-talet slang för "uppsats" och på Långholmen var det en text som
    skickades med linbana längs med fängelsemurarna.</summary>
    <link href="/2003/pek/"/>
    <dc:date>2003</dc:date>
    <updated>2009-06-09T20:25:00+01:00</updated>
    <category term="Music, language &amp; literature" label="musiclanglit"/>
    <id>https://sigfrid-lundberg.se/2003/pek/</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Pesistent länkning och digitala bibliotek</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <summary>Åtskillig uppmärksamhet har nyligen riktats mot problemen
    förknippade med att uppnå en stabilare webb. Det konstateras, helt
    korrekt, att mängder med dokument bara försvinner från sina ursprungliga
    platser. Vad skall man då göra åt saken? Vad är det för grundläggande
    designproblem som gör att organisationer vilka underhåller länksamlingar
    av olika slag tvingas bära en allt tyngre börda?</summary>
    <link href="/2003/urnar_och_digitala_bibliotek/"/>
    <dc:date>2003</dc:date>
    <updated>2009-06-09T20:36:00+01:00</updated>
    <category term="Digital libraries" label="digitallibraries"/>
    <category term="Metadata" label="metadata"/>
    <id>https://sigfrid-lundberg.se/2003/urnar_och_digitala_bibliotek/</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Ediffah – En digital infrastruktur för forskningsbibliotekens
    arkiv- och handskriftssamlingar</title>
    <link href="/2004/arkiv_bibliotek/"/>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <summary>Projektet syftar till att göra det möjligt att att skapa skapa
    allmänt tillgängliga kataloger och arkivbeskrivningar över bibliotekens
    handskriftssamlingar och personarkiv. Systemet skall vara enkelt, och
    innehålla ett arbetsflöde sådant att posterna som genereras också med
    automatik kan återfinnas i Nationella arkivdatabasen NAD, vårt
    gemensamma bibliotekssystem LIBRIS, såväl som i lokala
    databaser.</summary>
    <dc:date>2004</dc:date>
    <category term="Archival description" label="archivaldescription"/>
    <category term="Metadata" label="metadata"/>
    <category term="XML processing" label="xmlprocessing"/>
    <updated>2009-06-09T20:36:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>https://sigfrid-lundberg.se/2004/arkiv_bibliotek/</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Vad händer med biblioteket när dess samlingar finns överallt och
    ingen särskild stans?</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <link href="/2004/biblioteket/"/>
    <summary>Biblioteken existerar för att det finns användare som är beredda
    att betala för deras tjänster. Visserligen betalar man i regel via
    skattesedeln och inte med sitt betalkortet, men principen är densamma.
    Under vilka förutsättningar är användarna, eller deras valda
    representanter, redo att betala för bibliotekens tjänster? Går det att
    finansiera lokalt bibliotek när biblioteksresurserna finns överallt och
    ingen särskild stans? Vilken kommun eller vilket universitet kan
    finansiera ett bibliotek som bara har en katalog, men inga samlingar? Och
    när allt kommer omkring, vem vill ha samlingar och varför? De är ju dyra
    och tar plats.</summary>
    <dc:date>2004</dc:date>
    <category term="The Library" label="thelibrary"/>
    <category term="Digital libraries" label="digitallibraries"/>
    <category term="Internet" label="internet"/>
    <updated>2009-06-09T21:01:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>https://sigfrid-lundberg.se/2004/biblioteket/</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Vad en bra samling av digital text bör kunna</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <link href="/2004/digitalisering/position.pdf"/>
    <summary>En diskussion av vilka funktioner ett bra textarkiv bör, och vad
    digitalisering bör innebära.</summary>
    <category term="Digital libraries" label="digitallibraries"/>
    <category term="Metadata" label="metadata"/>
    <category term="Digital collections" label="digitalcollections"/>
    <dc:date>2004</dc:date>
    <updated>2009-06-09T21:10:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>https://sigfrid-lundberg.se/2004/digitalisering/position.pdf</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Digitalisering i Lund</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <summary>En presentation om digitalisering och digitalt bevarande i
    Lund. Jag tror att jag höll den vid ett stort möte på Kungl. Biblioteket i
    Stockholm.</summary>
    <link href="/2004/digitalisering/presentation_04-11-04.html"/>
    <category term="Digital preservation" label="preservation"/>
    <category term="Digitization" label="digitization"/>
    <dc:date>2004</dc:date>
    <updated>2009-06-09T21:45:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>https://sigfrid-lundberg.se/2004/digitalisering/presentation_04-11-04.html</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Metadata makes the world going round - en orientering om användning
    av Metadata och XML</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sara Kjellberg</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <link href="/2004/metadata_makes_the_world/"/>
    <summary>Sara Kjellberg och jag höll ett antal kurser om metadata
    o. XML. detta är vår presentation. Vi höll det inom ramen för BTJs
    kursutbud.</summary>
    <category term="XML processing" label="xmlprocessing"/>
    <category term="Metadata" label="metadata"/>
    <dc:date>2004</dc:date>
    <updated>2009-06-09T21:58:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>https://sigfrid-lundberg.se/2004/metadata_makes_the_world/</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Vilken arkitektur ger ett nav i ett nätverk?  Om
    KB-utredningen</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <link href="/2004/navet/navet.html"/>
    <summary>En recension av KB-utredningen, SOU 2003:129</summary>
    <category term="The Library" label="thelibrary"/>
    <category term="Reviews" label="reviews"/>
    <dc:date>2004</dc:date>
    <updated>2009-06-09T22:06:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>https://sigfrid-lundberg.se/2004/navet/navet.html</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Zornmedaljens baksida</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <summary>En diskussion av Zornmärket och
    riksspelmannainstitutionen och dess roll i svensk folkmusik</summary>
    <link href="/2004/zorn_etc/"/>
    <category term="Music, language &amp; literature" label="musiclanglit"/>
    <dc:date>2004</dc:date>
    <updated>2009-06-09T22:06:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>https://sigfrid-lundberg.se/2004/zorn_etc/</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Ediffah</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <link href="/2005/Oct_28/"/>
    <summary>En superkort presentation om Ediffah, hållen vid
    Ediffahprojektets avslutning på Kungl. Biblioteket i Stockholm den 28
    oktober 2005</summary>
    <category term="Metadata" label="metadata"/>
    <category term="Archival description" label="archivaldescription"/>
    <dc:date>2005</dc:date>
    <updated>2009-06-09T22:06:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>https://sigfrid-lundberg.se/2005/Oct_28/</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Digitala biblioteket</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <summary>En föreläsning om Internets historia, Det Digitala Biblioteket
    och Bibliotekets historia.</summary>
    <link href="/2005/bivil-digitala-bibliotek/"/>
    <dc:date>2005</dc:date>
    <updated>2009-06-09T22:06:00+01:00</updated>
    <category term="Digital libraries" label="digitallibraries"/>
    <category term="Internet" label="internet"/>
    <id>https://sigfrid-lundberg.se/2005/bivil-digitala-bibliotek/</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Digital preservation and digitization at Lund University (and
    elsewhere in Sweden)</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <link href="/2005/digital-preservation/"/>
    <summary>Notes to presentation held in Lund 7 June 2005. The audience was
    a group of people from China</summary>
    <category term="Digital preservation" label="preservation"/>    
    <category term="Digitization" label="digitization"/>
    <category term="Digital collections" label="digitalcollections"/>
    <dc:date>2005</dc:date>
    <updated>2009-06-09T22:06:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>https://sigfrid-lundberg.se/2005/digital-preservation/</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Konkurrerar Google framgångsrikt med biblioteken?</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <link href="/2006/google/google-vs-thelibrary.html"/>
    <summary>En diskussion om Bibliotekets förhållande till sökmaskinen
    Google</summary>
    <category term="The Library" label="thelibrary"/>
    <category term="Digital libraries" label="digitallibraries"/>
    <category term="Internet" label="internet"/>
    <dc:date>2006</dc:date>
    <updated>2009-06-09T23:14:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>https://sigfrid-lundberg.se/2006/google/google-vs-thelibrary.html</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Usage of digital resources with respect to method of publishing</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <link href="/2007/hidden_web/usage_vs_dissemination_method.html"/>
    <summary>I compared the usage of Digital material in relation to whether
    the material was hidden away in the the library opac or published on our
    web site. The result was as expected a disappointment for those who regard
    the Library catalogue as an important vehicle for dissemination of digital
    material</summary>
    <category term="The Library" label="thelibrary"/>
    <category term="Library catalogues" label="opac"/>
    <category term="Digital libraries" label="digitallibraries"/>
    <category term="Internet" label="internet"/>
    <category term="Structural web design" label="structuralwebdesign"/>
    <dc:date>2007</dc:date>
    <updated>2009-06-09T23:14:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>https://sigfrid-lundberg.se/2007/hidden_web/</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>

    <title>What do our users expect from the search field on our top
    page?</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <link href="/2007/search-statistics/user-expectations.html"/>
    <summary>What can deduced by analyses of the search terms entered into the
    search field on the home page of a large modern library? Could we possibly
    regard this form as the digital library´s information desk, and the
    queries as the request from its patrons? If we do that, what could we then
    learn about the quality of service?  In this note we do just that. We
    regard the terms entered into the form as manifestation of our patrons
    needs and in order to find out what they need, we have performed a
    preliminary text mining exercise. We hope that this will help us designing
    a new search facility that will better answer the needs of our
    users.</summary>
    <category term="Web indexing" label="webindexing"/>
    <category term="Harvesting" label="harvesting"/>
    <category term="Library catalogues" label="opac"/>
    <category term="Structural web design" label="structuralwebdesign"/>
    <dc:date>2007</dc:date>
    <updated>2009-06-09T23:31:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>https://sigfrid-lundberg.se/2007/search-statistics/</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>ADL i CLARIN-DK WP5</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <link href="/2008/clarin_adl/"/>
    <summary>En presentation jag höll om Arkiv før dansk litteratur (ADL)</summary>
    <category term="XML processing" label="xmlprocessing"/>
    <category term="Text encoding" label="textencoding"/>
    <category term="Digital humanities" label="ehumanities"/>
    <category term="Music, language &amp; literature" label="musiclanglit"/>
    <dc:date>2008</dc:date>
    <updated>2009-06-09T23:42:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>https://sigfrid-lundberg.se/2008/clarin_adl/</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Digital Humanities Infrastructures</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <link href="/2008/dighum/digital_humanities.xml"/>
    <summary>This note discusses different initiatives as regards providing
    access to resources and tools aimed at researchers within the
    humanities. Since the general breakthrough of search services like Google,
    annotation and bookmarking services like del.icio.us and the like, the
    attitudes towards the application of computing within the humanities has
    changed. In addition, the concept of e-science has contributed to make
    scholars positive to apply computing to various problems within the
    humanities.  Following a discussion started around year 2000, we propose
    that it is possible to formalize many humanities computing tasks as
    pipelines between XML processing steps.</summary>
    <category term="XML processing" label="xmlprocessing"/>
    <category term="Text encoding" label="textencoding"/>
    <category term="Digital humanities" label="ehumanities"/>
    <dc:date>2008</dc:date>
    <updated>2009-06-09T23:42:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>https://sigfrid-lundberg.se/2008/dighum/digital_humanities.xml</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Kortfattat Curriculum Vitae: Sigfrid Lundberg</title>
    <link href="/2009/cv/cv_sv.xml"/>
    <category term="About me" label="aboutme"/>
    <summary>Ett CV är väldigt tråkigt att skriva</summary>
    <dc:date>2009</dc:date>
    <updated>2009-06-09T23:54:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>https://sigfrid-lundberg.se/2009/cv/cv_sv.xml</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>List of publications by Sigfrid Lundberg
    </title>
    <link href="/2009/cv/publications.html"/>
    <summary>Both peer reviewed articles, other articles and some
    presentations</summary>
    <dc:date>2009</dc:date>
    <updated>2009-06-09T23:57:00+01:00</updated>
    <category term="About me" label="aboutme"/>
    <id>https://sigfrid-lundberg.se/2009/cv/publications.html</id>
  </entry>

  <entry xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>Add footnotes to my pages -- a prototype text annotation
  interface</title>
  <link href="/footnotes/"/>
  <summary>I've had a javascript based forum with thread for each entry. That
  seemed boring to me. Why should users be restricted to commenting entire
  articles. Why not letting them add footnotes to arbitrary positions in a
  text. In this entry I experiment with this feature.</summary>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

      <p>In order to understand what's going on here, you have have to <a
      href="https://sigfrid-lundberg.se/footnotes/">visit the
      resource</a>. There is a some scripting going on which cannot be
      syndicated. If you're reading this, you are on the wrong
      page. Sorry.</p>

      <h2>What you can do here</h2>

      <p>There is a link at the top of this page (if you're reading the HTML
      version <a href="https://sigfrid-lundberg.se/footnotes/">directly from my
      site</a>, that is). It says "Show anchors". It's not a very user
      friendly description of what it does, but I cannot figure out a better
      term right now. If you click on it, there will appear a link after most
      words in the text. These are the annotation anchors of this text.</p>

      <p>When visible, the anchors appears as a clickable asterisk '*', and a
      click on one of them activates the usual <a href="disqus.com">disqus.com
      forum</a>. This is by some client side DOM programming.</p>

      <p>Submitting a footnote works, but the script never get the
      acknowledgement from the disqus.com server. I don't know why, but it
      seems that the form doesn't like to live in an iframe.</p>

      <p id="anchor55576b680.592539918884886">My server retrieves the
      annotations from the disqus.com web services and print a list of notes
      at the end of the page. This is done server side, shuch that the
      discussions within the footnotes will be visible by search engines. The
      place of the annotation is marked as a note with a link to the
      notes. You may read the annotation when your mouse is over the link.</p>

      <p>Is this a good idea? Do you like it? Should all my pages have user
      supplied foot notes?</p>
      
      <h2>How is it done</h2>

      <p id="anchor55018b510.584488500647474">In order to add footnotes to a
      text, we need to be able to address individual positions in it. These
      positions are what I'd like to call annotation anchors. I've already
      briefly discussed the problem on how to create identifiers (see a <a
      href="https://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/08/quotations/">A
      quotation is much more than an extract</a>). For this entry I've
      extended the xslt script such that it can <a
      href="https://exslt.org/str/functions/tokenize/">tokenize</a> html text
      embedded in atom entry documents. It can also add anchors (id
      attributes) on each individual word (produced by the tokenize function)
      in the whole text. We also implement a javascript which expose these
      anchors to users, and allow them to comment more or less arbitrary point
      in the text.</p>

      <p id="anchor55402b10.359095368701543">There is a <strong>big</strong>
      drawback in this procedure; once you have processed your text and the
      anchors are there, then you <strong>must not</strong> change them. Each
      word has become a resource on the internet. Please view the source of
      this document, before you use the stylesheet <kbd><a
      href="https://sigfrid-lundberg.se/footnotes/atom_anchor_id.xsl">atom_anchor_id.xsl</a></kbd>.</p>

      <pre>
	&lt;span id="anchor54764">Would&lt;/span>
	&lt;span id="anchor54766">you&lt;/span>
	&lt;span id="anchor54768">like&lt;/span>
	&lt;span id="anchor54770">to&lt;/span>
	&lt;span id="anchor54772">edit&lt;/span>
	&lt;span id="anchor54774">this&lt;/span>
	&lt;span id="anchor54778">text?&lt;/span>
      </pre>

      <p>See what I mean? I cannot author prose like that in my XML
      editor. You wouldn't suffer as much using WYSIWYG tools, but on the hand
      it would presumably destroy the ID-strings.</p>

      <p>When preparing this text, I felt that I had to prepare some
      annotations of my own, and in order to do that I compiled the text,
      published it, made my annotation and then pasted the ID back into the
      source XML in order to be able to continue writing. Formbased proof
      reading of an existing digital text wouldn't be any problem, though.</p>

      <h2>Javascript &amp; DOM scripting</h2>

      <p>You can find the possible anchors by clicking on the link
      <strong>Show anchors</strong>, and hide them again by clicking on
      <strong>Hide anchors</strong> at the same place (there is a
      toggle). There are two javascript functions handling the toggling. The
      possibly most interesting, but also, the most vulnerable, feature is the
      generation of javascript from rss for handling the readable
      notes.</p>

      <pre>
      &lt;script type="text/javascript">
	    var usedAnchorIds = new Array();
	    var noteTexts     = new Array();
	    
	    usedAnchorIds[0]="anchor55402b10.359095368701543";

	    noteTexts[0]='I had problems obtaining unique id strings from the'
	    +'generate-id() function in XSLT. (siggelundberg, Fri, 18 Sep 2009'
	    +'17:46:27 -0000)';

	    usedAnchorIds[1]="anchor55018b510.584488500647474";

	    noteTexts[1]='This is an arbitrary point in my text. I find this'
	    +'really suitable for adding a footnote. (siggelundberg, Fri, 18 Sep
	    +'2009 03:27:16 -0000)';

	    printNotes(usedAnchorIds,noteTexts);

    &lt;/script>
      </pre>

      <p>The rest of the features are readily visible on this page. You have
      to reaload the page to see the new footnote -- if I implement this I'll
      will refresh those asynchronously.</p>

    </div>
  </content>
  <dc:date>2009</dc:date>
  <category label="structuralwebdesign" term="Structural web design"/>
  <category label="xmlprocessing" term="XML Processing"/>
  <updated>2009-09-19T15:13:49+01:00</updated>
  <id>https://sigfrid-lundberg.se/footnotes/</id>

</entry>


</feed>
