<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div>
    <h1 style="font-family: sans-serif; width: 55%; float: left;text-align: left;">Skirmishes along the boarder of the PC</h1>
    <p style="width: 38%; float: left;text-align: right">
      <em>
        <strong>
		Sigfrid Lundberg's Stuff,
	      2010-06-10</strong>
      </em>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div style="clear:both;"> </div>
  <div style="width:100%;">
    <div>

      <p><q>Tablets, eReaders, Smartbooks: You Name the Device and It’s News
      at Computex</q> <a href="http://blogs.arm.com/arm-events/tablets-ereaders-smartbooks-you-name-the-device-and-its-news-at-computex/">writes
      Katie Morgan</a> of Advanced Risc Machines (ARM). You may not know about
      it, but just as Intel rules the desktop, the British chip design
      company's ARM Architecture rules the pockets.</p>

      <p>According to Wikipedia, 90%+ of all processors in embedded devices and an even higher of the mobile 
      devices are designed around this architecture. 
      There's.a fair chance that both your phone, your wireless router and
      your fridge are all ARM systems.</p>

      <p>Most new gadgets appear first at <a href="http://www.computextaipei.com.tw/">Computex</a>, and most of them
      are based on <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ARM_architecture">the
      ARM architecture</a>.</p>

      <h3>The chip territories</h3>

      <p>The mobiles &amp; the tablets are currently given prominent positions
      in the news feeds, and as I write this there one such item in top of
      Google News' Sci/Tech section. It is usually about Apple's iPhone or
      iPad, both of which, by the way, like the Android systems, are ARM.</p>

      <p>Intel has tried to establish itself in this area, but have not been
      able to do so through can getting an increased market share by winning
      customers from ARM. The tablet is a new market segment, and the race has started to gain control over the as yet
      unchartered land. The chip Intel tries to market is the
      Atom processor which, of course, is x86. See, for instence:
      
	<a href="http://tech.fortune.cnn.com/2010/06/08/arm-intel-living-room/?section=magazines_fortune">ARM
	and Intel's new battleground: the living room</a>

      </p>

      <h3>Software frontiers</h3>

      <p>At basic academic levels there's differences. Frontiers. Different
      academic traditions expressing themselves in people's pockets.</p>

      <p>For those who don't know the history of the Unixes, it is well worth
      to know that Linux is a reverse engineered variant of the AT&amp;T
      System V Unix originally by Linus Torvalds who at the time lived in
      Hellsinki. There is also a free Unix coming from the Berkeley Software
      Distribution BSD Unix. BSD &amp; Linux come with very different open
      source licenses.</p>

      <p>Google's Android &amp; Chromium are both Linux platforms (hence
      Helsinki &amp; Stanford Universities), whereas iPhone OS is a
      redecorated Berkeley Unix with a Mach kernel. Yes, it is a Mach kernel,
      Mack as in the speed of sound, not Mac as in Macintosh. These gadgets
      are somehow affiliated to University of California &amp; Carnegie Mellon
      University. It shouldn't surprice you that Steve Wozniak got his
      training in computer science and electric engineering at Berkeley.</p>

      <p>Whenever there are conflicts, people form alliances, sometimes new and
      entirely unexpected:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>
	  <p>

	    <q>The good news is that we finally have an operating system to
	    unite behind. Android is an operating system that has gained a
	    tremendous amount of momentum all over the world</q>

	    [...]

	    <q>Android has become the fastest growing mobile operating system
	    in the world and, in fact, it has surpassed the iPhone in terms of
	    growth and in terms of users</q>,

	    said 

	    <a href="http://www.computerworld.com/s/article/9177518/Nvidia_CEO_Hardware_makers_uniting_behind_Android_for_tablets">Jen-Hsun Huang</a>,
	     president and CEO at Nvidia
	  </p>
	</li>

	<li>
	  <p>
	    <q>Global leaders Intel Corporation and Nokia merge Moblin and
	    Maemo to create MeeGo, a Linux-based software platform that will
	    support multiple hardware architectures across the broadest range
	    of device segments, including pocketable mobile computers,
	    netbooks, tablets, mediaphones, connected TVs and in-vehicle
	    infotainment systems.</q> [...]

	    <q>MeeGo will be hosted by the Linux Foundation and governed using
	    the best practices of the open source development model.</q>

	    <a href="http://www.intel.com/pressroom/archive/releases/2010/20100215corp.htm">intel.com</a></p>

	    <p><a href="http://meego.org/meego-v1-0-core-software-platform-netbook-user-experience-project-release/">Just
	    recently Meego 1.0 was released</a>. A lot of creative work focus
	    on Meego, and it seem to gain impetus, there are aleady quite
	    discussions around it and even a positive review in <a href="http://arstechnica.com/open-source/reviews/2010/05/hands-on-meego-for-netbooks-picks-up-where-moblin-left-off.ars">ArsTechnica</a>,
	    where you can find a <a href="http://arstechnica.com/open-source/news/2010/06/meego-linux-platform-gains-allies-at-computex.ars">discussion
	    of the prospects of the system</a>.</p>

	</li>

	<li>
	  <p>
	    This is very hardware oriented alliance, formalized as a not for profit company. Its mission is so.interesting, so I just had to quote the whole list:
	    <ul>
	      <li>ARM, Freescale, IBM, Samsung, ST-Ericsson and Texas
	      Instruments have created the not-for-profit company, Linaro,
	      committed to providing new resources and industry alignment for
	      open source software developers using Linux on the world’s most
	      sophisticated semiconductor System-on-Chips (SoCs).</li>

	      <li> Linaro will invest resources in open source projects that
	      can then be used by Linux-based distributions such as Android,
	      LiMo, MeeGo, Ubuntu and webOS.</li>

	      <li> Linaro will provide a stable and optimized base for
	      distributions and developers by creating new releases of
	      optimized tools, kernel and middleware software validated for a
	      wide range of SoCs, every six months.</li>

	      <li> Linaro's base of software and tools will be applicable to a
	      wide range of markets, helping reduce time-to-market for
	      products such as smart phones, tablets, digital televisions,
	      automotive entertainment and enterprise equipment.</li>

	      <li> Linaro's first software and tools release is due out in
	      November 2010, and will provide optimizations for the latest
	      range of ARM® Cortex™-A family of processors.</li>
	    </ul>
	  </p>
	  <p><a href="http://www.linaro.org/arm-freescale-ibm-samsung-st-ericsson-and-texas-instruments-form-new-company-to-speed-the-rollout-of-linux-based-devices/">linaro.org</a>. 
	  Linaro's mission is to ensure that there will be a Linux kernels and
	  device drivers for a large number of mobile platforms. See the point here? All of a sudden it will be as 
	easy to install Ubuntu Linux on a smart phone as 
	it is on a standard PC today.</p>

	</li>

      </ul>

      <p>Anyone percieving a pattern? There are quite a few companies out
      there that see an opportonity for both innovation and business. Quite a
      few of them would very much like to see one or more of the actors Google, Apple and
      Microsoft. Furthermore, there are some that wouldn't mind a bit less
      influence of Intel and AMD.</p>

      <h3>The PC and the Tablet</h3>

      <p>I read and write mail, manage my calendars, surf and do a better part
      of my wordprocessing with my <a href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2010/05/n900/">tablet</a>. 
      That is, I want a hand-held gadget which
      enables me to be creative anywhere anytime. 
	This is pin-points one of 
      questions most important questions: Why do we buy gadgets for computing.
      That is, does user consume digital media or should
      the gadget release his or her productivity.</p>

      <p>The vendors have obviously radically different views on the future of
      computing. Recently Steve Jobs claimed that the PC as we know it is like
      an old truck and that the future belongs to the tablets. Steve Ballmer
      participated in the same conference and disputed these claims. He seemed
      to be convinced that the desktop PC will continue to be the workstation
      for a foreseeable future. <a href="http://blogs.computerworld.com/16252/were_ballmer_ozzie_in_denial_at_d">Read
      more about blogosphere is saying about D</a></p>

      <p><q>The PC as we know it will continue to morph,</q> he said. <q>The
      real question is what are you going to push.</q> In Microsoft’s case,
      the answer is more machines that run flavors of Windows. <q>To a man
      with a hammer everything looks like a nail; we have a hammer,</q> <a href="http://bits.blogs.nytimes.com/2010/06/03/ballmer-the-pc-will-continue-to-thrive/">Mr. Ballmer
      joked</a>. The problem is, it isn't funny, not at all. It is as arrogant
      as it is tragic.</p>

    </div>
    <br clear="all"/>
    <p style="text-align: left;"><em><strong>Categories:</strong></em> 
	  <a href="/subjects/hardware/">Hardware</a>,
	    <a href="/subjects/software/">Software</a><br/><em><strong>
		Permalink:
	      </strong></em><a rel="bookmark" href="/entries/2010/06/frontiers/">http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2010/06/frontiers/</a></p>
    <hr width="50%" align="center"/>
  </div>
  <div>
    <h1>Other, not yet obsolete stuff</h1>
    <table class="news">
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2010</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2010/05/resourcecentric/"><em>Focus on the resources</em></a><br/>Having had a web site for about 15 years, I start to wonder why I
  keep it in the first place.<br/><a href="/subjects/digitalobjects/">Digital Object</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/objectstores/">Digital Object Stores</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2010</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2010/04/readings/"><em>Readings on digital objects: An annotated URIography</em></a><br/>I have a long list of articles to read on digital objects, how to
  model them etc. This page is for keeping track of my progress<br/><a href="/subjects/digitalcollections/">Digital collections</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/digitalobjects/">Digital objects</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2010</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2010/05/connected/"><em>On my life as being connected</em></a><br/>The new smartphone/tablet computer intervenes in my life, sometimes
  annoying me, but more often my wife and other people<br/><a href="/subjects/stories/">Stories</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2010</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2010/04/bells/"><em>Bell's Books</em></a><br/>I bought three books at Bell's Books, 536 Emerson Street, Palo
  Alto<br/><a href="/subjects/stories/">Stories</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2010</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2010/05/tabletsagain/"><em>Will the tablets change the world?</em></a><br/>I have previously discussed the impact of the tablet computer, an
  in particular iPad, and described how I've acqired one myself. Here I give
  some further pointers on the subject.<br/><a href="/subjects/hardware/">Hardware</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/media/">Media</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2010</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2010/05/tulips/"><em>Thinking about tulips dropping their petals</em></a><br/>The spring is advances. April's weather has been staying, but
  nevertheless the Thinker's Tulips have dropped their petals.<br/><a href="/subjects/images/">Images</a></td>
      </tr>
    </table>
  </div>
</div>
