<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div>
    <h1 style="font-family: sans-serif; width: 55%; float: left;text-align: left;">Twelve weeks</h1>
    <p style="width: 38%; float: left;text-align: right">
      <em>
        <strong>
		Sigfrid Lundberg's Stuff,
	      2009-09-05</strong>
      </em>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div style="clear:both;"> </div>
  <div style="width:100%;">
    <div>


      <p>It is about twelve weeks since i refurbished and redecorated this
      site. It is time for an evaluation. I do ask myself more or less daily
      if I can continue to say that this is worthwhile? My answer has been yes
      so far. I also ask myself if I do a good enough job, and to that my
      answer has been: Yes, I believe that some of my entries are good
      enough.</p>


      <div style="float: left; width: 50%; margin-left:0.5em;margin-right:0.5em;">

	<a href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/09/twelveweeks/usage.pdf">
	  <img src="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/09/twelveweeks/usage.png" alt="About 12 weeks usage statistics for my site." width="100%" border="0"/>
	</a>

	<p>
	  <small>Figure 1. Average number of visits per week for my site
	  sigfrid-lundberg.se (in blue) and the average time (in seconds)
	  people stay there (in red). Week 1 in the graph is the starting June
	  14, 2009. The last week is August 23 to 29.</small>
	</p>
      </div>

      <p>The number of visitors has been growing steadily from only a few
      individual visitors per week, to about two dozen. But on the other hand
      the time spend reading have declined dramatically (Figure 1). I do have
      a handful of visitors staying for a couple of minutes reading my weekly
      entry. This is easy to tell from the google statistics. I have no graphs
      on this, but distribution of time spent per visit is bimodal. A majority
      stays less than ten seconds, very few stay for a minute but a larger
      minority stay for three to five minutes, perhaps reading one entry and
      skimming another.</p>

      <p>My most successful entry is <a href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/08/trends/">On Divorce and
      Unemployment Benefit Societies</a>. I do think it deserves it, but the
      key to its success is that I wrote a comment on Google Research Blog, <a href="http://googleresearch.blogspot.com/2009/07/posted-by-hal-varian-chief-economist.html">the
      place</a> that inspired me to write in the first place. Just yesterday I
      got 26 visitors through that blog entry.</p>

      <p>That entry was also the one that took most time to write, followed by
      my text <a href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/07/commuting/">On being an
      international commuter</a> where the actual wordsmithing took an awful
      amount of time. Two people has told me that they thought it was funny.</p>

      <h2>Subject matters</h2>

      <p>I've mentioned earlier that I started all this by adding categories
      to all material that existed here before (mind you, this site is fifteen
      years old). I've hardly used any of them. Why should I. I'd rather not
      wright anything about harvesting or Z39.50. (I've done both the last
      three years, but these topics doesn't interest me anymore.)</p>

      <p>I suppose I should figure out a new system to categorize my material,
      but then why should I?</p>

      <h2>It does take time</h2>

      <p>All this writing takes time, and energy. I feel that I have to
      publish something every week. I mostly use the time I spend on train
      between Lund and Copenhagen, but I also use several hours on evenings
      and weekends on this. You cannot start a project which is time consuming
      without side effects. I read less novels and literature just for the fun
      of it. I've hardly touched my flute and <a href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/images/Degeberga_duo.shtml" title="me       and my son Erik cooking porridge while playing a polska">recorders</a>
      during this period.</p>

      <p>I've read somewhere that it takes about half a year to establish a
      blog, and I suppose that's about it. I won't write about web statistics
      until then.</p>


    </div>
    <p style="text-align: left;"><em><strong>Categories:</strong></em> 
	  <a href="/subjects/essays/">Essays</a><br/><em><strong>
		Permalink:
	      </strong></em><a rel="bookmark" href="/entries/2009/09/twelveweeks/">http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/09/twelveweeks/</a></p>
    <hr width="50%" align="center"/>
  </div>
  <div>
    <h1>Other, not yet obsolete stuff</h1>
    <table class="news">
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/08/diglib/"><em>The predigital library</em></a><br/>What is the strategic goal for a library web site? Could it be to
  put the library on the web, or is it basically to the library's resources
  visible to users anywhere on the globe?<br/><a href="/subjects/structuralwebdesign/">Structural web design</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/08/whatisabook/"><em>What is a book, and does it matter?</em></a><br/>Lorcan Dempsey of OCLC research, is involved in among lots of
  things, statistical analyses of media use. In that work they are forced to
  make operational definitions of the 'book'.<br/><a href="/subjects/essays/">Essays</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/media/">Media</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/08/threeyears/"><em>Five years that formed the digital library as we know it:
  1997-2001</em></a><br/>It appeared to me that many the standards and technologies
  underpinning the digital library as we know it were formed during five years
  around the turn of the century.<br/><a href="/subjects/metadata/">Metadata</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/08/quotations/"><em>A quotation is much more than an extract</em></a><br/>In my last entry, on cool URIs, I discussed the identification of
  documents. The conclusion from that is that people in the library world are
  obsessed by being able to find documents. I take that more serious than most
  other library folk. I'd say that it is our mission to help our patrons find
  a single word in a text, a rectangle in an image and so forth. The time is
  gone when we could tell users: The answer to your question might be in any
  of the books on that shelf.<br/><a href="/subjects/structuralwebdesign/">Structural web design</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/08/cooluris/"><em>Forgive me, Father, for I have sinned... I have moved a
  document</em></a><br/>The initiatives behind the persistent linking is trying to change
  the status of old documents. From 404 to 200. We've had some success with
  books and journals using ISBN and ISSN numbers. Why not try to copy this to
  the web? But, alas!, library people have in general too little understanding
  of the Worldwide Web. In particular those who advocate persistent
  identifiers.<br/><a href="/subjects/structuralwebdesign/">Structural web design</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/08/features/"><em>Changed URI for my feed, and a forum for discussions</em></a><br/>Having actively maintained my site for some, I've decided make a
  few changes...<br/><a href="/subjects/colophon/">Colophon</a></td>
      </tr>
    </table>
  </div>
</div>
