<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div>
    <h1 style="font-family: sans-serif; width: 55%; float: left;text-align: left;">Until death do us part -- an analysis of search statistics</h1>
    <p style="width: 38%; float: left;text-align: right">
      <em>
        <strong>
		Sigfrid Lundberg's Stuff,
	      2009-08-06</strong>
      </em>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div style="clear:both;"> </div>
  <div style="width:100%;">
    <div>

      <p>Hyunyoung Choi &amp; Hal Varian, Google Research, have
      claimed that it is possible to make <a href="http://googleresearch.blogspot.com/2009/07/posted-by-hal-varian-chief-economist.html">short
      term economic forcasts</a> using analysis of search terms entered into
      the Google search engine. In particular, they have shown that there is a
      positive correlation between the search interest for terms related to
      the filing for unemployment benefits. This has previously been shown to
      be a very good predictor of a future increase in unemployment.</p>

      <p>The search interest for terms in the <a href="http://www.google.com/insights/search/#cat=706&amp;geo=US&amp;cmpt=q">Welfare
      &amp; Unemployment category</a> appear to be a predictor of the number
      of people filing for benefits. I read these papers &amp; blog entries
      with great interest. These data are easily accessible. You retrieve them
      through a search form, and you can get them in CSV, so they can be
      loaded into your favorite statistics program via excel or any
      work-alike.</p>

      <div style="float: left; width: 50%; margin-left:0.5em;margin-right:0.5em;">
	<a href="/entries/2009/08/trends/kassa_series.png">
	  <img src="/entries/2009/08/trends/kassa_series.png" width="100%"/>
	</a>
	<p>
	  <small>Fig. 1. Time series for search interest for the Swedish term
	  "a kassa" (in red) and the corresponding Danish "a kasse" (in green)
	  with the same meaning.</small>
	</p>
      </div>

      <p>My idea was to track down effects of the recession on human life and
      people's interest. It is indeed easy to find such correlations. <a href="http://www.google.com/insights/search/#q=john%20maynard%20keynes&amp;cmpt=q">John
      Maynard Keynes</a> has experienced a formidable revival during the last
      six months or so. I had expected to see some shift in interest, where
      Karl Marx should gain Adam Smith would loose. <a href="http://www.google.com/insights/search/#q=Adam%20Smith%2CKarl%20Marx&amp;cmpt=q">I
      think that trend is real</a>.</p>

      <p>Having read Choi &amp; Varian's brilliant <a href="http://reseabrch.google.com/archive/papers/initialclaimsUS.pdf">little
      paper</a> (well, I'm neither economist nor statistician, but I think
      it's good), I just had to test this data source.</p>

      <h2>Cross country correlation</h2>

      <p>In Denmark and Sweden we have to become members in a unemployment
      benefit society, i.e., pay for an insurance policy against unemployment
      to get a sizeable unemployment allowance. There are a governmental dole
      as well, but that one is really so diminutive that it will hardly keep
      you from the street. Hence, we won't get benefit or allowance as some
      kind of charity from the other tax payers. You have pay in advance
      through your membership in an <strong>a kass<em>a</em></strong> in Sweden
      and an <strong>a kass<em>e</em></strong> in Denmark.</p>

      <div style="float: right; width: 50%; margin-left:0.5em;margin-right:0.5em;">
	<a href="/entries/2009/08/trends/kassa.png">
	  <img src="/entries/2009/08/trends/kassa.png" width="100%"/>
	</a>

	<p>
	  <small>Fig. 2. The search interest for the Danish search term 'a
	  kasse' (y axis) plotted against the corresponding Swedish 'a kassa'
	  the same week. The green line represent the least square fit. There
	  is quite some scatter but the positive correlation is highly
	  significant (n=177, t=4.252 and P&lt;0.00004, two-tailed).</small>
	</p>

      </div>

      <p>Now, these two words does not appear in any other language, and I can
      safely look up the <a href="http://www.google.com/insights/search/#q=a%20%20kassa%2Ca%20kasse&amp;cmpt=q">search
      interest</a> in Google Insight for Search and be fairly sure that these
      terms are not used anywhere else. The result is depicted in Fig. 1. Note
      that for a better part of 2004 one or both columns were zero. I've
      regarded those as missing values and removed them. The same was true for
      that were actually representing the future. I have plotted the data as
      delivered, and it seems to me that Google has to apply some kind
      smoothing such as a spline function.</p>

      <p>It seemed to me that major peaks appeared in both graphs in Fig. 1. T
      test for that I made a linear regressionn and correlation analysis. The
      correlation is indeed highly significant, which would indicate that
      Swedes and Danes start looking for an unemployment benefit society
      during the same periods. Makes sense to me.</p>

      <div style="float: left; width: 50%; margin-left:0.5em;margin-right:0.5em;">
	<a href="/entries/2009/08/trends/divorce-da-series.png">
	  <img src="/entries/2009/08/trends/divorce-da-series.png" width="100%"/>
	</a>
      </div>

      <div style="float: right; width: 50%; margin-left:0.5em;margin-right:0.5em;">
	<a href="/entries/2009/08/trends/divorce-da.png">
	  <img src="/entries/2009/08/trends/divorce-da.png" width="100%"/>
	</a>
      </div>

      <div style="float: left; width: 50%; margin-left:0.5em;margin-right:0.5em;">
	<a href="/entries/2009/08/trends/divorce-sv-series.png">
	  <img src="/entries/2009/08/trends/divorce-sv-series.png" width="100%"/> 
	</a>
      </div>

      <div style="float: right; width: 50%; margin-left:0.5em;margin-right:0.5em;">
	<a href="/entries/2009/08/trends/divorce-sv.png">
	  <img src="/entries/2009/08/trends/divorce-sv.png" width="100%"/> 
	</a>
      </div>

    </div>
    <p style="text-align: right">
      <em>
        <strong>
		Permalink:
	      </strong>
      </em>
      <a rel="bookmark" href="/entries/2009/08/trends/">http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/08/trends/</a>
    </p>
    <hr width="50%" align="center"/>
  </div>
  <div>
    <h1>Other, not yet obsolete stuff</h1>
    <table class="news">
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/07/blogging/"><em>What does Free mean for The Library</em></a><br/>Blogging is out, and the new trend is to tweet in
  Twitters. Syndication is out as well, since Google steals your content and
  you cannot make money on journalism. How can we survive when all media are
  free?<br/><a href="/subjects/media/">Media</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/thelibrary/">The Library</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/internet/">Internet</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/07/indexing_philosophy/"><em>Wagging the long tail</em></a><br/>The problem with providing an OK Amazoogle experience is that we
  might fail in providing advanced services to patrons that have special
  needs.<br/><a href="/subjects/opac/">Library catalogues</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/07/commuting/"><em>On being an international commuter</em></a><br/>The last four years I've spent more than two hours a day on
  trains. And usually, but not always less than three. Furthermore, I go from
  one nation to another and participate in the in the digital dissemination of
  cultural heritage of a country which isn't my own.<br/><a href="/subjects/essays/">Essays</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/07/xslt_extensions/"><em>Why I love XSLT extension functions</em></a><br/>xslt extensions allow you to define xpath functions and extension
  elements. That makes it easy for you to perform tasks within xslt that are
  just only theoretically possible to do.<br/><a href="/subjects/xmlprocessing/">XML processing</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/07/structure/"><em>The description and encoding of structure</em></a><br/>Much metadata is fairly stright forward. A book does have a title
  and an author. That's usually no big deal. We've been able to handle that
  for centuries. A digital book has chapters, and everything you might want to
  know may be in chapter two on page seventyfive. Or someone may tell you the
  solution to your problems after a quarter of an hour in some video on
  YouTube. Now, how do we cope with this?<br/><a href="/subjects/structuralwebdesign/">Structural web design</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/metadata/">Metadata</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/07/escience/"><em>Will the research libraries play a role in e-science</em></a><br/>I was asked to participate in an e-science pilot project.  The work
  in the project has been food for thought for me. Will libraries be a part of
  a future eScience infrastructure?<br/><a href="/subjects/escience/">eScience</a></td>
      </tr>
    </table>
  </div>
</div>
