<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div>
    <h1 style="font-family: sans-serif; width: 55%; float: left;text-align: left;">A phone for elderly hackers?</h1>
    <p style="width: 38%; float: left;text-align: right">
      <em>
        <strong>
		Sigfrid Lundberg's Stuff,
	      2010-05-05</strong>
      </em>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div style="clear:both;"> </div>
  <div style="width:100%;">
    <div>

      <p>I've been looking with envy on all people around with flashy smart
      phones. All these iPhones and Androids. My problem has been: Should I
      aquire a phone capable of computing or a computer capable of
      phoning.</p>

      <p>I'm an open source - open access kind of person. I just cannot buy
      any i* gadget. Apple's business model is clever, but I need a device I
      can understand. I've been UNIX man for more than twenty years and to buy
      something without a shell would be unthinkable. On the other hand I'm
      using my computer for the same reasons as every one else. I.e., mostly
      surfing and communication. Which would be the same as a mobile internet
      device (a MID).</p>

      <p>In spite of the fact that I had settled that my next phone should be
      an Android one, the fate wanted that I should run into Nokia N900. This
      gadget weighs more than twice as much as an iPhone but you i think you
      should compare it with an iPad rather than with a cell phone. It is
      actually easier to send an email than to make phone call.</p>

      <p>Nokia doesn't market the thing as a phone but as very mobile
      computer. Yes, I do know that iPad has a screen which is (perhaps) six
      times as large as the one on N900. But I have checked out my entire web
      site from my CVS repository and I'm able to run the entire rebuild
      machinery. This is a computer that allows creativity.</p>

      <p>I did try to install emacs and nxml mode but that wasn't trivial. The
      OS is called <a href="http://maemo.org/">Maemo</a>, which is a Debian
      based Linux maintained by a community sponsored by Nokia. The
      development is promising since Nokia and Intel are joining forces and
      are merging forces. Their respective mobile OSes will merge into <a href="http://meego.com/">Meego</a> maintained by Linux foundation.</p>

      <div style="float:right;width:60%;margin:0.5em;">
	<a href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2010/05/n900/20100504446.jpg" title="A phone for an old nerd?"><img src="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2010/05/n900/smaller20100504446.jpg" alt="A phone for an old nerd?"/></a>
	<p><small>The N900 is about as large as a state of the art smart
	phone, a bit larger when the keyboard is slid open. It is twice a
	thick as an iPhone, and when carried in your pocket it will
	bulge.</small></p>
      </div>


      <h3>Does it work?</h3>

      <p>Well. This is a very good little tablet computer.</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Web</li>
	<li>Mail using POP and IMAP</li>
	<li>SMS and other messaging</li>
	<li>Voice phoning using 3G and Skype</li>
	<li>Calendar</li>
	<li>Synchonizing with Outlook</li>
	<li>Wifi and mobile internet</li>
	<li>GPS and supporting software</li>
	<li>Camera and images with geodata</li>
	<li>And much more</li>
      </ul>

      <p>... just works. Sometimes things aren't really as intuitive as you
      wanted. Or, perhaps, the intuition of the designers were not the one you
      expected but that is common, isn't it?</p>

      <h3>A phone for an olde UNIX hacker</h3>


      <p>There's a lot of other software. OpenOffice.org is here and then
      there is the whole lot of UNIX utilities. I can plot my data using
      Gnuplot and edit perl script with VI.</p>

      <p>So what about the screen and keyboard?</p>

      <p>The buttons on this thing are smaller than on my phone. You operate
      with your thumbs, and it does work. The suite supplied by Nokia uses
      some clever T9 like algorithm for guessing what you're typing which
      minimises the typing.</p>

      <p>The thing will keep you connected 24/7. The thing has 3D graphics,
      and should you like a shoot'em: DOOM is ported!</p>

    </div>
    <br clear="all"/>
    <p style="text-align: left;"><em><strong>Categories:</strong></em> 
	  <a href="/subjects/hardware/">Hardware</a>,
	    <a href="/subjects/reviews/">Reviews</a><br/><em><strong>
		Permalink:
	      </strong></em><a rel="bookmark" href="/entries/2010/05/n900/">http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2010/05/n900/</a></p>
    <hr width="50%" align="center"/>
  </div>
  <div>
    <h1>Other, not yet obsolete stuff</h1>
    <table class="news">
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2010</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2010/04/atomlink/"><em>Atom contains all you need to annotate &amp; navigate</em></a><br/>Atom syndication format contains everything you need to build 
  good annotation and navigation systems<br/><a href="/subjects/digitalobjects/">Digital objects</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/xws/">XML web services</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2010</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2010/04/readings/"><em>Readings on digital objects: An annotated URIography</em></a><br/>I have a long list of articles to read on digital objects, how to
  model them etc. This page is for keeping track of my progress<br/><a href="/subjects/digitalcollections/">Digital collections</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/digitalobjects/">Digital objects</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2010</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2010/04/fedora/"><em>Fedora</em></a><br/>Carl Lagoze, Sandy Payette, Edwin Shin and Chris Wilper,
  2005. Fedora: an architecture for complex objects and their
  relationships<br/><a href="/subjects/metadataprocessing/">Metadata processing</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/digitalobjects/">Digital objects</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2010</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2010/04/thinkerinthespring/"><em>Holberg, the Thinker and the Tulips</em></a><br/>Two statues, one in Copenhagen and one in Bergen<br/><a href="/subjects/images/">Images</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2010</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2010/04/extractive/"><em>Does hypertext promote extractive interaction rather than
  immersive?</em></a><br/>Extractive and immersive are two forms of interactivity. This note
  claims that the digital library services have successfully implemented
  facilities for extractive media consumption but that it is very difficult to
  help users in the immersive pattern.<br/><a href="/subjects/essays/">Essays</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2010</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2010/04/gstupid/"><em>Is Google Making us Stupid?</em></a><br/>Having had a web site for about 15 years, I start to wonder why I
  keep it in the first place.<br/><a href="/subjects/digitalobjects/">Digital objects</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/internet/">Internet</a></td>
      </tr>
    </table>
  </div>
</div>
