<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div>
    <h1 style="width: 58%; float: left;text-align: leftt">Wagging the long tail</h1>
    <p style="width: 38%; float: left;text-align: right">
      <em>
        <strong>
		Sigfrid Lundberg's Stuff,
	      2009-07-29</strong>
      </em>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div style="clear:both;"> </div>
  <div style="width:100%;">
    <div>

      <p>By and large we in the library world have, finally, accepted the
      reality. We do no longer regard the online catalogue's poor usability as
      an <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Information_literacy">information
      literacy problem</a>. As such, there was a remedy: User education. The
      roots of education are bitter, but the fruit is sweet. The path towards
      mastering the online catalogue is like a very long session in the
      gym. You feel better the day after tomorrow.</p>

      <p>After (rougly) 2003, there was a general acceptance that the our
      patrons deserved an easier to use interface, and the concept of the
      integrated library system was born. The <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_next-generation_catalogs">new
      kind of system</a> should be so easy to use that new generations used to
      <a href="http://orweblog.oclc.org/archives/000562.html">Amazoogle and
      Googlezon</a> should not be frustrated by the complications of the
      typical scanlists generated by the library opac upon the entering of a
      long and complicated query in <a href="http://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Common_Command_Language">CCL</a>.</p>

      <p>The user preferences have been known for a long time. For instance,
      all users of the <a href="http://www.tbray.org/ongoing/When/200x/2003/06/17/SearchUsers">Open
      Text search engine</a> used the simple form, except those that
      didn't. They used the advanced one, and they amounted to about 0.5% of
      the grand total. Such users belong to the tip of some <a href="http://www.thelongtail.com/">long tail</a>, and they do know what
      they want to know, but knowing that might not help if we cannot
      deliver.</p>

      <p>I heard a story from a librarian at The Royal Library. A student
      appeared at the information desk at one of our reading rooms requesting
      a list of contemporary Japanese literature translated into Danish for
      some paper in translation studies. Our nice ILS <a href="http://www.exlibrisgroup.com/category/PrimoOverview">Primo</a>
      provides an OK Amazoogle experience. But, well... An user hostile
      boolean fielded search in the rusty old OPAC did the job.</p>

      <p>The good news is that the advanced search form is much cheaper to
      build than simple one. That one is still the real challange. Even for
      Google.</p>

    </div>
    <p style="text-align: right">
      <em>
        <strong>
		Permalink:
	      </strong>
      </em>
      <a rel="bookmark" href="/entries/2009/07/indexing_philosophy/">http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/07/indexing_philosophy/</a>
    </p>
    <hr width="50%" align="center"/>
  </div>
  <div>
    <h1>Other, not yet obsolete stuff</h1>
    <table class="news">
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/07/commuting/"><em>On being an international commuter</em></a><br/>The last four years I've spent more than two hours a day on
  trains. And usually, but not always less than three. Furthermore, I go from
  one nation to another and participate in the in the digital dissemination of
  cultural heritage of a country which isn't my own.<br/><a href="/subjects/essays/">Essays</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/07/xslt_extensions/"><em>Why I love XSLT extension functions</em></a><br/>xslt extensions allow you to define xpath functions and extension
  elements. That makes it easy for you to perform tasks within xslt that are
  just only theoretically possible to do.<br/><a href="/subjects/xmlprocessing/">XML processing</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/07/structure/"><em>The description and encoding of structure</em></a><br/>Much metadata is fairly stright forward. A book does have a title
  and an author. That's usually no big deal. We've been able to handle that
  for centuries. A digital book has chapters, and everything you might want to
  know may be in chapter two on page seventyfive. Or someone may tell you the
  solution to your problems after a quarter of an hour in some video on
  YouTube. Now, how do we cope with this?<br/><a href="/subjects/structuralwebdesign/">Structural web design</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/metadata/">Metadata</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/07/escience/"><em>Will the research libraries play a role in e-science</em></a><br/>I was asked to participate in an e-science pilot project.  The work
  in the project has been food for thought for me. Will libraries be a part of
  a future eScience infrastructure?<br/><a href="/subjects/escience/">eScience</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/07/victory/"><em>The predator rests on its prey</em></a><br/>I've seen this image before. An excavator has demolished a
  building, and has then proudly been parked on top of the remnants.<br/><a href="/subjects/essays/">Essays</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/07/technorati/"><em>This is a dummy entry for technorati</em></a><br/>uw5m38jba7
  <br/><a href="/subjects/structuralwebdesign/">Structural web design</a></td>
      </tr>
    </table>
  </div>
</div>
