<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div>
    <h1 style="width: 58%; float: left;text-align: leftt">On being an international commuter</h1>
    <p style="width: 38%; float: left;text-align: right">
      <em>
        <strong>
		Sigfrid Lundberg's Stuff,
	      2009-07-21</strong>
      </em>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div style="clear:both;"> </div>
  <div style="width:100%;">
    <div>

      <p>In both Lund and Copenhagen there are a lot of people riding
      bicycles. They behave very differently, however, and their spatial
      distribution is different. In Copenhagen the riders have a much more
      aggregated distribution. They ride at high speed in squadrons, somewhat
      like Mongolian cavalry. Before their mounted attacks against the
      pedestrians on H.C. Andersens Boulevard, their prime target, the
      Copenhagen bicycle riders congregate at traffic lights.</p>

      <p>In Lund, where the where the traffic lights are more scarce, there
      are few natural meeting points. In Lund bicycle riders operate in much
      smaller units, or solitarily. Great speed and bravery is nevertheless
      needed, as Lund's bicycle riders are well known for their suicidal
      attacks upon four-wheeled vehicles.</p>

      <p>Currently I usually leave home and mount my bike ten past seven in
      the morning. That gives me ample time to catch the 07.39 train from
      Lund to Copenhagen. Except for occasional encounters with dog owners and
      an increasing number of power walking young ladies the trip is
      uneventful. The power walkers stride along in a frenzy, their eyes fixed
      at a point on the horizon. Neither their faces nor their eyes reveal any
      emotion whatsoever, other than utter dislike for walking. I honestly
      believe that they are all in a terrible hurry home for a shower and a
      nice slow breakfast. What else could it be? They are completely absent
      when I return home in the afternoon. Or when it's raining.</p>

      <h2>A parking place</h2>

      <img src="/galleri/200907-200907/smaller/cimg1352.jpg" style="margin-left:0.5em;float:left;margin-right:0.5em;" alt="Secure locking is essential"/>

      <p>I have one serious problem. That is to find a secure parking place
      for my bike at the railway station. A lot of people who park there have
      lost their vehicles. The rumour tells stories about thieves coming there
      with lorries, stealing bicycles for export to Poland. I've recently
      acquired a new bike, since my previous one was stolen. But that was
      outside our home. Apart from finding the parking place, the first
      temporal bottle-neck is to lock the thing. I've got two solid locks, and
      try to park where I can use one of them for locking the bike to the iron
      structure provided by the local council for the benefit for of paranoid
      bicycle owners (see the image). They are always taken before I get
      one.</p>

      <p>That would describe the normal sequence of events, but right now they
      replacing 12 kilometers of tracks. Hence the railway which is normally
      double track is now running on half its normal capacity. I could dwell
      on the inconveniences caused by this, but I'll spare you that pain. The
      normal state of affairs is that I after about an hour on the
      train. Right now it's more often one and a half.</p>

      <h2>Two cultures</h2>

      <p>Swedes &amp; Danes are cousins. Both tribes are viking
      grandchildren. So are off course the Icelanders and Norwegians, but it
      is only the Icelanders who have kept their old language. The rest of us
      has diverged, but still there has been some force that has kept us
      together linguistically as well as culturally. I've been told that
      people from Algeria cannot talk to people from Egypt, in spite of the
      fact that they all speak Arabic. Now, I speak Swedish and my colleagues
      all speak Danish. And we can all laugh at a good joke.</p>

      <p>Many Danes think of us Swedes as being more formalistic, moralistic
      and prone to bureaucracy than Danes. In Sweden everything that make life
      worth living, such as tobacco and alcohol, either prohibited or somehow
      controlled by the government</p>

      <h2>Working in Denmark</h2>

      <p>The Royal Library has in total an excess of five hundred
      employees. About a handful of them are Swedes. There are about 30000
      people commuting this way, so we have perhaps a representative proportion
      of Swedes.</p>

      <p>All Swedish commuters I've talked to about the cultural differences
      between Danes and Swedes tell a story which is quite the opposite from
      the Danish self image. All Swedes who have no longer experience with
      working in Denmark actually believe that this is the case.</p>

      <p>I won't say that there are no problems, but none we can't live
      with. One thing which is a problem, and that is writing. My written
      Danish is a joke, like the speech of the Swedish chef in the Muppet
      show. Collaborative writing is worst, since that forces colleagues
      translation. I usually write documentation in English, and everything
      else in Swedish. Both will be understood.</p>


      
    </div>
    <p style="text-align: right">
      <em>
        <strong>
		Permalink:
	      </strong>
      </em>
      <a rel="bookmark" href="/entries/2009/07/commuting/">http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/07/commuting/</a>
    </p>
    <hr width="50%" align="center"/>
  </div>
  <div>
    <h1>Other, not yet obsolete stuff</h1>
    <table class="news">
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/07/xslt_extensions/"><em>Why I love XSLT extension functions</em></a><br/>xslt extensions allow you to define xpath functions and extension
  elements. That makes it easy for you to perform tasks within xslt that are
  just only theoretically possible to do.<br/><a href="/subjects/xmlprocessing/">XML processing</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/07/structure/"><em>The description and encoding of structure</em></a><br/>Much metadata is fairly stright forward. A book does have a title
  and an author. That's usually no big deal. We've been able to handle that
  for centuries. A digital book has chapters, and everything you might want to
  know may be in chapter two on page seventyfive. Or someone may tell you the
  solution to your problems after a quarter of an hour in some video on
  YouTube. Now, how do we cope with this?<br/><a href="/subjects/structuralwebdesign/">Structural web design</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/metadata/">Metadata</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/07/escience/"><em>Will the research libraries play a role in e-science</em></a><br/>I was asked to participate in an e-science pilot project.  The work
  in the project has been food for thought for me. Will libraries be a part of
  a future eScience infrastructure?<br/><a href="/subjects/escience/">eScience</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/07/victory/"><em>The predator rests on its prey</em></a><br/>I've seen this image before. An excavator has demolished a
  building, and has then proudly been parked on top of the remnants.<br/><a href="/subjects/essays/">Essays</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/07/technorati/"><em>This is a dummy entry for technorati</em></a><br/>uw5m38jba7
  <br/><a href="/subjects/structuralwebdesign/">Structural web design</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/07/client_side_xslt/"><em>XML on the web, Client Side XSLT and Google</em></a><br/>The market has forced the major browser manufacturers to converge
  on standards. But why are the search engines lagging behind? Browsers are
  capable of AJAX and advanced XML processing, but the search engines are
  still basically just removing tags and presenting raw text extracts.<br/><a href="/subjects/structuralwebdesign/">Structural web design</a></td>
      </tr>
    </table>
  </div>
</div>
