<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div>
    <h1 style="font-family: sans-serif; width: 55%; float: left;text-align: left;">George Smiley and libraries</h1>
    <p style="width: 38%; float: left;text-align: right">
      <em>
        <strong>
		Sigfrid Lundberg's Stuff,
	      2010-04-02</strong>
      </em>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div style="clear:both;"> </div>
  <div style="width:100%;">
    <div>
      <p>Year 1986 is special since it is the year I spent as a PosDoc year in
      London. During that year I ran into John le Carré's books. Some of my
      spare time, quite a few weekends actually, I spent as a literary tourist
      in London.</p>

      <p>I bought and read a handful of le Carré's books.
      In particular, those about the old spy master <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Smiley">George Smiley</a> and
      of those, it is in particular the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Smiley#The_Karla_trilogy">The
      Karla Trilogy</a> I like the most. George Smiley is an academic,
      germanist and a spy. During the thirties he had operated under cover in
      Germany and during the World War II he ran networks in Germany, Sweden
      and Switzerland. If you are to believe the Wikipedia article about
      him. I've just recently had a very nice time enjoying <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/radio4/features/smiley-season/">BBC's Smiley
      Season</a> and rereading <em>The Secret Pilgrim</em>.  </p>

      <p>The trilogy consists of <em><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tinker,_Tailor,_Soldier,_Spy">Tinker
      Tailor Soldier Spy</a></em> (1974) which tells the story on how Smiley
      tracks down a Soviet mole inside British intelligence, 

      <em><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Honourable_Schoolboy">The
      Honourable Schoolboy</a></em> (1977) on how he restores the "Circus" to
      something that looks like an intelligence service

      and finally <em><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Smiley%27s_People">Smiley's
      People</a></em> (1979) on how he finally forces his old Soviet adversary
      with code name Karla to defect.</p>

      <div style="float:right;width:40%;margin-left:0.5em;margin-right:0.5em;">
	<a href="http://www.londonlibrary.co.uk/press/General%20library%20images.htm" title="The reading room at the London Library">

	  <img src="http://www.londonlibrary.co.uk/press/photos/General%20library%20images/picture-005.jpg" width="100%" alt="The reading room at the London Library"/>
	</a>
	<p><small>The reading room at the London Library. It is hard to tell
	whether the window is a sash-window, or if there are trees
	outside.</small></p>
      </div>

      <p>The first and the last of the three books have in common that George
      is called in from his retirement. An important part of Smiley's
      character is his involvement in various scholarly pursuits, like the
      writing of a monograph about the bard Opitz.  In <em>Smiley's
      people</em> George</p>

      <blockquote>
	[...] <em>was toiling obliviously, with whatever conviction he could
	muster, at his habitual desk in the London Library in St James's
	Square, with two spindly trees to look at through the sash-window of
	the reading room [...] for at the time he was writing a monograph on
	the bard Opitz and trying loyally to distinguish true passion from the
	literary convention of the period.</em><sup><a href="#londonlib">1</a></sup>
      </blockquote>

      <p>Passion is not a characteristic of George, but his work requires not
      only borrowed books, but also scholarly journals, and the library
      reminds him of expired loans:</p>

      <blockquote>
	<em>What was due?</em> German Life and Letters? Philology? Philology
	<em>he decided; it was already overdue. Putting on the hall light he
	stooped and peered through his post.</em><sup><a href="#whatisdue">2</a></sup>
      </blockquote>

      <p>From what I can tell from the <a href="http://lms3.londonlibrary.co.uk/F">London Library's catalogue</a>,
      it has <em>German Life and Letters</em> in its holdings since 1936, but
      not any journal called <em>Philology</em> there.</p>

      <p>The London Library is an UK Registered Charity and a <a href="http://www.londonlibrary.co.uk/join/individualmembership.htm">membership
      lending library</a>. The staff where at the time were not particularly
      interested in showing the reading room for literary tourists. I think
      that <a href="http://www.londonlibrary.co.uk/visit/index.htm">may have
      changed somewhat</a>. Some day I will go to London visit the London
      Library and look through the window in the reading room. Maybe there are
      still two trees outside the sash-window. I suppose that they must have
      grown since the seventies, though.</p>

      <h3>Notes</h3>

      <p>You need to be logged in to Amazon to look inside these books.</p>

      <ol>
	<li id="londonlib">le Carré, John, 1979. <em>Smiley's People</em> <a href="http://www.amazon.com/s/ref=nb_sb_noss?url=search-alias%3Daps&amp;field-keywords=with+two+spindly+trees+to+look+at+through+the+sash-window+of+the+reading+room&amp;x=0&amp;y=0">Amazon</a></li>

	<li id="whatisdue">le Carré, John, 1974. <em>Tinker, Tailor, Soldier, Spy</em> <a href="http://www.amazon.com/s/ref=nb_sb_noss?url=search-alias%3Daps&amp;field-keywords=Putting+on+the+hall+light+he+stooped+and+peered+through+his+post&amp;x=0&amp;y=0">Amazon</a></li>

      </ol>

    </div>
    <br clear="all"/>
    <p style="text-align: left;"><em><strong>Categories:</strong></em> 
	  <a href="/subjects/essays/">Essays</a>,
	    <a href="/subjects/musiclanglit/">Music, language &amp; literature</a><br/><em><strong>
		Permalink:
	      </strong></em><a rel="bookmark" href="/entries/2010/04/smiley/">http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2010/04/smiley/</a></p>
    <hr width="50%" align="center"/>
  </div>
  <div>
    <h1>Other, not yet obsolete stuff</h1>
    <table class="news">
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2010</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2010/03/teimime/"><em>application/tei+xml</em></a><br/>We are about to register a mime type for TEI. This page tracks the
  progress of that effort<br/><a href="/subjects/internet/">Internet</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2010</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2010/03/appteixml/"><em>A new line in the list</em></a><br/>I've spent half of this week writing an Internet draft<br/><a href="/subjects/internet/">Internet</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2010</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2010/03/syndication/"><em>The syndication of style &amp; layout</em></a><br/>Quite a few and perhaps a majority of my readers seldom visits my
  site. This entry is about the problems of syndication and how you are
  limited by the styling and layout on the site where your material is
  presented.<br/><a href="/subjects/structuralwebdesign/">Structural web design</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2010</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2010/03/stanford/"><em>Stanford</em></a><br/>I've never been to California before. Now I'm here late in March
  after an unusually harsh Scandinavian winter<br/><a href="/subjects/images/">Images</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2010</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2010/03/xslt_indexer/"><em>On indexing of XML using XSLT</em></a><br/>One of my really deep interests is the indexing of complex XML
  content. Please find here the home page of one my software projects,
  xslt_indexer<br/><a href="/subjects/xmlprocessing/">XML Processing</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2010</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2010/03/pilin/"><em>Modelling identifers?</em></a><br/>Nick Nicholas, Nigel Ward and Kerry Blinco helps obscuring the
  digital identifiers concept<br/><a href="/subjects/structuralwebdesign/">Structural web design</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/internet/">Internet</a></td>
      </tr>
    </table>
  </div>
</div>
