<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div>
    <h1 style="font-family: sans-serif; width: 55%; float: left;text-align: left;">Idempotency and HTTP methods</h1>
    <p style="width: 38%; float: left;text-align: right">
      <em>
        <strong>
		Sigfrid Lundberg's Stuff,
	      2010-03-12</strong>
      </em>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div style="clear:both;"> </div>
  <div style="width:100%;">
    <div>

      <p>I've been working with the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Representational_State_Transfer">REST
      paradigm for years</a>. Or that is what I've claimed. But really, what
      I've been delivering is really GETful web services. These are services
      delivering all services using GET-requests, which good if you're
      actually just delivering content. But REST the architecture behind the
      IT revolution. And central in the WWW is HTTP and there in the midst
      you'll find the HTTP methods.</p>

      <div style="float:right;width:33%;margin-left:0.5em;margin-right:0.5em;margin-bottom:0.5em;">
	<table style="width:100%;">
	  <caption>Tab. 1. The methods defined in HTTP 1.1. Safe methods
	  should not take any other action than retrieval. An idempotent
	  method is one that has the same side effects if it is applied
	  <em>n</em> times (<em>n</em>&gt;0), as when it it is applied
	  once.</caption>

	  <tr>
	    <th>Method</th>
	    <th>safe</th>
	    <th>idempotent</th>
	  </tr>

	  <tr>
	    <td>HEAD</td>
	    <td>Yes</td>
	    <td>Yes</td>
	  </tr>

	  <tr>
	    <td>GET</td>
	    <td>Yes</td>
	    <td>Yes</td>
	  </tr>

	  <tr>
	    <td>DELETE</td>
	    <td>Yes</td>
	    <td>No</td>
	  </tr>

	  <tr>
	    <td>PUT</td>
	    <td>No</td>
	    <td>Yes</td>
	  </tr>

	  <tr>
	    <td>POST</td>
	    <td>No</td>
	    <td>No</td>
	  </tr>

	  <tr>
	    <td>TRACE</td>
	    <td/>
	    <td/>
	  </tr>

	  <tr>
	    <td>OPTIONS</td>
	    <td/>
	    <td/>
	  </tr>

	</table>
      </div>

      <p>You can do a lot using REST and the set of <a href="http://www.w3.org/Protocols/rfc2616/rfc2616-sec9.html">methods
      defined for HTTP 1.1</a>. I've put the method in Tab. 1. I'd like to
      dwell on the idempotency concept as applied to computing. I <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Idempotence#In_computing">quote
      directly from Wikipedia</a>:</p>

      <blockquote style="font-style:italic;">
	<p style="margin-left:+5%;">In computer science, the term idempotent
	is used to describe methods or subroutine calls that can safely be
	called multiple times, as invoking the procedure a single time or
	multiple times has the same result; i.e., after any number of method
	calls all variables have the same value as they did after the first
	call.</p>


	<p style="margin-left:+5%;">This is a very useful property in many
	situations: It means that an operation can be repeated or retried as
	often as necessary without causing unintended effects. If the
	operation were non-idempotent, it would be necessary to keep track of
	whether it was already performed or not, which complicates many
	algorithms.</p>
      </blockquote>

      <p>Let us make the <a href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/science/blog/2009/aug/14/hans-christian-rsted-birthday">gedanken
      experiment</a> that the retrieval methods, GET and HEAD, in HTTP where
      <strong>not idempotent in exactly this sense</strong>. Lean back, close
      your eyes and meditate over the problem: <em>Which sequence of pages
      would be necessary to retrieve <strong>today</strong> in order to get
      the original <a href="http://www.nature.com/nature/dna50/watsoncrick.pdf">DNA</a>
      structure.</em></p>

      <p>To put it in another way: Idempotency is the feature of HTTP ensuring
      that you receive predictable content when you dereference an URI, rather
      than a my personalized version of, say, Watson &amp; Crick.</p>

    </div>
    <br clear="all"/>
    <p style="text-align: left;"><em><strong>Categories:</strong></em> 
	  <a href="/subjects/internet/">Internet</a><br/><em><strong>
		Permalink:
	      </strong></em><a rel="bookmark" href="/entries/2010/03/modactions/">http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2010/03/modactions/</a></p>
    <hr width="50%" align="center"/>
  </div>
  <div>
    <h1>Other, not yet obsolete stuff</h1>
    <table class="news">
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2010</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2010/03/chemistry/"><em>Drugs and OpenAccess</em></a><br/>In a recent article Theresa Velden &amp; Carl Lagoze (Communicating
  chemistry, Nature Chemistry 1, 673-678 (2009)) discusses how tradition and
  attitudes concerning IPR affect data sharing and how that in turn affects
  scientists propensities to use web 2.0 tools and web of data
  technologies.<br/><a href="/subjects/escience/">eScience</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2010</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2010/03/thinking/"><em>Thinking when the spring is approaching</em></a><br/>Winter is just the worst part of the year. Where approaching the
  end of it.<br/><a href="/subjects/essays/">Essays</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/images/">Images</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2010</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2010/03/solarenergy/"><em>Solar energy</em></a><br/>White reflects radiation from the sun to a larger degree than do
  other colours<br/><a href="/subjects/images/">Images</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2010</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2010/03/bash/"><em>Bourne Again Shell</em></a><br/>The Bourne Again Shell is a prominent part of my life. Dark moments
  I've felt that I'm obsoleted by modern technologies, but all of a sudden I
  realised that I'm as modern as smarphone users<br/><a href="/subjects/images/">Images</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2010</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2010/03/aformwithajoin/"><em>A form with a join</em></a><br/>A form is a document, or part of one, that can be used for the
  entry of data. A join is a construct in query languages such SQL. A join
  allows you to lookup data in one part of a database based on a query in an
  other part. Joins are very general, and may appear in other contexts. Such
  as the XML forms language.<br/><a href="/subjects/xmlprocessing/">XML processing</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/metadataprocessing/">Metadata processing</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2010</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2010/02/youdontneed/"><em>Why you need a persistence strategy</em></a><br/>Here I go through some of the arguments why you need to implement a
  persistence strategy. We also conclude that the hypertext link is the single
  thing that makes the Worldwide web to a web. Hence it is a serious thing. If
  you're working within the digital library world you should be devoted to the
  hypertext link.<br/><a href="/subjects/structuralwebdesign/">Structural web design</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/internet/">Internet</a></td>
      </tr>
    </table>
  </div>
</div>
