<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div>
    <h1 style="width: 58%; float: left;text-align: leftt">This is a dummy entry for technorati</h1>
    <p style="width: 38%; float: left;text-align: right">
      <em>
        <strong>
		Sigfrid Lundberg's Stuff,
	      2009-07-13</strong>
      </em>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div style="clear:both;"> </div>
  <div style="width:100%;">
    <div>
uw5m38jba7
    </div>
    <p style="text-align: right">
      <em>
        <strong>
		Permalink:
	      </strong>
      </em>
      <a rel="bookmark" href="/entries/2009/07/technorati/">http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/07/technorati/</a>
    </p>
    <hr width="50%" align="center"/>
  </div>
  <div>
    <h1>Other, not yet obsolete stuff</h1>
    <table class="news">
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/07/victory/"><em>The predator rests on its prey</em></a><br/>I've seen this image before. An excavator has demolished a
  building, and has then proudly been parked on top of the remnants.<br/><a href="/subjects/essays/">Essays</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/07/client_side_xslt/"><em>XML on the web, Client Side XSLT and Google</em></a><br/>The market has forced the major browser manufacturers to converge
  on standards. But why are the search engines lagging behind? Browsers are
  capable of AJAX and advanced XML processing, but the search engines are
  still basically just removing tags and presenting raw text extracts.<br/><a href="/subjects/structuralwebdesign/">Structural web design</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/07/opml/"><em>OpenSearch, RSS and OPML as XML Webservices for information
  retrieval</em></a><br/>At the Royal Library we have been working with the building of an
  infrastructure for publishing of digitized material. It is collections of
  digital images, usually with very little textual content to go with it. It
  is quite a challenge to build workflows satisfying the needs of technical
  staff running the scanners, the librararian and editorial staff doing the
  cataloging and the needs for crosswalking metadata from the OPAC and at the
  same time be able to syndicate the material in other services adhering to
  different standards.<br/><a href="/subjects/xmlprocessing/">XML processing</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/colophon/">Colophon</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/07/colophon/"><em>About this site</em></a><br/>I'm a terrible nerd. To use software like content management
  systems or blog software is unthinkable for me. There are many ways to build
  a site like this. I have chosen one that maximizes the use of angle
  brackets.<br/><a href="/subjects/structuralwebdesign/">Structural web design</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/colophon/">Colophon</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/06/mor/"><em>Min mor</em></a><br/>Min mor var 43 år gammal när hon födde mig 1956. Alltså föddes hon
  själv 1913, året innan första världskriget bröt ut. Nu är hon 96, och lever,
  som hon säger, på lånad tid. Tid, det är något som hon tar på största
  allvar. Vi talas vid per telefon varje dag. Hon ringer 20.10, nästan
  exakt. Det blir alltid ett trevligt samtal.<br/><a href="/subjects/essays/">Essays</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/06/atom/"><em>My first serious experience with ATOM</em></a><br/>You don't really understand a document format until you've manually
  encoded some documents, and written the software to parse and use it for
  something useful. This somewhat refurbished version of my web site is to a
  large extent built upon the ATOM syndication format, and here I discuss my
  experience.<br/><a href="/subjects/structuralwebdesign/">Structural web design</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/metadata/">Metadata</a></td>
      </tr>
    </table>
  </div>
</div>
