<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div>
    <h1 style="width: 58%; float: left;text-align: leftt">OpenSearch, RSS and OPML as XML Webservices for information
  retrieval</h1>
    <p style="width: 38%; float: left;text-align: right">
      <em>
        <strong>
		Sigfrid Lundberg's Stuff,
	      2009-07-09</strong>
      </em>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div style="clear:both;"> </div>
  <div style="width:100%;">
    <div>

      <p>At the <a href="http://www.kb.dk/">Royal Library</a> we have been
      working with the building of an infrastructure for publishing of
      digitized material. It is collections of digital images, usually with
      very little textual content to go with it.</p>

      <p>The cataloging of the images has been made by library staff using the
      image datase system Cumulus from <a ref="http://www.canto.com/">Canto</a>.  Cumulus is designed as digital
      asset management system for people within graphical industry. Canto is
      producing an advanced Web user interface, but it is rather poor as
      regards dissemination of the collections on the web. For example, images
      published that way never ever appear in Google Images. Syndication of
      our content has not been possible, since the system have been lacking
      any concept of standardized metadata, which is essential for all
      collaboration between institions in the library communities.</p>

    
      <div style="float: left;margin-left:5px;margin-right:5px;">
	<div style="height:350px;width:300px;">
	  <a href="http://static.grazr.com/gzpanel.html?view=s&amp;file=http://www.kb.dk/opml_category_service/danmarksbilleder/?opml_mode=shallow&amp;subject=8">
	    <img alt="Grazr" src="http://static.grazr.com/images/grazrbadge.png" style="border:none"/>
	  </a>
	  <script defer="defer" type="text/javascript" src="http://static.grazr.com/gzloader.js?view=s&amp;file=http://www.kb.dk/opml_category_service/danmarksbilleder/?opml_mode=shallow&amp;subject=8">
	  </script>
	</div>
      </div>

      <p>To take advantage of the relative ease of use for the people handling
      the images, but still be able to provide access to our collections on
      the Internet we have an entirely new web interface. For performace
      reasons, we decided that it should <em>not</em> access the cumulus
      database directly, but a mirror in our Oracle db. Furthermore we wanted
      a REST XML web service layer.</p>

      <p>The latter goal was achieved by using two syndication services, built
      on top of Oracle. The two services were written as JAVA servlets, and
      supported Outline Processor Markup Language (<a href="http://www.opml.org/">OPML</a>) and <a href="http://www.opensearch.org">OpenSearch</a>, together with RSS. The
      rationale for the latter choice of standard was that we wanted
      mainstream Internet Standards rather than typical library standards such
      as <a href="http://www.loc.gov/standards/sru/">SRU</a>. OpenSearch is
      promoted by <a href="http://a9.com">A9</a>, a subsidiary of <a href="http://www.amazon.com">Amazon</a> and there are at least pledges
      of support from other big players such as Google and Yahoo.</p>

      <p>OPML was not an as obvious choice. However, OpenSearch is basically a
      Syndication protocol and as such OPML is a candidate since its most
      common usage is to provide subject structured access to feeds. An early
      version of the system is available on our web site, the first version
      was released for about a year ago. Our technology choices makes it
      stright forward to syndicate the content. The gadget on this page is an
      example of this. It is a gadget showing the OPML and RSS from the first
      collection of images released in this way, <a href="http://www.kb.dk/images/billed/2008/maj/danmarksbilleder/">Danmarksbilleder</a>,
      a collection of historical images from a few Danish cities. The widget
      itself is "The Original Feed Widget" a nifty thing coming from <a href="http://grazr.com">grazr.com</a>. You can make one of your own by
      filling in the URI <a href="http://www.kb.dk/opml_category_service/danmarksbilleder/?opml_mode=shallow&amp;subject=8">http://www.kb.dk/opml_category_service/danmarksbilleder/?opml_mode=shallow&amp;subject=8</a>
      in the form on grazr.com.</p>

      <p>The use of truly simple de facto Internet standards is one
      advantage. But we needed a way to build traditional web contents on top
      of our two web services. Sites as <a href="http://www.kb.dk/images/billed/2008/maj/danmarksbilleder/">Danmarksbilleder</a>
      mentioned above, and its "cousins" <a href="http://www.kb.dk/images/billed/2008/sep/kistebilleder/">Kistebilleder</a>,
      <a href="http://www.kb.dk/images/billed/2008/sep/daellsvarehus/">Daells
      varehus</a> and <a href="http://www.kb.dk/images/billed/2008/sep/partiprogrammer/">Partiprogrammer</a>. All
      these are actually deliverd by one single servlet, which is most
      appropriately described as a mashup-engine.</p>

      <p>The engine is written in-house, and supports multiple skins (as seen
      in the examples above -- <a href="http://www.kb.dk/images/billed/2008/maj/danmarksbilleder/">Danmarksbilleder</a> differs from <a href="http://www.kb.dk/images/billed/2008/sep/kistebilleder/">Kistebilleder</a>).</p>

      <p>In this application a skin is a XML document consisting of the
      framework for the html page. Appart from html tags it also contain
      &lt;kb:include/&gt; tags identified by they id attribute. Each
      kb:include tag corresponds to a REST XML web service and is connected to
      a XSLT script via configuration file. The mashup engine reads the skin
      at initialization, and upon a request it retrieves the required OPML or
      RSS, transforms the content, pastes these fragments into the
      skin DOM tree and finally delivers the content to the client.</p>

      <p>The mashup engine is not very well written. I can do better. Also the
      current set of services requires an Oracle schema per application which
      is wasteful. We've haven't got the time yet to fix the first problem,
      but the second problem is about to be solved since we have a second
      generation of web services in the pipe-line for release real soon. In
      this application we've just one single Oracle database for all editions
      served. I will give you a report on that one when it is online.</p>


    </div>
    <p style="text-align: right">
      <em>
        <strong>
		Permalink:
	      </strong>
      </em>
      <a href="/entries/2009/07/opml/">http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/07/opml/</a>
    </p>
    <hr width="50%" align="center"/>
  </div>
  <div>
    <h1>Other, not yet obsolete stuff</h1>
    <table class="news">
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/07/colophon/"><em>About this site</em></a><br/>I'm a terrible nerd. To use software like content management
  systems or blog software is unthinkable for me. There are many ways to build
  a site like this. I have chosen one that maximizes the use of angle
  brackets.<br/><a href="/subjects/structuralwebdesign/">Structural web design</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/colophon/">Colophon</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/07/technorati/"><em>technorati verification</em></a><br/>A dummy entry<br/><a href="/subjects/structuralwebdesign/">Structural web design</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/06/mor/"><em>Min mor</em></a><br/>Min mor var 43 år gammal när hon födde mig 1956. Alltså föddes hon
  själv 1913, året innan första världskriget bröt ut. Nu är hon 96, och lever,
  som hon säger, på lånad tid. Tid, det är något som hon tar på största
  allvar. Vi talas vid per telefon varje dag. Hon ringer 20.10, nästan
  exakt. Det blir alltid ett trevligt samtal.<br/><a href="/subjects/essays/">Essays</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/06/atom/"><em>My first serious experience with ATOM</em></a><br/>You don't really understand a document format until you've manually
  encoded some documents, and written the software to parse and use it for
  something useful. This somewhat refurbished version of my web site is to a
  large extent built upon the ATOM syndication format, and here I discuss my
  experience.<br/><a href="/subjects/structuralwebdesign/">Structural web design</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/metadata/">Metadata</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/06/why/"><em>Why do I keep this site?</em></a><br/>Having had a web site for about 15 years, I start to wonder why I
  keep it in the first place.<br/><a href="/subjects/structuralwebdesign/">Structural web design</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2008</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/2008/clarin_adl/"><em>ADL i CLARIN-DK WP5</em></a><br/>En presentation jag höll om Arkiv før dansk litteratur (ADL)<br/><a href="/subjects/xmlprocessing/">XML processing</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/textencoding/">Text encoding</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/ehumanities/">Digital humanities</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/musiclanglit/">Music, language &amp; literature</a></td>
      </tr>
    </table>
  </div>
</div>
