<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div>
    <h1 style="font-family: sans-serif; width: 55%; float: left;text-align: left;">Changed URI for my feed, and a forum for discussions</h1>
    <p style="width: 38%; float: left;text-align: right">
      <em>
        <strong>
		Sigfrid Lundberg's Stuff,
	      2009-08-11</strong>
      </em>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div style="clear:both;"> </div>
  <div style="width:100%;">
    <div>
      <p>Dear Reader!</p>

      <p>I've got <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/SigfridLundbergsStuff?format=xml">a
      new URI</a> for my ATOM feed. I appologize for the inconvenience. This
      entry will be the only one available at the original one. Feed burner
      provides so many advantages that I cannot ignore them. Just click on the
      link above and subscribe, and you'll get my scribbles as usual. However,
      I've got another new feature as well.</p>

      <p>The really substantial responses I've got on this site I got from my
      <a href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/images/jacob.shtml">colleague
      Jacob</a> and <a href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/images/Gertrud_berger.shtml">my wife
      Gertrud</a></p>

      <p>Both agree that my note on <a href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/07/commuting/">commuting
      is brilliant</a>. I'm grateful for that, but as far I can tell from the
      download stats, they are the only ones who like. Then Jacob told me I
      ought to have a forum for discussions in relation to my scribbles. Well,
      then... I've added one of those nifty javascript based ones, <a href="http://disqus.com/">disqus.com</a>. Then Gertrud said: You'll
      never find the time to moderate that. We'll see.</p>

      <p>I guess it's more likely that it will be yet another of those
      pathetic empty discussion things on the net.</p>

    </div>
    <p style="text-align: left;"><em><strong>Tags:</strong></em> 
	  <a href="/subjects/structuralwebdesign/">Structural web design</a><br/><em><strong>
		Permalink:
	      </strong></em><a rel="bookmark" href="/entries/2009/08/features/">http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/08/features/</a></p>
    <hr width="50%" align="center"/>
  </div>
  <div>
    <h1>Other, not yet obsolete stuff</h1>
    <table class="news">
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/08/trends/"><em>On Divorce and Unemployment Benefit Societies</em></a><br/>Here I analyse of some data retrieved from Google Insight
  Search. This little study is inspired by the study performed by Hyunyoung
  Choi &amp; Hal Varian, Google Research, were they were able to show that it
  is possible to make short-term forcasts of economic behavours using search
  statistics.<br/><a href="/subjects/essays/">Essays</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/07/blogging/"><em>What does Free mean for The Library</em></a><br/>Blogging is out, and the new trend is to tweet in
  Twitters. Syndication is out as well, since Google steals your content and
  you cannot make money on journalism. How can we survive when all media are
  free?<br/><a href="/subjects/media/">Media</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/thelibrary/">The Library</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/internet/">Internet</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/07/indexing_philosophy/"><em>Wagging the long tail</em></a><br/>The problem with providing an OK Amazoogle experience is that we
  might fail in providing advanced services to patrons that have special
  needs.<br/><a href="/subjects/opac/">Library catalogues</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/07/commuting/"><em>On being an international commuter</em></a><br/>The last four years I've spent more than two hours a day on
  trains. And usually, but not always less than three. Furthermore, I go from
  one nation to another and participate in the in the digital dissemination of
  cultural heritage of a country which isn't my own.<br/><a href="/subjects/essays/">Essays</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/07/xslt_extensions/"><em>Why I love XSLT extension functions</em></a><br/>xslt extensions allow you to define xpath functions and extension
  elements. That makes it easy for you to perform tasks within xslt that are
  just only theoretically possible to do.<br/><a href="/subjects/xmlprocessing/">XML processing</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/07/structure/"><em>The description and encoding of structure</em></a><br/>Much metadata is fairly stright forward. A book does have a title
  and an author. That's usually no big deal. We've been able to handle that
  for centuries. A digital book has chapters, and everything you might want to
  know may be in chapter two on page seventyfive. Or someone may tell you the
  solution to your problems after a quarter of an hour in some video on
  YouTube. Now, how do we cope with this?<br/><a href="/subjects/structuralwebdesign/">Structural web design</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/metadata/">Metadata</a></td>
      </tr>
    </table>
  </div>
</div>
