<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div>
    <h1 style="font-family: sans-serif; width: 55%; float: left;text-align: left;">Does hypertext promote extractive interaction rather than
  immersive?</h1>
    <p style="width: 38%; float: left;text-align: right">
      <em>
        <strong>
		Sigfrid Lundberg's Stuff,
	      2010-04-20</strong>
      </em>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div style="clear:both;"> </div>
  <div style="width:100%;">
    <div>

      <p>There is an academic genre often referred to as <em>New Media
      Research</em>. To what extent this pursuit really deserve the lable
      research I won't go into here. I usually find contributions from this
      area utterly boring. The <a href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/08/diglib/">digital
      revolution ended 1998</a> and hence all new the media are old by now,
      and that includes Twitter and Facebook. Period.</p>

      <p>In addition I find almost all comparisons between old and new medias
      tedious, inasmuchas that I seldom learn something new reading
      them. Similarly, any text starting by claiming that the ICT area is
      under rapid development will remain only partly read. Usually only the
      very first part. Unless the first few sentences contain something
      interesting <strong>and</strong> something that's new to me. Like the <a href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2010/04/gstupid/">article by
      Nicholas Carr I mentioned the other day</a>. Carr argues that we
      nowadays have difficulties immerse in really long texts, which to
      correspond to changes in mentality.</p>

      <p>I picked up two adjectives describing people's media consumption
      patterns: <em>Extractive</em> and <em>immersive</em>. The dichotomy
      seems to come from a paper by <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_Lunenfeld">Peter Lunefeld</a>,
      who, is a student of interactive media, computer games etc. You'll find
      the two adjectives in connection with nouns as "navigation",
      "interaction" or gerunds like "<a href="http://www.blackplasticglasses.com/2010/03/23/digital-reading/">reading</a>". As
      far as reading is concerned, I'll add <a href="http://camqtly.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/abstract/34/3/285">
      this paper</a> to my reading list. It analyzes the consequences of a
      spread of extractive reading behaviours from a language pedagogy
      perspective.</p>

      <p>What worries Carr is a shift from immersive to extractive reading and
      its psychological or even neurological consequences. I do both, a
      lot. On a personal level I can vividly recall my reading of the last
      volume in <a href="http://www.stieglarsson.com/Millennium-series">Stieg
      Larsson's Millenium Trilogy</a>. I just read one page more many houndred
      times that night, until the alarm went off, and I stumbled to the
      shower, the breakfeast and off to work trying to look as if I was able
      to do something useful. Such as coding new interfaces for media
      consumption.</p>

      <p>Does the digital revolution make people less able to immerse in books
      like Donald Knuth's <em><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Art_of_Computer_Programming">The
      Art of Computer Programming</a></em> with about 650 pages per volume?
      Seven volumes are planned but three have yet to appear. Fascicle four
      was printed as recent as 2005. You need to able to immerse in books like
      that to devise search algorithms, so we may get into trouble with the
      next generation global search engines.</p>

    </div>
    <br clear="all"/>
    <p style="text-align: left;"><em><strong>Categories:</strong></em> 
	  <a href="/subjects/essays/">Essays</a><br/><em><strong>
		Permalink:
	      </strong></em><a rel="bookmark" href="/entries/2010/04/extractive/">http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2010/04/extractive/</a></p>
    <hr width="50%" align="center"/>
  </div>
  <div>
    <h1>Other, not yet obsolete stuff</h1>
    <table class="news">
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2010</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2010/04/gstupid/"><em>Is Google Making us Stupid?</em></a><br/>Having had a web site for about 15 years, I start to wonder why I
  keep it in the first place.<br/><a href="/subjects/digitalobjects/">Digital objects</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/internet/">Internet</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2010</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2010/04/darcitecture/"><em>Towards an Architectural Document
      Analysis</em></a><br/>Helena Francke, 2008. Towards an Architectural Document
      Analysis. Journal of Information Architecture<br/><a href="/subjects/structuralwebdesign/">Structural web design</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/digitalobjects/">Digital objects</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2010</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2010/04/perl/"><em>Pathologically Eclectic Rubbish Lister</em></a><br/>For many years I wrote most of my code in the Perl programming
  language. Now I've been a exclusively java programmers for five years<br/><a href="/subjects/images/">Images</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/programming/">Programming</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2010</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2010/04/buzzetti/"><em>Digital Representation and the Text Model</em></a><br/>Dino Buzzetti, 2002. Digital Representation and the Text Model. New
  Literary History, 33(1), p. 61-88.<br/><a href="/subjects/textencoding/">Text encoding</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/digitalobjects/">Digital objects</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2010</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2010/04/readings/"><em>Readings on digital objects: An annotated URIography</em></a><br/>I have a long list of articles to read on digital objects, how to
  model them etc. This page is for keeping track of my progress<br/><a href="/subjects/digitalcollections/">Digital collections</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/digitalobjects/">Digital objects</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2010</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2010/03/teimime/"><em>application/tei+xml</em></a><br/>We are about to register a mime type for TEI. This page tracks the
  progress of that effort<br/><a href="/subjects/internet/">Internet</a></td>
      </tr>
    </table>
  </div>
</div>
