<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div>
    <h1 style="font-family: sans-serif; width: 55%; float: left;text-align: left;">Are the Ways of Seeing Franscesca Woodman and Edith Gowin the
  same?</h1>
    <p style="width: 38%; float: left;text-align: right">
      <em>
        <strong>
		Sigfrid Lundberg's Stuff,
	      2015-10-04</strong>
      </em>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div style="clear:both;"> </div>
  <div style="width:100%;">
    <div>
      <p>Francesca Woodman took her life 1981 at 22 years of age. By then she
      had become a serious, hardworking and extremely skilled artistic
      photographer. She had started her exploration of art photography when
      she was 13. Here we are talking of a serious endeavour of a precosious,
      talented teenager, not a child's play. Much of her work is self
      portraiture, and often she portrays herself naked.</p>

      <p>There are several female photographers who have earned well-deserved
      fame for (among other thing) photographing naked humans, such as Imogen
      Cunningham and Ruth Bernard. They both depicted naked women, but as far
      as I know, neither Cunningham nor Bernard portrayed themselves, with or
      without clothes.</p>

      <p>According to <a href="http://www.fotosidan.se/cldoc/podd-kultforklarad-angel-fascinerar-alltjamt.htm">an
      interview with the curator, Anna Tellgren</a> the reason why Woodman
      used herself as model was just practical. She was there we she needed
      it. The cost was lower and there were no problems with model release
      contracts. I am sure there is more to than that. Since Francesca
      Woodman, Cindy Sherman and several contemporaries, the interest in this
      kind of self-portraiture has increased and is now a fairly common
      genre. I think it is much more common among women than men. This text is
      about my attempt to understand that difference.</p>

      <p>The only things I know about Edith Gowin is that she is a beautiful
      woman and that her husband is photographer Emmet Gowin. He is a
      wellknown photographer but almost certainly best known for his portraits
      of his often scantily clad or naked wife. The two have now celebrated
      their golden wedding anniversary since several years. In the
      interviews you find of them (for example) YouTube they seem to be still a
      loving couple. However, it might be that Emmet don't take as many photographs of
      Edith now as he did 40-50 years ago.</p>

      <p>Many men, photographers or not, take pictures of naked women, often
      their wives. Some of have earned well-deserved fame.</p>

      <p>There are photos taken by husband photographers of their wives that
      go far beyond the average such as Alfred Stieglitz (1864-1946) potraits
      of Georgia O'Keeffe (1887-1986) which arose from an intensive love
      story. <sup><a href="note#1">1</a></sup> Edward Weston shot countless of
      nudes, of which, according to Robert Adams, most are fairly
      uninteresting:</p>

      <blockquote>
	<p>With the exception of two fullength nudes of Tina Modotti and five
	of Charis Wilson in the Oceano dunes (not many, considering the number
	of nudes Weston took), the pictures that supposedly resulted from
	Weston's love for his subjects are relative to the rest of his life's
	work, unsuccesful; they are cold to the point of being dead.</p>
      </blockquote>

      <p>Many photos of lesser artists than Weston deserve even less praise,
      and perhaps most such pictures shouldn't really have been taken.</p>

      <p>One of the best, earliest and still extremely influential theoretical
      analyses of the nude in western art is in <em>Ways of seeing</em> by
      John Berger<sup><a href="#note3">3</a></sup>.</p>

      <p>His arguments can be summarized in contrasting statements. For
      example:</p>

      <table>
	<tr>
	  <td>Men survey</td>
	  <td>
	    <pre>
	    </pre>
	  </td>
	  <td>Women are the surveyed</td>
	  <td>p. 46</td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
	  <td>Men act</td>
	  <td>
	    <pre>
	    </pre>
	  </td>
	  <td>Women appear</td>
	  <td>p. 47</td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
	  <td>Men look at women.</td>
	  <td>
	    <pre>
	    </pre>
	  </td>
	  <td>Women watch themselves being looked at.</td>
	  <td>p. 47</td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
	  <td>To be naked is to be oneself</td>
	  <td>
	    <pre>
	    </pre>
	  </td>
	  <td>To be nude is to be seen as naked by others and yet not
	  recognized for oneself</td>
	  <td>p. 54</td>
	</tr>
      </table>

      <div>
	<h3>Foot notes</h3>
	<ol>

	  <li id="note1"><a href="http://www.npr.org/2011/07/21/138467808/stieglitz-and-okeeffe-their-love-and-life-in-letters">Stieglitz
	  And O'Keeffe: Their Love And Life In Letters</a></li>

	  <li>Adams, Robert, 1994. <em>Why people photograph.</em> Aperture Foundation,
	  New York.</li>

	  <li id="note3">Berger, John, 1972. <em>Ways of Seeing</em>. Penguin Books
	  ltd. London.</li>


	</ol>
      </div>
    </div>
    <br clear="all"/>
    <p style="text-align: left;"><em><strong>Categories:</strong></em> 
	  <a href="/subjects/photography/">Photography</a><br/><em><strong>
		Permalink:
	      </strong></em><a rel="bookmark" href="/entries/2015/10/francesca/">http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2015/10/francesca/</a></p>
    <hr width="50%" align="center"/>
  </div>
  <div>
    <h1>Other, not yet obsolete stuff</h1>
    <table class="news">
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2015-08-24</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2015/08/fotofestival/"><em>Landskrona fotofestival 2015</em></a><br/>Fotofestivalen i Landskrona har seglat upp som en fixstjärna på den
  nordiska fotohimlen. Jag har varit där tre år i rad nu. Håller den
  måttet? Har den växtverk?<br/><a href="/subjects/photography/">Photography</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2015-05-23</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2015/05/exhibits/"><em>Gerillautställning</em></a><br/>Lördagen den 23 maj, 13:00-16:00, Katarina Bangata 25, Södermalm, Stockholm<br/><a href="/subjects/photography/">Photography</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2015-05-22</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2015/05/witt/"><em>The Times They Are a-Changin'</em></a><br/>Knausgård går till rasande attack på Cyklopernas Land och
  Witt-Brattström Har inte tid att hyckla mer<br/><a href="/subjects/ageing/">Ageing</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2015-05-17</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2015/05/spidering/"><em>Om sökmaskiner och spindlar</em></a><br/>År 1995 är ett märkesår för mig. Det är då jag bestämmer mig för
  att byta karriär till Internet och programmering.<br/><a href="/subjects/webindexing/">Web indexing</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2015-05-12</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2015/05/markings/"><em>Vägmärken</em></a><br/>Min Far fick Vägmärken i femtioårspresent för nästan exakt femtio
  år sedan. Jag läser den just nu, och har faktiskt följt mig av och till ett
  par år nu.<br/><a href="/subjects/religion/">Religion</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/essays/">Essays</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/spirituality/">Spirituality</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2015-04-20</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2015/03/averylongday/"><em>At the end of the day there's another day dawning</em></a><br/>From the life of a trans-national commuter<br/><a href="/subjects/photography/">Photography</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/video/">Video</a></td>
      </tr>
    </table>
  </div>
</div>
