<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div>
    <h1 style="font-family: sans-serif; width: 55%; float: left;text-align: left;">Reflections on a Library at Dusk</h1>
    <p style="width: 38%; float: left;text-align: right">
      <em>
        <strong>
		Sigfrid Lundberg's Stuff,
	      2010-01-28</strong>
      </em>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div style="clear:both;"> </div>
  <div style="width:100%;">
    <div>
      <div style="margin: 0.5em; float: left; width:40%;">
	<a href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/galleri/200908-200912/smaller/20091201108.jpg" border="0" title="library at dusk">
	  <img src="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/galleri/200908-200912/smaller/20091201108.jpg" width="100%" alt="library at dusk"/>
	</a>
      </div>

      <p>This is The Royal Library, Copenhagen, also known as The Black
      Diamond.  I've seen its exterior in all kinds of weather conditions
      during the five years I've been working there. I'll give you some images
      showing the spectacular black granite fasade at dusk.</p>

      <p>I have taken all of them with my mobile, from the stop of bus
      66. While waiting for the bus, I can see the library if I turn towards
      the east. Towards the south I can see the harbour, which is a strait
      separating the island of Amager from Copenhagen. Here you'll recognize
      the reflections of the water in the harbour. You can also see the
      Langebro bridge and the large Ny Kredit building. These are structures
      situated west from the library, behind my back.</p>

      <div style="margin: 0.5em; float: right; width:40%;">
	<a href="/entries/2010/01/dusk/20100120204.jpg" title="rush hour reflected in a library">
	  <img src="/entries/2010/01/dusk/20100120204.jpg" width="100%" alt="rush hour reflected in a library"/>
	</a>
      </div>

      <p>There is a red dot in the black granite. It is the reflections of the
      back light of a car driving westwards from the bus stop towards the
      bridge. If you look really careful you'll see a green traffic light
      mirror itself close the the red dot.</p>

      <div style="margin: 0.5em; float: left; width:40%;">
	<a href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/galleri/200908-200912/smaller/20091130106.jpg" border="0" title="library under the rainbow">
	  <img src="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/galleri/200908-200912/smaller/20091130106.jpg" width="100%" alt="library under the rainbow"/>
	</a>
      </div>


      <p>I've been really fascinated by these reflections for some time
      now. Here is another image which is cropped to show the traffic. There
      is read traffic lights just outside the library, and green at the
      Langebro bridge. You can see a distinct green dot in the black
      granite. There's quite a few eastbound cars taking the opportunity to
      mirror themselves in the black granite while waiting.</p>

      <h2>Somewhere under the rainbow</h2>

      <p>A classical rainbow contains most visible colours. This one, however,
      is taken at dusk. Hence there is more red in it than you're used to. To
      be honest, this image is taken east of the bus stop. You see, I had to
      position myself such that the pot of gold should be found by Our
      Saviour's Church. If you look carefully, you should be able to see the
      tip of its cork screw shaped tower just where the rain bow hits the
      ground.</p>


    </div>
    <p style="text-align: left;"><em><strong>Categories:</strong></em> 
	  <a href="/subjects/essays/">Essays</a><br/><em><strong>
		Permalink:
	      </strong></em><a rel="bookmark" href="/entries/2010/01/dusk/">http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2010/01/dusk/</a></p>
    <hr width="50%" align="center"/>
  </div>
  <div>
    <h1>Other, not yet obsolete stuff</h1>
    <table class="news">
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/07/commuting/"><em>On being an international commuter</em></a><br/>The last four years I've spent more than two hours a day on
  trains. And usually, but not always less than three. Furthermore, I go from
  one nation to another and participate in the in the digital dissemination of
  cultural heritage of a country which isn't my own.<br/><a href="/subjects/essays/">Essays</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/11/kbmetadta/"><em>Fifteen polar bears and one architecture</em></a><br/>Today I gave a presentation on our metadata work. My experience of
  that turned out to be about images.<br/><a href="/subjects/metadata/">Metadata</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/10/programming/"><em>The specification and the TODO-list</em></a><br/>Through the web, a software vendor and a service provider could all
  of a sudden compete on the same market. The software vendor use the
  traditional specification, but a service implies software which is in
  continuous development. Strictly speaking, there are no projects anymore,
  just different activities. No specifications anymore, but TODO lists
  containing incidents, bugs and requests for features ranked by
  importance.<br/><a href="/subjects/programming/">Programming</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/11/twocultures/"><em>The two Cultures</em></a><br/>Do you know the second law of thermodynamics?<br/><a href="/subjects/programming/">Programming</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/10/webdevelopment/"><em>What about the HECS platforms?</em></a><br/>I've used fortran, pascal, C, perl, php and java in addition to
  more specialized tools such as SQL and XSLT. There is currently a lot of
  discussions on what platform will be the next winner.<br/><a href="/subjects/programming/">Programming</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/08/opensearch/"><em>Syndication and Simple REST XML web services in a library context</em></a><br/>Some time ago I demonstrated our navigation services. In that entry
  I promised to tell you more about these services when they are are more
  mature. Here is the story on the architecture of some of our new
  digitization services.<br/><a href="/subjects/xws/">XML web services</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/metadataprocessing/">Metadata processing</a></td>
      </tr>
    </table>
  </div>
</div>
