<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div>
    <h1 style="font-family: sans-serif; width: 55%; float: left;text-align: left;">What is a book, and does it matter?</h1>
    <p style="width: 38%; float: left;text-align: right">
      <em>
        <strong>
		Sigfrid Lundberg's Stuff,
	      2009-08-26</strong>
      </em>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div style="clear:both;"> </div>
  <div style="width:100%;">
    <div>
      <p>Lorcan Dempsey of OCLC research, is involved in among lots of things,
      statistical analyses of media use. In that work he and his colleagues
      are forced to make som operational definitions of the 'book'. Definitions
      that inspired Lorcan to make some <a href="http://orweblog.oclc.org/archives/002000.html">interesting
      reflections on books</a>.</p>

      <p>I once had a chat with a book historian. Her view is was that a book
      is defined by its binding. The binding is the most important part of a
      book. Without it, it's just a pile of paper.</p>

      <p>My answer was as follows: Assume that an author is writing a
      book. While working on it there is a mansuscript -- which is a computer
      file. After a year or so, the book is completed and is accepted for
      publication.</p>

      <p>In my view it is now a book. After all <em>the book has been accepted
      for publication</em>. When you send it to the printers workshop, then I
      suppose it is manuscript. 5On the other hand, when you download the thing
      from <a href="http://www.amazon.com/">amazon.com</a> to your kindle,
      then it's a book.</p>
    </div>
    <p style="text-align: left;"><em><strong>Categories:</strong></em> 
	  <a href="/subjects/essays/">Essays</a>,
	    <a href="/subjects/media/">Media</a><br/><em><strong>
		Permalink:
	      </strong></em><a rel="bookmark" href="/entries/2009/08/whatisabook/">http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/08/whatisabook/</a></p>
    <hr width="50%" align="center"/>
  </div>
  <div>
    <h1>Other, not yet obsolete stuff</h1>
    <table class="news">
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/08/threeyears/"><em>Five years that formed the digital library as we know it:
  1997-2001</em></a><br/>It appeared to me that many the standards and technologies
  underpinning the digital library as we know it were formed during five years
  around the turn of the century.<br/><a href="/subjects/metadata/">Metadata</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/08/quotations/"><em>A quotation is much more than an extract</em></a><br/>In my last entry, on cool URIs, I discussed the identification of
  documents. The conclusion from that is that people in the library world are
  obsessed by being able to find documents. I take that more serious than most
  other library folk. I'd say that it is our mission to help our patrons find
  a single word in a text, a rectangle in an image and so forth. The time is
  gone when we could tell users: The answer to your question might be in any
  of the books on that shelf.<br/><a href="/subjects/structuralwebdesign/">Structural web design</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/08/cooluris/"><em>Forgive me, Father, for I have sinned... I have moved a
  document</em></a><br/>The initiatives behind the persistent linking is trying to change
  the status of old documents. From 404 to 200. We've had some success with
  books and journals using ISBN and ISSN numbers. Why not try to copy this to
  the web? But, alas!, library people have in general too little understanding
  of the Worldwide Web. In particular those who advocate persistent
  identifiers.<br/><a href="/subjects/structuralwebdesign/">Structural web design</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/08/features/"><em>Changed URI for my feed, and a forum for discussions</em></a><br/>Having actively maintained my site for some, I've decided make a
  few changes...<br/><a href="/subjects/colophon/">Colophon</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/08/trends/"><em>On Divorce and Unemployment Benefit Societies</em></a><br/>Here I analyse of some data retrieved from Google Insight
  Search. This little study is inspired by the study performed by Hyunyoung
  Choi &amp; Hal Varian, Google Research, were they were able to show that it
  is possible to make short-term forcasts of economic behavours using search
  statistics.<br/><a href="/subjects/essays/">Essays</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/07/blogging/"><em>What does Free mean for The Library</em></a><br/>Blogging is out, and the new trend is to tweet in
  Twitters. Syndication is out as well, since Google steals your content and
  you cannot make money on journalism. How can we survive when all media are
  free?<br/><a href="/subjects/media/">Media</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/thelibrary/">The Library</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/internet/">Internet</a></td>
      </tr>
    </table>
  </div>
</div>
