<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div>
    <h1 style="font-family: sans-serif; width: 55%; float: left;text-align: left;">Fifteen polar bears and one architecture</h1>
    <p style="width: 38%; float: left;text-align: right">
      <em>
        <strong>
		Sigfrid Lundberg's Stuff,
	      2009-11-30</strong>
      </em>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div style="clear:both;"> </div>
  <div style="width:100%;">
    <div>

      <p>Today I gave a presentation on our metadata work. It was meant to be
      about METS and MODS, but it became more of a justification for our work
      than about. As usual I had <a href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/2009/nov30/presentation.xml">too many
      slides</a>. My main idea was to use google images instead of slides, but
      then I had to add some slides anyway because the navigation overhead was
      too high and I had difficulties to remember which images to click on.</p>

      <p>The google searches are interesting. The visual result sets give you
      an overview very different from the text search. The visual search
      engines (see, for example <a href="http://www.search-cube.com/">Search
      Cube</a>) base their navigation on some kind of canned screen dumps.
      That's nice but it isn't the images produced by the author, but an image
      of the text.</p>

      <p>Please find below an annotated list of links to searches I like:</p>

      <div style="float: left; width: 50%; margin-left:0.5em;margin-right:0.5em;">
	<a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/webarch/" title="Architecture of the worldwide web"><img src="http://www.w3.org/2001/tag/2004/webarch-20041021/uri-res-rep.png" width="90%" border="0" alt="URI &amp; representations &amp; resources"/></a>
	<p><small>Figure 1</small></p>

      </div>

      <h2><a href="http://images.google.com/images?gbv=2&amp;hl=en&amp;um=1&amp;sa=1&amp;q=architecture+of+the+worldwide+web&amp;aq=f&amp;oq=&amp;aqi=&amp;start=0">Architecture of the worldwide web</a></h2>

      <p>First hit is Figure 1, from <a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/webarch/">the appropriate W3
      recommendation</a>. Then there are fifteen polar bears belonging to the
      cover of <q>Information Architecture for the World Wide Web</q>, a title
      that I think I should read when I get the opportunity.</p>

      <h2><a href="http://images.google.com/images?gbv=2&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=1&amp;q=library+catalog&amp;aq=f&amp;oq=&amp;aqi=g1&amp;start=0">Library
      catalog</a></h2>

      <p>This one isn't as spectacular as the architecture, but it
      gives you an idea on what people know and believe they know when it
      comes to what libraries and cataloging is about.</p>

      <div style="float: right; width: 50%; margin-left:0.5em;margin-right:0.5em;">
	<a href="http://www.library.nd.edu/daiad/morgan/musings/ngc/" title="Eric Lease Morgan's musings on next generation catalog">
	  <img src="http://www.library.nd.edu/daiad/morgan/musings/ngc/ngo.gif" width="100%" border="0" alt="Eric Lease Morgan's musings on next generation catalog"/>
	  </a>
	  <p><small>Figure 2. Eric Lease Morgan's musing on the Next
	  Generation Opac</small></p>

      </div>

      <p>There is a wonderful image (Figure 2) showing what we were all
      thinking about around 2006. When I think of it, we still are. The range
      of protocols to support, and the list of metadata formats are the
      same. The ideas doesn't change that fast.</p>

      <h2><a href="http://images.google.com/images?gbv=2&amp;hl=en&amp;q=circulation+desk&amp;sa=N&amp;start=0&amp;ndsp=20">Circulation desk</a></h2>

      <p>All libraries I know have a circulation desk. Searching for it in
      Google images yields 978000 hits. Adding quotation marks reduces the
      number to 34400. None of them are particularly interesting, except
      perhaps the one at <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/army_arch/2691906687/">Doheny
      Library</a>.</p>

      <p>My fascination is more due to fact that they are all there, all these
      desks. I mean, how interesting is a circulation desk?</p>

      <div style="float: right; width: 50%; margin-left:0.5em;margin-right:0.5em;">
	<a href="http://library.web.cern.ch/library/Webzine/10/papers/1/">
	  <img src="http://library.web.cern.ch/library/Webzine/10/papers/1/figure3.jpg" width="90%" border="0" alt="Works, expressions, manifestations and relations"/>
	</a>

	<p><small>Figure 3. Knut Hegna (2004) <q>Using FRBR</q></small></p>

      </div>

      <h2><a href="http://images.google.com/images?hl=en&amp;source=hp&amp;q=work+expression+manifestation+item&amp;gbv=2&amp;aq=f&amp;oq=&amp;aqi=">work expression manifestation item</a></h2>

      <p>This one hard core information science. <em>Work</em> is the
      ontological work, before it is expressed in a manuscript. The platonic
      blog entry, before it hits the web.</p>

      <p>There are other hard core ones, such as <a href="http://images.google.com/images?gbv=2&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=1&amp;q=collect+preserve+organize+provide+access&amp;aq=f&amp;oq=&amp;aqi=&amp;start=0">collect
      preserve organize provide access</a>. As a <a href="http://www.google.com/search?gbv=2&amp;hl=en&amp;q=collect%20preserve%20organize%20provide%20access&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;sa=N&amp;tab=iw&amp;start=0">web
      search</a>, it yields hits mainly in library &amp; archive mission
      statements.</p>



    </div>
    <p style="text-align: left;"><em><strong>Categories:</strong></em> 
	  <a href="/subjects/metadata/">Metadata</a><br/><em><strong>
		Permalink:
	      </strong></em><a rel="bookmark" href="/entries/2009/11/kbmetadta/">http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/11/kbmetadta/</a></p>
    <hr width="50%" align="center"/>
  </div>
  <div>
    <h1>Other, not yet obsolete stuff</h1>
    <table class="news">
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/10/programming/"><em>The specification and the TODO-list</em></a><br/>Through the web, a software vendor and a service provider could all
  of a sudden compete on the same market. The software vendor use the
  traditional specification, but a service implies software which is in
  continuous development. Strictly speaking, there are no projects anymore,
  just different activities. No specifications anymore, but TODO lists
  containing incidents, bugs and requests for features ranked by
  importance.<br/><a href="/subjects/programming/">Programming</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/11/twocultures/"><em>The two Cultures</em></a><br/>Do you know the second law of thermodynamics?<br/><a href="/subjects/programming/">Programming</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/10/webdevelopment/"><em>What about the HECS platforms?</em></a><br/>I've used fortran, pascal, C, perl, php and java in addition to
  more specialized tools such as SQL and XSLT. There is currently a lot of
  discussions on what platform will be the next winner.<br/><a href="/subjects/programming/">Programming</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/08/opensearch/"><em>Syndication and Simple REST XML web services in a library context</em></a><br/>Some time ago I demonstrated our navigation services. In that entry
  I promised to tell you more about these services when they are are more
  mature. Here is the story on the architecture of some of our new
  digitization services.<br/><a href="/subjects/xws/">XML web services</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/metadataprocessing/">Metadata processing</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/09/msb/"><em>Att tjäna den demokratiska kulturnationens minne</em></a><br/>Jag har arbetat med att programmera digitala bibliotek i ungefär 15
  år. När jag läser debatten om biblioteket i Sydsvenskan känner jag att jag
  borde säga något. Jag vet inte i vilken utsträckning mitt perspektiv kommer
  att kännas relevant för alla de som känner sig kallade att yttra sig, men
  jag har en hel del erfarenheter som nog de flesta andra saknar.<br/><a href="/subjects/thelibrary/">The Library</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/internet/">Internet</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/footnotes/"><em>Add footnotes to my pages -- a prototype text annotation
  interface</em></a><br/>I've had a javascript based forum with thread for each entry. That
  seemed boring to me. Why should users be restricted to commenting entire
  articles. Why not letting them add footnotes to arbitrary positions in a
  text. In this entry I experiment with this feature.<br/><a href="/subjects/structuralwebdesign/">Structural web design</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/xmlprocessing/">XML Processing</a></td>
      </tr>
    </table>
  </div>
</div>
