<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div>
    <h1 style="font-family: sans-serif; width: 55%; float: left;text-align: left;">Costs and benefits of standards</h1>
    <p style="width: 38%; float: left;text-align: right">
      <em>
        <strong>
		Sigfrid Lundberg's Stuff,
	      2011-09-16</strong>
      </em>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div style="clear:both;"> </div>
  <div style="width:100%;">
    <div>

      <p>For about fifteen years I've been active with both the creation and
      implementations of standards. I've been an evangelist for good metadata,
      good text encoding and sound internet standards. Good standards do
      help. In the library world we have the MARC bibliographic record as a
      prime example. Without such a standard it would have been much more
      difficult to establish the computerized library catalog as we know
      it. That concept has been the basis for a small but not insignificant
      branch of the software industry.</p>

      <p>The uniform acceptance of the MARC format makes it possible to
      exchange records on a global scale across systems from different
      vendors. To the success we have to add the Z39.50 protocol for
      bibliorgraphic search and information retrieval, which has enabled us to
      cross-search virtually any library OPACS.</p>

      <p>All this is indeed useful. But to prove that we've saved money is
      hard. The bibliographic records are created and maintained in workflows
      that are supported by sets of complicated cataloging rules. The
      bibliographic processes requires trained staff, often with academic
      education.</p>

      <p>
	Now Library of Congress has finally reached the following conclusion:
	<q style="font-style:italic;">Recognizing that Z39.2/MARC are no longer fit for the purpose, work
	with the library and other interested communities to specify and
	implement a carrier for bibliographic information that is capable of
	representing the full range of data of interest to libraries, and of
	facilitating the exchange of such data both within the library
	community and with related communities.</q>
	<a href="http://www.loc.gov/marc/transition/news/framework-103111.html">
	  A Bibliographic Framework for the Digital Age
	</a>
      </p>

      <p>I sincerely think that this will lead to lesser costs for OPAC
      software. Noone knows if this will benefit the libraries or just
      increase the revenues of the software houses that will implement the
      next generation of library catalogs.</p>

      <p>I doubt that RDA will be cheaper to use than AACR2.</p>

    </div>
    <br clear="all"/>
    <p style="text-align: left;"><em><strong>Categories:</strong></em> 
	  <a href="/subjects/metadata/">Metadata</a>,
	    <a href="/subjects/metadataprocessing/">Metadata processing</a>,
	    <a href="/subjects/thelibrary/">The Library</a><br/><em><strong>
		Permalink:
	      </strong></em><a rel="bookmark" href="/entries/2011/09/standards/">http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2011/09/standards/</a></p>
    <hr width="50%" align="center"/>
  </div>
  <div>
    <h1>Other, not yet obsolete stuff</h1>
    <table class="news">
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2011-05-24</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2011/05/gustav/"><em>A neighbour, almost</em></a><br/>I've made a new acquaintance, Gustav Holmberg, a history of science
  scholar with a deep interest in photography. He has started a small series
  with portraits of cameras he meets on the streets of the world.<br/><a href="/subjects/photography/">Photography</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/hardware/">Hardware</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/neighbours/">Neighbours</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2011-05-07</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2011/05/focus/"><em>On focusing on the essentials</em></a><br/>I acquired a socalled mirrorless interchangable lens camera in
  August last year. Since than I have used it exclusively with manual focus
  vintage lenses. Here I discuss my experience blending old and new imaging
  technologies.<br/><a href="/subjects/images/">Images</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/photography/">Photography</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/hardware/">Hardware</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2011-05-03</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2011/04/rokkor/"><em>A Leica lens from Minolta?</em></a><br/>The M Rokkor lenses were produced by Minolta for their excellent
  rangefinder camera Minolta CLE. I aquired one of them, the 40mm f2.0, for
  use with my Olympus E-P2.<br/><a href="/subjects/images/">Images</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/photography/">Photography</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/hardware/">Hardware</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2011-01-12</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2011/01/thief/"><em>I have smoked a cigarr together with The Book Thief</em></a><br/>This is the story about the one and only book thief I've met<br/><a href="/subjects/thelibrary/">The Library</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/stories/">Stories</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2010-12-02</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2010/12/twolenses/"><em>A tale of two lenses</em></a><br/>Here I discuss two lenses. Both are very new. I've owned them less
  than three months, and they represent recent developments from the
  respective companies building them. But appart from that they differ in
  almost all aspects. Even in the very idea behind their existence.<br/><a href="/subjects/images/">Images</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/hardware/">Hardware</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2010-11-28</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2010/11/patience/"><em>On patience and bus stops</em></a><br/>Waiting at a bus stop can learn us something significant about
  human nature<br/><a href="/subjects/essays/">Essays</a></td>
      </tr>
    </table>
  </div>
</div>
