<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div>
    <h1 style="font-family: sans-serif; width: 55%; float: left;text-align: left;">Thinking when the spring is approaching</h1>
    <p style="width: 38%; float: left;text-align: right">
      <em>
        <strong>
		Sigfrid Lundberg's Stuff,
	      2010-03-09</strong>
      </em>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div style="clear:both;"> </div>
  <div style="width:100%;">
    <div>

      <div style="float:right;width:33%;margin-right:0.5em;margin-left:0.5em;">
	<a href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2010/03/thinking/20100218231.jpg" title="The Thinker"><img src="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2010/03/thinking/smaller20100218231.jpg" alt="The Thinker" width="100%"/></a>
	<p>
	  <small>Fig. 1. There is no doubt what the thinker has been thinking
	  about this winter. Or that is what I think.</small>
	</p>
      </div>

     <p>It has been a long and harsh winter here in Scandinavia. I am one of
     those who hate the cold darkness which characterizes my part of the
     world. Many of us have been thinking about the weather (Fig. 1).</p>

     <p>Since christmas I've been involved two projects, one of which is
     currently approaching deliverable. Unfortunately it has been delayed but
     on the other hand I've got the opportunity to learn <a href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2010/03/aformwithajoin/" title="A Form with a Join">Xforms</a>. I think that both the library and
     myself will benefit from it.</p>

     <div style="float:left;width:33%;margin-right:0.75em;margin-left:0.5em;">
       <a href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2010/03/thinking/20100130216.jpg" title="Public Transport Burdened by Ice">
	 <img src="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2010/03/thinking/smaller20100130216.jpg" width="100%" alt="Public Transport Burdened by Ice"/>
       </a>
       <p><small>Fig. 2. All public transport has had far too much
       problems. And far too few trains has carried too many passengers, and
       too much ice.</small></p>
     </div>

     <p>The other project, a redesign of our Digital Object Management System
     (DOMS), is approaching a journey to Stanford together with some good
     colleagues.</p>

     <p>Those of us who <a href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/07/commuting/">commute</a>
     has had problems during the winter (Fig. 2). Regardless of how we travel,
     most of us look forward to the spring (Fig. 3).</p>

      <div style="float:right;width:45%;margin-right:0.5em;margin-left:0.5em;">
	<a href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2010/03/thinking/20100207227.jpg" title="Socially unacceptable vehicle in snow"><img src="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2010/03/thinking/smaller20100207227.jpg" alt="Socially unacceptable vehicle in snow" width="100%"/></a>

	<p><small>Fig. 3. But so has all Socially Unacceptable Vehicles. This
	vehicle is buried. In snow. The owner looks forward to spring. So do
	I.</small></p>
      </div>

      <h2>New projects</h2>

      <p>I have two really stimulating projects which will keep me occupied
      for the better part of the coming year. The most important one for me is
      that I've been given the opportunity to spend one quarter of my time on
      basic research into digital library objects.</p>

      <p>The idea is to start from the <a href="http://scholar.google.com/scholar?hl=en&amp;q=soda%20model%20dumb%20archive&amp;aql=&amp;oq=&amp;um=1&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;sa=N&amp;tab=ws">Smart
      Object Dumb Archive</a> (SODA) model. It is an old model, but there is
      not many alternatives.  There are a number of new approaches that look
      very much like SODA, such as the successful <a href="http://www.idpf.org/">.epub format</a> and the formats used within
      <a href="http://www.upnp.org/">Universal Plug and Play</a>. UPnP
      distributes both metadata and digital objects such as music and film
      within a local area network.</p>

      <p>The second project is still just planning but here I will contribute
      to a new critical edition of Ludvig Holbergs collected work.</p>

    </div>
    <br clear="all"/>
    <p style="text-align: left;"><em><strong>Categories:</strong></em> 
	  <a href="/subjects/essays/">Essays</a>,
	    <a href="/subjects/images/">Images</a><br/><em><strong>
		Permalink:
	      </strong></em><a rel="bookmark" href="/entries/2010/03/thinking/">http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2010/03/thinking/</a></p>
    <hr width="50%" align="center"/>
  </div>
  <div>
    <h1>Other, not yet obsolete stuff</h1>
    <table class="news">
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2010</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2010/03/solarenergy/"><em>Solar energy</em></a><br/>White reflects radiation from the sun to a larger degree than do
  other colours<br/><a href="/subjects/images/">Images</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2010</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2010/03/bash/"><em>Bourne Again Shell</em></a><br/>The Bourne Again Shell is a prominent part of my life. Dark moments
  I've felt that I'm obsoleted by modern technologies, but all of a sudden I
  realised that I'm as modern as smarphone users<br/><a href="/subjects/images/">Images</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2010</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2010/03/aformwithajoin/"><em>A form with a join</em></a><br/>A form is a document, or part of one, that can be used for the
  entry of data. A join is a construct in query languages such SQL. A join
  allows you to lookup data in one part of a database based on a query in an
  other part. Joins are very general, and may appear in other contexts. Such
  as the XML forms language.<br/><a href="/subjects/xmlprocessing/">XML processing</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/metadataprocessing/">Metadata processing</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2010</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2010/02/youdontneed/"><em>Why you need a persistence strategy</em></a><br/>Here I go through some of the arguments why you need to implement a
  persistence strategy. We also conclude that the hypertext link is the single
  thing that makes the Worldwide web to a web. Hence it is a serious thing. If
  you're working within the digital library world you should be devoted to the
  hypertext link.<br/><a href="/subjects/structuralwebdesign/">Structural web design</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/internet/">Internet</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2010</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2010/02/persid/"><em>The URN:NBN is dead and resurrection is meaningless</em></a><br/>I'm one of those who try to base all decisions on facts. Politics
  belong to the strategic field, and in that field the only thing I can offer
  is advice.<br/><a href="/subjects/structuralwebdesign/">Structural web design</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/internet/">Internet</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2010</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2010/02/mor_minns/"><em>Podcast: Mor minns</em></a><br/>Min mor har tre år kvar till 100. Jag menar att hon är en helt
  fantastisk kvinna, med ett knivskarpt intellekt. Hon fick aldrig gå mer än
  sju år i skolan som barn, men i 60-årsåldern tog hon i princip
  gymnasiekompetens. I denna serie läser hon dikter och berättar ur minnet
  eftersom hon är nästan blind.<br/><a href="/subjects/essays/">Essays</a></td>
      </tr>
    </table>
  </div>
</div>
