<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div>
    <h1 style="width: 58%; float: left;text-align: leftt">The description and encoding of structure</h1>
    <p style="width: 38%; float: left;text-align: right">
      <em>
        <strong>
		Sigfrid Lundberg's Stuff,
	      2009-07-21</strong>
      </em>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div style="clear:both;"> </div>
  <div style="width:100%;">
    <div>

      <p>Many things in life can best be represented as trees. Indeed, life
      itself is a tree of various life forms. We have the animal and plant
      kingdoms, and these main categories are further sub-divided into phylae,
      classes, genera. The animal kingdom is divided into invertebrates and
      vertebrates. The latter include amphibians, reptiles, birds and
      mammals. Human knowledge is also depicted as a tree.</p>

      <p>A lot of other things are trees. Hence, philosophers, mathematicins
      and computer scientists have put quite an effort into the modelling
      stuff as trees. Within library &amp; information science we have used
      the term classification systems for centuries, I suppose, and more
      recently we have started to talk about ontologies and knowledge
      organization. There are a lot of theory and a lot of standards in this
      area. Systems like <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Topic_Maps">topic maps</a> (see also
      <a href="http://www.topicmaps.org/">topicmaps.org</a>) and more recently
      Simple Knowledge Organization System <a href="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/">SKOS</a>) are available for those
      who need a standard for knowledge organization.</p>

      <p>On a very down to earth level, I tend to think of controlled
      vocabularies as filters and navigators. The latter are trees and may
      contain many terms arranged into a tree of arbitrary depth. The filters
      are lists of controlled terms, which may be whereabout in the tree we
      are. Think of Yahoo Directory. You can browse into <a href="http://dir.yahoo.com/Regional/Countries/Italy/Regions/Tuscany/">Tuscany</a>
      and get a very long list of resources. Then there was a menu at the top
      where you can choose between "Business and Shopping", "Entertainment and
      Arts", "Recreation and Sports", "Travel and Transportation" and so
      forth. These are broader categorizations that apply to Firenze as well
      as Siena or New York city or any place you may want to visit. We in the
      Web business call them <em>filters</em> or <em>facets</em>.</p>

      <h2>Recognizing and recalling</h2>

      <p>From a user perspective, you have to take into account that there are
      two cognitive processes involved when using services which like Yahoo
      Directory employ navigators and filters. The first process one is much
      more fundamental, and is by nurture and possibly nature a part of the
      human mind: This is to say: Ah Tuscany, that is a part of Italy, isn't
      it. It's like distinguishing between a wasp and a bumble bee. On an
      evolutionary time-scale we've benefitted from being able to say, this is
      edible this is not, or this one has a sting and is likely to use
      it. This is to recognize something when you see it.</p>

      <p>The opposite is a much more difficult cognitive process: I want to
      know something about Tuscany: Ok, I then start clicking on Italy. You
      have to connect Italy with Tuscany, not only recognize Tuscany. This
      makes it more difficult to find Tuscany given Italy than Italy given
      Tuscany. Remembering might not be trivial. To know in advance things
      like "frogs are amphibians" and that "diabetes is an endocrinological
      disorder". On the other hand, to perform successful searching in Google
      is even more demanding.</p>

      <h2>Ordered hierarchies of content objects</h2>

      <p>There are structures that are inside a resource, and that require
      navigation as well. As a first approximation we can assume that digital
      resources, such as electronic books, are trees as well. This modelis
      called OHCO (ordered hierarchy of content objects). That view has been
      questioned, and it is for instance claimed that any ordinary text
      consists of many, <a href="http://www.stg.brown.edu/resources/stg/monographs/ohco.html">overlapping
      hierarchies</a>. I just love overlapping hierarchies. They are great fun.</p>

      <p>Anyway, if your search the scientific literature on the theory of
      text, you'll find everything you want to know about post-structuralistic
      deconstruction of the OCHO model. Theoretically, I can understand the
      problems. But for me they are more often than not purely academical.</p>

      <p>If you instead search Google books for some real content, <a href="http://books.google.com/books?spell=1&amp;q=nightingale+lark+balcony&amp;as_brr=1">nightingale
      lark balcony</a> you'll find Romeo &amp; Juliet in her bed room. Scene V
      in Act III of Romeo and Juliet, on page <a href="http://books.google.com/books?id=09qTVKsjwSwC&amp;lpg=PA190&amp;dq=nightingale%20lark%20balcony&amp;as_brr=1&amp;pg=PA189">189</a>,

      <a href="http://books.google.com/books?id=H_EjAAAAMAAJ&amp;dq=nightingale%20lark%20balcony&amp;as_brr=1&amp;pg=PA160">160</a>
      and a lot of other page numbers, dependent on which edition. In the
      world accoring to me, you may have a lot of hierarchies and they may
      overlap, and OHCO may be false. But if you want to be able to address
      content in a more clever way than the one chosen by Google books, then
      you cannot do without a content model that looks like, well, a tree.</p>

    </div>
    <p style="text-align: right">
      <em>
        <strong>
		Permalink:
	      </strong>
      </em>
      <a rel="bookmark" href="/entries/2009/07/structure/">http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/07/structure/</a>
    </p>
    <hr width="50%" align="center"/>
  </div>
  <div>
    <h1>Other, not yet obsolete stuff</h1>
    <table class="news">
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/07/xslt_extensions/"><em>Why I love XSLT extension functions</em></a><br/>xslt extensions allow you to define xpath functions and extension
  elements. That makes it easy for you to perform tasks within xslt that are
  just only theoretically possible to do.<br/><a href="/subjects/xmlprocessing/">XML processing</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/07/escience/"><em>Will the research libraries play a role in e-science</em></a><br/>I was asked to participate in an e-science pilot project.  The work
  in the project has been food for thought for me. Will libraries be a part of
  a future eScience infrastructure?<br/><a href="/subjects/escience/">eScience</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/07/victory/"><em>The predator rests on its prey</em></a><br/>I've seen this image before. An excavator has demolished a
  building, and has then proudly been parked on top of the remnants.<br/><a href="/subjects/essays/">Essays</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/07/technorati/"><em>This is a dummy entry for technorati</em></a><br/>uw5m38jba7
  <br/><a href="/subjects/structuralwebdesign/">Structural web design</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/07/client_side_xslt/"><em>XML on the web, Client Side XSLT and Google</em></a><br/>The market has forced the major browser manufacturers to converge
  on standards. But why are the search engines lagging behind? Browsers are
  capable of AJAX and advanced XML processing, but the search engines are
  still basically just removing tags and presenting raw text extracts.<br/><a href="/subjects/structuralwebdesign/">Structural web design</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/07/opml/"><em>OpenSearch, RSS and OPML as XML Webservices for information
  retrieval</em></a><br/>At the Royal Library we have been working with the building of an
  infrastructure for publishing of digitized material. It is collections of
  digital images, usually with very little textual content to go with it. It
  is quite a challenge to build workflows satisfying the needs of technical
  staff running the scanners, the librararian and editorial staff doing the
  cataloging and the needs for crosswalking metadata from the OPAC and at the
  same time be able to syndicate the material in other services adhering to
  different standards.<br/><a href="/subjects/xmlprocessing/">XML processing</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/colophon/">Colophon</a></td>
      </tr>
    </table>
  </div>
</div>
