<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div>
    <h1 style="font-family: sans-serif; width: 55%; float: left;text-align: left;">Questions after twenty years on the web</h1>
    <p style="width: 38%; float: left;text-align: right">
      <em>
        <strong>
		Sigfrid Lundberg's Stuff,
	      2014-09-14</strong>
      </em>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div style="clear:both;"> </div>
  <div style="width:100%;">
    <div>

      <div style="margin: +1%; width:50%;float:right;">
	<a href="/entries/2014/09/language/readers_according_to_google_analytics.png" title="Readers by contry, according to google analytics.">
	  <img src="/entries/2014/09/language/readers_according_to_google_analytics.png" width="100%" alt="Readers by contry, according to google analytics."/>
	</a>
	<p><small>Figure 1. My largest readership comes from Sweden. However,
	the total number of readers from the rest of the world exceeds my
	Swedish readership. So, I suppose it might still be worthwhile for me
	to write in English.</small></p>
      </div>

      <p>I have had this site since 1995, but the oldest parts are in fact
      from 1994, which makes twenty years of personal presence on the web. I have
      thought about this for a while. For example, should I keep the site
      or just through it away and save a couple of hundred SEK per month?</p>

      <p>I've discussed <a href="/entries/2009/06/why/">why</a> before. After
      that, I decide to keep it several times a year. Whenever I pay the bill
      to my service provider.</p>

      <p>At times I just don't care about the site. I'm up to something
      else. If people have problem with my material not being up-to-date,
      that's their problem.  I don't care</p>

      <p>Although I only periodically care for the stuff I keep here, I've
      thought about if I</p>

      <ol style="margin:+0.5em; list-style-type: lower-roman;">
	<li>should continue with my current hosting and my own (home
	brewed) software.</li>
	<li>should stick to English as its main language, or
	return to my mother tongue Swedish?</li>
      </ol>

      <p>However, now I feel that there are things that is more easy to
      discuss in my native language, and many of my readers should find my
      material more accessible. After all, Swedes are the largest single
      nationality visiting my site. However the total number of readers from
      the rest of the world exceeds my Swedish readership (Figure 1).</p>

      <p>In short, expect more material in Swedish, but I will continue write
      in English whenever I expect that it is worthwhile.</p>

      <p>This means that you shouldn't really expect any significant changes
      here..., and don't ask me why I use several hundred words for telling
      you why I won't make any substantial change.</p>

    </div>
    <br clear="all"/>
    <p style="text-align: left;"><em><strong>Categories:</strong></em> 
	  <a href="/subjects/colophon/">Colophon</a>,
	    <a href="/subjects/internet/">Internet</a><br/><em><strong>
		Permalink:
	      </strong></em><a rel="bookmark" href="/entries/2014/09/language/">http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2014/09/language/</a></p>
    <hr width="50%" align="center"/>
  </div>
  <div>
    <h1>Other, not yet obsolete stuff</h1>
    <table class="news">
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2014-09-03</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2014/09/granite/"><em>Granite is hard</em></a><br/>He sat on his knees and started to penetrate the tiles with hammer
  and chisel<br/><a href="/subjects/essays/">Essays</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/images/">Images</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/photography/">Photography</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2013-09-09</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2013/06/evenwider/"><em>With a full frame sensor my lenses become wider</em></a><br/>This is an addendum to my earlier review of the 15mm Super-Wide
  Heliar lens<br/><a href="/subjects/images/">Images</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/lenses/">Lenses</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/photography/">Photography</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2012-11-18</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2012/07/biogon/"><em>Biogon T* 2,8/25 ZM: Portrait of a lens</em></a><br/>This is one of the very sharpest lenses made by mankind.<br/><a href="/subjects/images/">Images</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/lenses/">Lenses</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/photography/">Photography</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2012-11-18</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2012/07/sonnar/"><em>Zeiss ZM 50mm f1.5 C-Sonnar: Portrait of a lens </em></a><br/>The 50mm Sonnar f1.5 is a transplant from the Contax rangefinder
  world. A real classic there. Also, it is indeed a personality with a
  focus shift.<br/><a href="/subjects/images/">Images</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/lenses/">Lenses</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/photography/">Photography</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2012-11-18</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2012/07/heliar/"><em>Voigtländer 15mm f/4.5 Super Wide Heliar: A portrait of a lens</em></a><br/>Super-wide Heliar was the first M Mount lens I bought. I have used
  it extensively, in particular on my Olympus E-P2. But I still use it over and
over again.<br/><a href="/subjects/images/">Images</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/lenses/">Lenses</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/photography/">Photography</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2012-05-14</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2012/05/colour/"><em>On colour</em></a><br/>When a subject contains vidid colours, I invariably transform the
  photo to black and white. If there are few I usually preserve colour. Unless
  there is special conditions that make me feel that colour is important. For
  instance, when the image contain vivid colours.<br/><a href="/subjects/flickr/">Flickr</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/photography/">Photography</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/images/">Images</a></td>
      </tr>
    </table>
  </div>
</div>
