<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div>
    <h1 style="font-family: sans-serif; width: 55%; float: left;text-align: left;">Drugs and OpenAccess</h1>
    <p style="width: 38%; float: left;text-align: right">
      <em>
        <strong>
		Sigfrid Lundberg's Stuff,
	      2010-03-10</strong>
      </em>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div style="clear:both;"> </div>
  <div style="width:100%;">
    <div>

      <p>In a recent article Theresa Velden &amp; Carl Lagoze
      <em>Communicating chemistry</em>, <a href="http://www.nature.com/nchem/journal/v1/n9/full/nchem.448.html">Nature
      Chemistry 1, 673-678 (2009)</a> discusses how traditions and attitudes
      concerning IPR affect data sharing and how that in turn affects
      scientists propensities to use web 2.0 tools and web of data
      technologies.</p>

      <p>They address the problem why chemists, as opposed to (say) physicists
      and molecular biologists are late adopters of Web 2.0 and
      OpenAccess. These two are entirely different entities. The former is a
      set of technologies and the second is a business model for the
      publishing industry. Nevertheless, they are related.</p>

      <h3>Chemistry is a bit different</h3>

      <p>Chemical and pharmaceutical industry are large employers of
      chemists. Velden &amp; Lagoze mentions that ACS has 155000 members. Of
      them <a href="http://pubs.acs.org/cen/acsnews/87/8710salary.html"> 62%
      works within industry</a>. As a comparison, American physical Society
      has <a href="http://www.aps.org/publications/apsnews/200902/loader.cfm?csModule=security/getfile&amp;pageid=159887">47189
      members (year 2009)</a> but only about <a href="http://www.pas.rochester.edu/urpas/summary_of_aps_report_on_physicists_in_industry">20%
      of them work within industry</a>. On the other hand, the same US source
      claims that 56% of all physics PhDs worked in industry. </p>

      <p>I don't think that the proportion of chemists working within industry
      is high compared with people having training in engineering or computer
      science. However, chemistry should be compared with the other sciences
      not with engineering. Here chemistry appears to be a bit different in
      comparison with physics or earth and life sciences.</p>

      <p>Chemistry is the science where a the largest proportion of all
      researchers just consume scientific publication, but not contribute. It
      should, conclude Velden &amp; Lagoze, not conclude anyone that IPR
      thinking and secrecy more common within chemistry than elsewhere.</p>

      <p>Chemistry has fewer OpenAccess journals than most other part of
      science, and chemists are less interested in social media kind of
      e-science than are most other branches.</p>

      <h3>Infrastructure</h3>

      <p>In spite of this, there are some really interesting developments
      coming from chemistry. Velden &amp; Lagoze mentions</p>

      <blockquote><em>a standardized chemical mark-up language, a computable
      identifier for organic molecules (the IUPAC international chemical
      identifier, or InChI), open-source tools for the manipulation and
      management of chemical information6, and the use of free, hosted Web 2.0
      services to support 'open-notebook science'</em></blockquote>

      <p><a href="http://www.slideshare.net/jcbradley/scholar2scholar-presentation">This
      open lab notebook</a> is interesting. It is fascinating to see how an
      e-science infrastructure makes use of off-the shelf wiki and blog
      software and combine these with storage in Google apps and communicates
      via syndication feeds.</p>

    </div>
    <br clear="all"/>
    <p style="text-align: left;"><em><strong>Categories:</strong></em> 
	  <a href="/subjects/escience/">eScience</a><br/><em><strong>
		Permalink:
	      </strong></em><a rel="bookmark" href="/entries/2010/03/chemistry/">http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2010/03/chemistry/</a></p>
    <hr width="50%" align="center"/>
  </div>
  <div>
    <h1>Other, not yet obsolete stuff</h1>
    <table class="news">
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2010</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2010/03/thinking/"><em>Thinking when the spring is approaching</em></a><br/>Winter is just the worst part of the year. Where approaching the
  end of it.<br/><a href="/subjects/essays/">Essays</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/images/">Images</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2010</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2010/03/solarenergy/"><em>Solar energy</em></a><br/>White reflects radiation from the sun to a larger degree than do
  other colours<br/><a href="/subjects/images/">Images</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2010</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2010/03/bash/"><em>Bourne Again Shell</em></a><br/>The Bourne Again Shell is a prominent part of my life. Dark moments
  I've felt that I'm obsoleted by modern technologies, but all of a sudden I
  realised that I'm as modern as smarphone users<br/><a href="/subjects/images/">Images</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2010</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2010/03/aformwithajoin/"><em>A form with a join</em></a><br/>A form is a document, or part of one, that can be used for the
  entry of data. A join is a construct in query languages such SQL. A join
  allows you to lookup data in one part of a database based on a query in an
  other part. Joins are very general, and may appear in other contexts. Such
  as the XML forms language.<br/><a href="/subjects/xmlprocessing/">XML processing</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/metadataprocessing/">Metadata processing</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2010</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2010/02/youdontneed/"><em>Why you need a persistence strategy</em></a><br/>Here I go through some of the arguments why you need to implement a
  persistence strategy. We also conclude that the hypertext link is the single
  thing that makes the Worldwide web to a web. Hence it is a serious thing. If
  you're working within the digital library world you should be devoted to the
  hypertext link.<br/><a href="/subjects/structuralwebdesign/">Structural web design</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/internet/">Internet</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2010</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2010/02/persid/"><em>The URN:NBN is dead and resurrection is meaningless</em></a><br/>I'm one of those who try to base all decisions on facts. Politics
  belong to the strategic field, and in that field the only thing I can offer
  is advice.<br/><a href="/subjects/structuralwebdesign/">Structural web design</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/internet/">Internet</a></td>
      </tr>
    </table>
  </div>
</div>
