<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div>
    <h1 style="font-family: sans-serif; width: 55%; float: left;text-align: left;">Digital Representation and the Text Model</h1>
    <p style="width: 38%; float: left;text-align: right">
      <em>
        <strong>
		Sigfrid Lundberg's Stuff,
	      2010-04-09</strong>
      </em>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div style="clear:both;"> </div>
  <div style="width:100%;">
    <div>

      <p>Dino Buzzetti, 2002. Digital Representation and the Text Model.<em>New
      Literary History</em>, 33(1), p. 61-88.  <a href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/pdfplus/20057710.pdf">http://www.jstor.org/stable/pdfplus/20057710.pdf</a></p>

      <p>I found this article by searching for <q>Ordered Hierarchy of
      Content Objects</q> (OHCO) in Google Scholar.</p>

      <p>The study and use of the theory and methodologies of text is
      either very practical, i.e., deployed by people attempting to use it for
      producing digital editions or text collections. It can also be extremely
      theoretical, i.e., used by people proving that it is impossible to
      represent using such crude technologies such stronly embedded markup
      languages, such as Text Encoding Initiative XML.</p>

      <p>It should not suprise you that the people discussing OHCO belong to
      the latter category. It is those who perceive problems that need to name
      them.</p>

      <h3>Bumblebees and the theory of text</h3>

      <p>I am writing code for my living. I spend most of my time on practical
      problems. I'm about as interested in the intricacies of the theory of
      text as I am in flight mechanics theories proving that bumblebees are
      unable to fly.</p>

      <p>However, if you want a really good discussion about text, you have to
      turn to these contributions. They are written by people that are just as
      smart as the students of flight mechanics. Recently they managed to
      prove that bumblebees can fly which required more sofisticated
      mathematics and data. That is, it required new knowledge.</p>

      <p>Buzzettis contribution is a classic in the area. It was published
      2002, but that version is a translation. The original was published
      in Italian 1999. That means that it was written somewhere in the interval
      1997-1999. That means that he might have started his research before XML
      even were a recommendation. Most of the tools we use today where not
      even on the drawing board. When he offers criticism against markup
      languages, he talks exclusively about SGML, the precursor of XML -- the
      much extended subset of SGML.</p>

      <h3>The Map isn't the Landscape</h3>

      <p>Anything which somehow depicts something else can be said to be
      model, like a globe is a model of the earth. Buzetti focus two aspects
      of any model of a text.</p>

      <ol>
	<li>the information represented</li>
	<li>the represention of the information</li>
      </ol>

      <p>The first aspect is called the <em>content</em> of the text, whereas
      the second is referred to as an <em>expression</em> of it. For example,
      assume that you want to preserve a MS Word document. One way would be to
      <q>print</q> it to a file and transform that to a (i) high resolution
      bitmap as a (say) tif or jpeg2000. You could also export it as (ii)
      ASCII text. The former would be an expression of the text and the latter
      would be its content.</p>

      <p>The conventional wisdom says that we have two aspects of a text, its
      form and its content. Buzzetti doesn't mention this dichotomy at
      all. Rather, he says that an expression as well as the content may have
      a <em>form</em> and a <em>substance</em>. In his parlance, an
      <em>edition</em> is the set of the various contents and expressions
      available that can be linked to work. The edition may then represented
      by <em>interpretations</em>, that may be seen as expressions or
      content.</p>

      <h3>Embedded vs. external encoding</h3>

      <p>Buzzetti is very much against the use of SGML. I will not go into his
      discussion of the lack of datamodels connected to the the markup, since
      the explosive development of XML technologies make that part of his
      criticism obsolete. The Document Object Model api supported by all major
      programming languages is just one of many answers to that critique.</p>

      <p>Buzzetti makes a distinction between strong and weak embedded
      markup. Languages that embed marks both at the beginning and at the end
      of character sequences inside a text are strongly embedded. Those that
      mark onsets are weakly embedded. Buzzetti is against strong embedding,
      but claims that text encoding ideally should be done without any
      embedded markup. By using that you blur the distincion between the
      form of substance.</p>

      <p>The ideal form of text encoding is to store the offsets, string
      lengths and corresponding semantics externally. Doing encoding this way
      you may support as many overlapping hierarchies of content objects your
      heart may desire. No hierarchy need to be given more importance all of
      them are are equal.</p>

      <h3>Buzzetti is right, but...</h3>

      <p>TEI doesn't do things this way. It isn't because Buzzetti isn't
      right. I'm sure he is. We who do text encoding thought that SGML was
      good enough. Now we think that XML is OK and practical to use.</p>

      <p>The designers of TEI choose to give a priority to the logical
      structure of the texts we are encoding. That is, since we are allowed to
      have one single hierarchy, we use it for encoding the content. I.e., the
      chapters, sections, paragraphs and phrases. We don't use it for pages,
      lines and characters which belong to the expression. We regard the page
      and line breaks as points in the character stream and add empty tags for
      them. These empty tags are called <em>milestones</em>. If we accept some
      computational difficulties we can encode a lot using this machinery.</p>

      <p>But, yes, our encoded text is an expression of the content, and we
      limited the number of possible interpretations of the text.</p>

      <p>This entry is part of my series <a href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2010/04/readings/">Readings on
      digital objects</a></p>

    </div>
    <br clear="all"/>
    <p style="text-align: left;"><em><strong>Categories:</strong></em> 
	  <a href="/subjects/textencoding/">Text encoding</a>,
	    <a href="/subjects/digitalobjects/">Digital objects</a><br/><em><strong>
		Permalink:
	      </strong></em><a rel="bookmark" href="/entries/2010/04/buzzetti/">http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2010/04/buzzetti/</a></p>
    <hr width="50%" align="center"/>
  </div>
  <div>
    <h1>Other, not yet obsolete stuff</h1>
    <table class="news">
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2010</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2010/03/teimime/"><em>application/tei+xml</em></a><br/>We are about to register a mime type for TEI. This page tracks the
  progress of that effort<br/><a href="/subjects/internet/">Internet</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2010</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2010/04/kahnframework/"><em>A framework for distributed digital object services</em></a><br/>Robert Kahn and Robert Wilensky, 2006. A framework for distributed
  digital object services<br/><a href="/subjects/digitalobjects/">Digital objects</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/objectstores/">Digital object stores</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2010</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2010/04/readings/"><em>Readings on digital objects: An annotated URIography</em></a><br/>I have a long list of articles to read on digital objects, how to
  model them etc. This page is for keeping track of my progress<br/><a href="/subjects/digitalcollections/">Digital collections</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/digitalobjects/">Digital objects</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2010</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2010/04/votives/"><em>Recycled Votive Guitar on the Compost</em></a><br/>A view of a cemetary<br/><a href="/subjects/images/">Images</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2010</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2010/04/subscriptions/"><em>A Safari among Subscription Libraries</em></a><br/>I have been a subscriber to O'Reilly's Safari services for quite
  some years now. Recently I upgraded the subscription such that I get access
  to the entire stock without limitations.<br/><a href="/subjects/thelibrary/">The Library</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2010</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2010/04/smiley/"><em>George Smiley and libraries</em></a><br/>I'm an ardent John le Carré reader. In particular I'm very fond of
  the books about George Smiley.<br/><a href="/subjects/essays/">Essays</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/musiclanglit/">Music, language &amp; literature</a></td>
      </tr>
    </table>
  </div>
</div>
