<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div>
    <h1 style="width: 58%; float: left;text-align: leftt">On being an international commuter</h1>
    <p style="width: 38%; float: left;text-align: right">
      <em>
        <strong>
		Sigfrid Lundberg's Stuff,
	      2009-07-21</strong>
      </em>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div style="clear:both;"> </div>
  <div style="width:100%;">
    <div>

      <p>In both Lund and Copenhagen there are a lot of people riding their
      bicycles. They behave very differently, however, and their spatial
      distribution is different. In Copenhagen the riders have a much more
      aggregated distribution. They ride at high speed in herds, somewhat like
      Mongolian cavalry. Before their attacks against the pedestrians, their
      primary targets, the Copenhagen bicycle riders congregate at traffic
      lights. In Lund, where the where the density of traffic lights is lower,
      we bicycle riders tend to have a more solitary life style.</p>

      <p>Currently I usually leave home ten past seven. That gives me ample of
      time to catch the 07.39 train from Lund to Copenhagen. Except for
      occasional encounters with dog owners and an increasing number of power
      walking young ladies that, trip is uneventful. When it isn't
      raining. The power walkers look as if they hate walking; they seem to be
      in a terrible hurry to get home for a shower and a nice slow
      breakfast. I don't blame them. For some reason, the power walking ladies
      never appear when it is raining, as far as I can tell from the bus.</p>

      <img src="/galleri/200907-200907/smaller/cimg1352.jpg" style="margin-left:0.5em;float:left;margin-right:0.5em;" alt="Secure locking is essential"/>

      <p>The only really serious problem is to find a secure parking place for
      my bike. A lot of fellow bicycle riders who park there have lost their
      vehicles there, through theft. I've recently aquired a new bike, since
      my previous one was stolen outside our home. The first temporal
      bottle-neck is to lock the thing. I've got two solid locks, and try to
      park where I can use one of them for locking the bike to an iron
      structure (see the image).</p>

      <p>That would describe the normal sequence of events, but right now they
      replacing 12 kilometers of tracks. Hence the railway which is normally
      double track is now running on half its normal capacity. I could dwell
      on the inconvinience caused by this, but I'll spare you that pain. The
      normal state of affairs is that I after about an hour on the train</p>
      
    </div>
    <p style="text-align: right">
      <em>
        <strong>
		Permalink:
	      </strong>
      </em>
      <a rel="bookmark" href="/entries/2009/07/commuting/">http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/07/commuting/</a>
    </p>
    <hr width="50%" align="center"/>
  </div>
  <div>
    <h1>Other, not yet obsolete stuff</h1>
    <table class="news">
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/07/xslt_extensions/"><em>Why I love XSLT extension functions</em></a><br/>xslt extensions allow you to define xpath functions and extension
  elements. That makes it easy for you to perform tasks within xslt that are
  just only theoretically possible to do.<br/><a href="/subjects/xmlprocessing/">XML processing</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/07/structure/"><em>The description and encoding of structure</em></a><br/>Much metadata is fairly stright forward. A book does have a title
  and an author. That's usually no big deal. We've been able to handle that
  for centuries. A digital book has chapters, and everything you might want to
  know may be in chapter two on page seventyfive. Or someone may tell you the
  solution to your problems after a quarter of an hour in some video on
  YouTube. Now, how do we cope with this?<br/><a href="/subjects/structuralwebdesign/">Structural web design</a>,
	<a href="/subjects/metadata/">Metadata</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/07/escience/"><em>Will the research libraries play a role in e-science</em></a><br/>I was asked to participate in an e-science pilot project.  The work
  in the project has been food for thought for me. Will libraries be a part of
  a future eScience infrastructure?<br/><a href="/subjects/escience/">eScience</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/07/victory/"><em>The predator rests on its prey</em></a><br/>I've seen this image before. An excavator has demolished a
  building, and has then proudly been parked on top of the remnants.<br/><a href="/subjects/essays/">Essays</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/07/technorati/"><em>This is a dummy entry for technorati</em></a><br/>uw5m38jba7
  <br/><a href="/subjects/structuralwebdesign/">Structural web design</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/07/client_side_xslt/"><em>XML on the web, Client Side XSLT and Google</em></a><br/>The market has forced the major browser manufacturers to converge
  on standards. But why are the search engines lagging behind? Browsers are
  capable of AJAX and advanced XML processing, but the search engines are
  still basically just removing tags and presenting raw text extracts.<br/><a href="/subjects/structuralwebdesign/">Structural web design</a></td>
      </tr>
    </table>
  </div>
</div>
