<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div>
    <h1 style="font-family: sans-serif; width: 55%; float: left;text-align: left;">An Irish Stew</h1>
    <p style="width: 38%; float: left;text-align: right">
      <em>
        <strong>
		Sigfrid Lundberg's Stuff,
	      2010-02-14</strong>
      </em>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div style="clear:both;"> </div>
  <div style="width:100%;">
    <div>

      <p>An earlier version of this entry had the title: <em>Social media,
      Google adwords and the curation of digital refuse</em>. However, it
      would be misleading call this document a version of the text I planned
      to write.</p>

      <p>I just couldn't get the various threads in place and write a single
      text with a neat take home message. Instead, the result is a relatively
      shallow annotated URIography, rather than a deep analysis of some
      current trends in the evolution of the Internet and the western
      societies. Sorry.</p>
      
      <h3>Power Sites</h3>

      <p>A site which <q cite="http://www.tbray.org/ongoing/When/201x/2010/01/19/Power-Web-Site">is
      designed as the primary Web property for a person, place, or thing is a
      power site</q>, <a href="http://www.tbray.org/ongoing/When/201x/2010/01/19/Power-Web-Site">says
      Tim Bray</a>, <q>if the person, place, or thing has a Wikipedia entry
      but, in popular search engines, the site ranks above that Wikipedia
      entry.</q></p>

      <p>Tim Bray's own blog is a power site, my stuff isn't. I have no
      Wikipedia entry ;-). Power sites are assets these days, if you put
      adverts on the, that is.</p>


      <h3>Power Universities and Researchers</h3>

      <p>Lorcan Dempsey, whose blog is also a Power Site, discusses a number
      of social technology sites <a href="http://orweblog.oclc.org/archives/002011.html">for research
      information</a>, complete with friends and ranking etc.</p>

      <p>I <strong>like</strong> facebook for scientific papers. Do you
      <strong>like</strong> too?.</p>

      <p>The <a href="http://ouseful.wordpress.com/">Ouseful blog</a>
      discusses <a href="http://ouseful.wordpress.com/2010/02/13/virtual-revolution-google-economics/">google
      economics and page ranks</a>, while <a href="http://www.timeshighereducation.co.uk/story.asp?sectioncode=26&amp;storycode=408908&amp;navcode=105">The
      Times Higher Education</a> has ranked universities for years. That is a
      not enough, obviously, since <a href="http://science.thomsonreuters.com/globalprofilesproject/gpp-opinion/">Thomson
      Reuters</a> and <a href="http://informatics.indiana.edu/scholmet09/announcement.html">NSF
      follow suit.</a>.</p>

      <h3>Content farming</h3>

      <p>During the year 2009 we saw the advent of the <a href="http://www.readwriteweb.com/archives/content_farms_impact.php">content
      farms</a>. It is fairly easy to rapidly aggregate content by archiving
      mailing lists, RSS feeds etc. Adding Google Ads you get a business model
      as well. There's good reason to be worried, in particular for Google. A
      few other voices:

      <a href="http://www.readwriteweb.com/archives/how_google_can_combat_content_farms.php">Combat
      content farms</a>, <a href="http://techcrunch.com/2009/12/13/the-end-of-hand-crafted-content/">The
      rise of fast food content is upon us, and it’s going to get ugly</a> and
      <a href="http://www.buzzmachine.com/2009/12/14/content-farms-v-curating-farmers/">curating
      farmers</a>.</p>

      <h3>Books and parasites</h3>

      <p>To my knowledge, Jacob Nielsen was the first to describe the <a href="http://www.useit.com/alertbox/search_engines.html">parasitic
      nature of the search engine's business model</a>. The dilemma is that
      without the search engine, noone would find your pages and with the
      search engine noone will click on ads on your pages. More recently there
      has been discussions on how people will be able to survive as
      journalists and authors on a market where content farms and real news
      sites generate about as much revenue. See Charles Stross' <a href="http://www.antipope.org/charlie/blog-static/2010/01/the-monetization-paradox-or-wh.html">The
      monetization paradox (or why Google is not my friend)</a>.
      </p>

      <h3>Pointless babble</h3>

      <p>Tim O'Reilly &amp; Sarah Milstein have written <a href="http://oreilly.com/catalog/9780596802820">The Twitter Book</a>. I
      haven't read it, but then I have to confess I'm no Twitter Power
      user. I'm not even a user.</p>

      <p>Bill Heil and Mikolaj Piskorski <a href="http://blogs.hbr.org/cs/2009/06/new_twitter_research_men_follo.html">describe
      recent results from their research on Twitter</a>. They are really
      interesting and some of them are surprising, such as that the top 10% of
      prolific Twitter users accounted for over 90% of the tweets. These
      numbers are very much more aggregated than for social internet sites in
      general, where the top 10% accounts for about 30% of the activity. The
      same study shows that men follows men to a very large extent, and also
      that woman follows men more than other women but that they are more
      <q>equal</q> in their preferences. (see also <a href="http://www.businessweek.com/innovate/NussbaumOnDesign/archives/2009/06/twitter_hype_or.html">twitter
      hype or, businessweek.com</a>).</p>

      <p>One study shows that many <q>people still perceive Twitter as just
      mindless babble of people telling you what they are doing
      minute-by-minute</q> and that the tweets is written in <q>self-promotion
      with very few folks actually paying attention</q> (<a href="http://www.pearanalytics.com/blog/2009/twitter-study-reveals-interesting-results-40-percent-pointless-babble/">Pointless babble</a>)</p>

      <h3>There is a single theme</h3>

      <p>I feel that there is a single theme in all this. There are problems
      here. There are needs for business models and new methods for
      monetization. We need that as well, we in the library business. Perhaps
      a public service model could make a difference?</p>



    </div>
    <p style="text-align: left;"><em><strong>Categories:</strong></em> 
	  <a href="/subjects/internet/">Internet</a><br/><em><strong>
		Permalink:
	      </strong></em><a rel="bookmark" href="/entries/2010/01/crossroad/">http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2010/01/crossroad/</a></p>
    <hr width="50%" align="center"/>
  </div>
  <div>
    <h1>Other, not yet obsolete stuff</h1>
    <table class="news">
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2010</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2010/01/dusk/"><em>Reflections on a Library at Dusk</em></a><br/>During my soon five years at The Royal Library, I've seen its
  exterior in all kinds of weather conditions. Here I give you some images
  showing the spectacular black granite fasade at dusk.<br/><a href="/subjects/essays/">Essays</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/07/commuting/"><em>On being an international commuter</em></a><br/>The last four years I've spent more than two hours a day on
  trains. And usually, but not always less than three. Furthermore, I go from
  one nation to another and participate in the in the digital dissemination of
  cultural heritage of a country which isn't my own.<br/><a href="/subjects/essays/">Essays</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/11/kbmetadta/"><em>Fifteen polar bears and one architecture</em></a><br/>Today I gave a presentation on our metadata work. My experience of
  that turned out to be about images.<br/><a href="/subjects/metadata/">Metadata</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/10/programming/"><em>The specification and the TODO-list</em></a><br/>Through the web, a software vendor and a service provider could all
  of a sudden compete on the same market. The software vendor use the
  traditional specification, but a service implies software which is in
  continuous development. Strictly speaking, there are no projects anymore,
  just different activities. No specifications anymore, but TODO lists
  containing incidents, bugs and requests for features ranked by
  importance.<br/><a href="/subjects/programming/">Programming</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/11/twocultures/"><em>The two Cultures</em></a><br/>Do you know the second law of thermodynamics?<br/><a href="/subjects/programming/">Programming</a></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td class="left">2009</td>
        <td class="left"><a href="/entries/2009/10/webdevelopment/"><em>What about the HECS platforms?</em></a><br/>I've used fortran, pascal, C, perl, php and java in addition to
  more specialized tools such as SQL and XSLT. There is currently a lot of
  discussions on what platform will be the next winner.<br/><a href="/subjects/programming/">Programming</a></td>
      </tr>
    </table>
  </div>
</div>
