<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>Sigfrid Lundberg's Stuff</title>
  <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/files.atom</id>
  <link rel="self" href="/files.atom"/>
  <updated>2006-06-08T00:03:00+01:00</updated>
  <!--
      $Revision$, last modified $Date$
      $Id$
  -->
  <entry>
    <title>NWI — En nordisk söktjänst för World Wide Web</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Anders Ardö</name>
    </author>
    <link href="/1996/nwi/press_release.html"/>
    <summary>Ett konsortium av nordiska forskningsbibliotek och nätverksorgan
    presenterar Nordiskt Webindex, en nordisk söktjänst utvecklad i norden för
    en nordisk publik. I dag finns en experimentell tjänst offentligt
    tillgänglig på nätet på URL http://nwi.ub2.lu.se.</summary>
    <category term="Web indexing" label="webindexing"/>
    <category term="Harvesting" label="harvesting"/>
    <dc:date>1996</dc:date>
    <updated>2006-06-08T00:03:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/1996/nwi/nwi.pdf</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>A proposal for metadata formats for use in the Swedish Enviro-Net</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <link href="/1997/SMN_metadata/smn_metadata.pdf"/>
    <summary>This paper outlines a combination of the Dublin Core metadata
    embedded in HTML metadata tags and the GILS Z39.50 profile used for
    information retrieval. It is a combination would solve the distributed
    indexing, search and retrieval problems within a network of environmental
    authorities. The Swedish Enviro-Net lived for a few years at the end of
    1990ties.</summary>
    <category term="Web indexing" label="webindexing"/>
    <category term="Metadata" label="metadata"/>
    <category term="Z39.50" label="z3950"/>
    <dc:date>1997</dc:date>
    <updated>2006-06-08T00:04:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/1997/SMN_metadata/smn_metadata.pdf</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Kulturnät Sverige</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <link href="/1997/kultur_naet_sverige/"/>
    <summary>En recension av IT i kulturens tjänst, SOU 1997:14 som i mina
    ögon vid den tidpunkten var en fullständigt överflödig utredning. Här
    fanns alla möjligheter att börja arbeta för en konvergens när det gäller
    beskrivningsstandard och protokoll för informationsretrieval mellan olika
    grenar av kultursektorn. En tjock bok som ledde fram till en numera
    nerlagd ämnesportal.</summary>
    <dc:date>1997</dc:date>
    <updated>2009-06-08T00:05:00+01:00</updated>
    <category term="Digital collections" label="digitalcollections"/>
    <category term="Reviews" label="reviews"/>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/1997/kultur_naet_sverige/</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Kulturarw3 archiving format</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg, Lund University</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Allan Arvidson, The Royal Library</name>
    </author>
    <link href="/1998/KulturArw3/archive-format-1.rtf"/>
    <summary>This note describes a file format intended for the joint storage of
    objects retrieved from the World Wide Web and various kinds of meta
    information on those objects. The information includes the HTTP response
    header but may also contain information needed for version control etc
    within the archive. Kulturarw3 project proposes an archiving record format
    based on open standards, namely that objects are stored as HTTP MIME
    multpart/mixed messages (cf. RFC2068 and RFC1521 respectively).</summary>
    <dc:date>1997</dc:date>
    <updated>2006-06-08T00:07:00+01:00</updated>
    <category term="Digital preservation" label="preservation"/>
    <category term="Harvesting" label="harvesting"/>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/1998/KulturArw3/archive-format-1.rtf</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>NWI II, An Enhanced Nordic Web index: Final report</title>
    <author><name>Anders Ardö</name></author>
    <author><name>Allan Arvidson</name></author>
    <author><name>Sebastian Hammer</name></author>
    <author><name>Kenneth Holmlund</name></author>
    <author><name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name></author>
    <link href="/1998/nwi2/"/>
    <summary>The Nordic Web Index (NWI) project is a collaborative effort
    across the Nordic countries, aiming at providing a free Worldwide Web
    search service to the general public in the countries involved. NWI has
    been fruitful for several reasons: First and foremost we are today
    providing access to databases covering the WWW in four of the Nordic
    countries and, as of September 1998, five service points in six languages
    Denmark, Finland, Sweden, Norway and Iceland.</summary>
    <category term="Web indexing" label="webindexing"/>
    <category term="Harvesting" label="harvesting"/>
    <category term="Metadata" label="metadata"/>
    <category term="Z39.50" label="z3950"/>
    <dc:date>1998</dc:date>
    <updated>2006-06-08T00:08:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/1998/nwi2/</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>En arkitektur för ett distribuerat system för spridning av
    forskningsinformation</title>
    <link href="/1998/safari/cris.pdf"/>
    <summary>Arkitekturen för ett nätverk av tjänster för spridning av
    forskningsinformation beskrivs. Nätverket tillåter distribuerat underhåll
    av såväl data som metadata. Till nätverket kan anslutas såväl
    bibliografiska databaser som helt WWWbaserade metadataberikade
    tjänster. Metadataproduktionen följer standarden Dublin Core. De förra
    typerna av tjänster inkorporeras i nätverket genom interoperabilitet på
    sökprotokollsnivå, medan metadata och fulltext från de senare göres
    sökbara genom en WWWrobot.  Kommunikation inom nätverket utnyttjar
    standardiserade Internet protokoll som HTTP, och för
    informationsåtervinning Z39.50</summary>
    <category term="Web indexing" label="webindexing"/>
    <category term="Harvesting" label="harvesting"/>
    <category term="Metadata" label="metadata"/>
    <category term="Z39.50" label="z3950"/>
    <dc:date>1998</dc:date>
    <updated>2006-06-08T00:10:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/1998/safari/cris.pdf</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>A regional distributed WWW search and indexing service - the DESIRE
    way</title>
    <link href="/1998/www7/"/>
    <summary>In an attempt to implement a regional search engine we have
    created an open, metadata aware system for distributed, collaborative
    WWW-indexing. The system has three main components: a harvester (for
    collecting information), a database (for making the collection
    searchable), and a user interface (for making the information
    available). All components can be distributed across networked computers,
    thus supporting scalability. The system is metadata aware and thus allows
    searches on several fields including title, document author, and
    URL. Nordic Web Index (NWI) is an application using this system to create
    a regional Nordic web-indexing service. NWI is built using five
    collaborating service points within the Nordic countries. The NWI
    databases can be used to build additional services. Services today include
    special metadata databases, multimedia databases, and statistics about the
    Nordic Web.</summary>
    <category term="Web indexing" label="webindexing"/>
    <category term="Harvesting" label="harvesting"/>
    <category term="Metadata" label="metadata"/>
    <category term="Z39.50" label="z3950"/>
    <dc:date>1998</dc:date>
    <updated>2008-06-08T00:10:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/1998/www7/</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Noble Art of Being Indexed or the Webmaster's Guide to
    Harvesting Robots</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Lars Nooden</name>
    </author>
    <link href="/1999/web_masters_guide/"/>
    <summary>As the title indicates, this is a note on how to be indexed by
    search engines. It is obsolete. Please note that it does not contain
    anything about search engine optimization in the modern evil
    sense. Instead it pinpoints what harvesting robots did understand, and what
    they didn't at the turn of the last century.</summary>
    <category term="Web indexing" label="webindexing"/>
    <category term="Metadata" label="metadata"/>
    <category term="Structural web design" label="structuralwebdesign"/>
    <dc:date>1999</dc:date>
    <updated>2006-06-09T00:11:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/1999/web_masters_guide/</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Metadata harvesting</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <link href="/2000/delft/"/>
    <summary>This is unfortunately unpublished, but it presents most one of
    the most extensive datasets on the content of HTML embedded metadata which
    I collected while working with the Nordic Webindex.</summary>
    <category term="Web indexing" label="webindexing"/>
    <category term="Harvesting" label="harvesting"/>
    <category term="Metadata" label="metadata"/>
    <category term="Z39.50" label="z3950"/>
    <dc:date>2000</dc:date>
    <updated>2006-06-09T15:11:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/2000/delft/</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Technical description of the Studera.Nu search engine Harvesting
    policies, maintenance and software used</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <link href="/2001/studera.nu/documentation/studera.pdf"/>
    <summary>This is a description of the Studera.NU search engine in the very
    first version. The search engine carries focused information, all of which is
    indexed manually by content providers. The indexing information is
    embedded into web pages using meta tags, and the service is built using a
    harvesting robot.  This article documents the functions of the search
    engine Studera.NU, its robot, search software etc. It aims at providing
    necessary background information both for staff involved in system
    management and future developers. A second aim is to give pinpoint areas
    for future developments of the service.</summary>
    <category term="Web indexing" label="webindexing"/>
    <category term="Harvesting" label="harvesting"/>
    <category term="Metadata" label="metadata"/>
    <dc:date>2001</dc:date>
    <updated>2009-06-09T00:18:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/2001/studera.nu/documentation/studera.pdf</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Lecture notes: S:t Laurentius Digital Manuscript Library</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <link href="/2002/DRH2002/toc.html"/>
    <summary>In this lecture, I discussed the
    experiences gained by the development of a specific service, which, using
    a collection of detailed XML descriptions, provides its users access to a
    collection of digitized medieval manuscripts.  Secondly, I discussed the
    database used from the point of view of both retrieval of the intellectual
    content (the texts) of these manuscripts and of the retrieval of the
    manuscripts as unique entities. Finally, I turned to the possibilities for
    searching a collection of complex XML documents using a full text
    retrieval engine used together with the Z39.50 information retrieval
    protocol.</summary>
    <dc:date>2002</dc:date>
    <category term="XML processing" label="xmlprocessing"/>
    <category term="Metadata" label="metadata"/>
    <category term="Digital humanities" label="ehumanities"/>
    <category term="Digitization" label="digitization"/>
    <updated>2009-06-11T00:06:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/2002/DRH2002/toc.html</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>S:t Laurentius Digital Manuscript Library: An excursion along the
    border between resource discovery and resource description</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <link href="/2002/Laurentius/laurentius.pdf"/>
    <summary>This note has three aims. First it discusses the experiences
    gained by the development of a specific service, which, using a collection
    of detailed XML descriptions, provides its users access to a collection
    of digitized medieval manuscripts.  Secondly, it discusses the database
    used from the point of view of both retrieval of the intellectual content
    (the texts) of these manuscripts and of the retrieval of the manuscripts
    as unique entities. Finally, it explores the possibilities for searching
    a collection of complex XML documents using a full text retrieval engine
    used together with the Z39.50 information retrieval protocol.</summary>
    <dc:date>2002</dc:date>
    <category term="XML processing" label="xmlprocessing"/>
    <category term="Text encoding" label="textencoding"/>
    <category term="Metadata" label="metadata"/>
    <category term="Digital humanities" label="ehumanities"/>
    <category term="Digitization" label="digitization"/>
    <updated>2009-06-11T00:19:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/2002/Laurentius/laurentius.pdf</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Förslag till policy för digitaliseringsprojekt inom Lunds
    Universitets Bibliotek</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <link href="/2002/DigitaliseringsPolicy/digitaliserings_policy.pdf"/>
    <summary>Digital arkivering är att bereda serverplats för information om
    oss, vår tid och vår historia för våra barn och deras efterkommande. Detta
    dokument beskriver förutsättningarna för digitalisering, lagring och
    arkivering samt elektronisk publicering av olika samlingar inom Lunds
    universitet och dess bibliotek. Särskild vikt läggs vid att utveckla en
    nansieringsmodell för lagring, tillgängliggörande och bevarande.</summary>
    <dc:date>2002</dc:date>
    <category term="Digitization" label="digitization"/>
    <category term="Digital collections" label="digitalcollections"/>
    <updated>2009-06-11T00:18:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/2002/DigitaliseringsPolicy/digitaliserings_policy.pdf</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Metadata model in Scripta Academica Lundensis</title>
    <author>
      <name>Colm Doyle</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Jörgen Eriksson</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Sara Kjellberg</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Tomas Schönthal</name>
    </author>
    <link href="/2002/Scripta/"/>
    <summary>This document specifies the metadata once used in the Lund university
    dissertation database.</summary>
    <category term="Digital collections" label="digitalcollections"/>
    <category term="XML processing" label="xmlprocessing"/>
    <category term="Metadata" label="metadata"/>
    <dc:date>2002</dc:date>
    <updated>2009-06-12T00:20:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/2002/Scripta/</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>XML -- en mjuk start för biblioteksfolk Mitt ständigt ofärdiga
    undervisningsmaterial (...och en del annat)</title>
    <link href="/2003/XMLforLibrarians/"/>

    <summary>Denna text syftar till att ge en överblick över vissa områden av
    det digitala biblioteksområdet vilka är stadda i snabb utveckling. En
    utveckling som i hög grad katalyseras av utvecklingen av olika
    tillämpningar av eXtensible Markup Language, XML, som i år fyller fem år.
    Utöver användningen av XML inom det digitala biblioteksväsendet ges en
    överblick över modernt tänkande när det gäller metadata, hur XML kan
    tänkas påverka hur vi tar del av, och hanterar elektroniska texter både i
    form av digitalt bevarande och publicering av t ex
    forskningsrapporter.</summary>

    <category term="XML processing" label="xmlprocessing"/>
    <category term="Text encoding" label="textencoding"/>
    <category term="Metadata" label="metadata"/>
    <dc:date>2002</dc:date>
    <updated>2006-06-11T00:21:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/2003/XMLforLibrarians/</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Implementering av OAI-PMH i ett bibliotekssystem -- Några ord på
    vägen</title>
    <link href="/2003/axiell-oai/oai-opac.pdf"/>
    <summary>Syftet med denna text är att ge lite kött på benen om vad OAI-PMH
    är, vad det kan användas till och hur det skulle kunna integreras i ett
    bibliotekssystem. Det är inte en ersättning för andra dokument utan skall
    ses som några ord på vägen för organisationer som planerar att eller är i
    färd med att implementera OAI-PMH. Texten skrevs på uppdrag av
    http://www.axiell.se/bookit</summary>
    <updated>2009-06-09T08:08:00+01:00</updated>
    <dc:date>2003</dc:date>
    <category term="Harvesting" label="harvesting"/>
    <category term="Metadata" label="metadata"/>
    <category term="Library catalogues" label="opac"/>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/2003/axiell-oai/oai-opac.pdf</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Teknisk samverkan mellan svenska ämnesportaler - Test och
    utvärdering av portalprogramvaran TKL</title>
    <author>
      <name>Colm Doyle</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Jörgen Eriksson</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Tomas Schönthal</name>
    </author>
    <summary>En utvärdering av digital library produkten Keystone DLS (TKL)</summary>
    <link href="/2003/def-test/"/>
    <updated>2009-06-09T08:23:00+01:00</updated>
    <dc:date>2003</dc:date>
    <category term="Digital collections" label="digitalcollections"/>
    <category term="Metadata" label="metadata"/>
    <category term="Reviews" label="reviews"/>
    <category term="XML processing" label="xmlprocessing"/>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/2003/def-test/</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Vad är ett PEK?</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <summary>Här rapporterar jag en konvergent språklig utveckling mellan
    forskare och internerna på Långholmen. I båda kategorierna används ordet
    "pek" för att beskriva en kommunikation, bland akademiker var det på
    1980-talet slang för "uppsats" och på Långholmen var det en text som
    skickades med linbana längs med fängelsemurarna.</summary>
    <link href="/2003/pek/"/>
    <dc:date>2003</dc:date>
    <updated>2009-06-09T20:25:00+01:00</updated>
    <category term="Music, language &amp; literature" label="musiclanglit"/>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/2003/pek/</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Pesistent länkning och digitala bibliotek</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <summary>Åtskillig uppmärksamhet har nyligen riktats mot problemen
    förknippade med att uppnå en stabilare webb. Det konstateras, helt
    korrekt, att mängder med dokument bara försvinner från sina ursprungliga
    platser. Vad skall man då göra åt saken? Vad är det för grundläggande
    designproblem som gör att organisationer vilka underhåller länksamlingar
    av olika slag tvingas bära en allt tyngre börda?</summary>
    <link href="/2003/urnar_och_digitala_bibliotek/"/>
    <dc:date>2003</dc:date>
    <updated>2009-06-09T20:36:00+01:00</updated>
    <category term="Digital libraries" label="digitallibraries"/>
    <category term="Metadata" label="metadata"/>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/2003/urnar_och_digitala_bibliotek/</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Ediffah – En digital infrastruktur för forskningsbibliotekens
    arkiv- och handskriftssamlingar</title>
    <link href="/2004/arkiv_bibliotek/"/>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <summary>Projektet syftar till att göra det möjligt att att skapa skapa
    allmänt tillgängliga kataloger och arkivbeskrivningar över bibliotekens
    handskriftssamlingar och personarkiv. Systemet skall vara enkelt, och
    innehålla ett arbetsflöde sådant att posterna som genereras också med
    automatik kan återfinnas i Nationella arkivdatabasen NAD, vårt
    gemensamma bibliotekssystem LIBRIS, såväl som i lokala
    databaser.</summary>
    <dc:date>2004</dc:date>
    <category term="Archival description" label="archivaldescription"/>
    <category term="Metadata" label="metadata"/>
    <category term="XML processing" label="xmlprocessing"/>
    <updated>2009-06-09T20:36:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/2004/arkiv_bibliotek/</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Vad händer med biblioteket när dess samlingar finns överallt och
    ingen särskild stans?</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <link href="/2004/biblioteket/"/>
    <summary>Biblioteken existerar för att det finns användare som är beredda
    att betala för deras tjänster. Visserligen betalar man i regel via
    skattesedeln och inte med sitt betalkortet, men principen är densamma.
    Under vilka förutsättningar är användarna, eller deras valda
    representanter, redo att betala för bibliotekens tjänster? Går det att
    finansiera lokalt bibliotek när biblioteksresurserna finns överallt och
    ingen särskild stans? Vilken kommun eller vilket universitet kan
    finansiera ett bibliotek som bara har en katalog, men inga samlingar? Och
    när allt kommer omkring, vem vill ha samlingar och varför? De är ju dyra
    och tar plats.</summary>
    <dc:date>2004</dc:date>
    <category term="The Library" label="thelibrary"/>
    <category term="Digital libraries" label="digitallibraries"/>
    <category term="Internet" label="internet"/>
    <updated>2009-06-09T21:01:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/2004/biblioteket/</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Vad en bra samling av digital text bör kunna</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <link href="/2004/digitalisering/position.pdf"/>
    <summary>En diskussion av vilka funktioner ett bra textarkiv bör, och vad
    digitalisering bör innebära.</summary>
    <category term="Digital libraries" label="digitallibraries"/>
    <category term="Metadata" label="metadata"/>
    <category term="Digital collections" label="digitalcollections"/>
    <dc:date>2004</dc:date>
    <updated>2009-06-09T21:10:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/2004/digitalisering/position.pdf</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Digitalisering i Lund</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <summary>En presentation om digitalisering och digitalt bevarande i
    Lund. Jag tror att jag höll den vid ett stort möte på Kungl. Biblioteket i
    Stockholm.</summary>
    <link href="/2004/digitalisering/presentation_04-11-04.html"/>
    <category term="Digital preservation" label="preservation"/>
    <category term="Digitization" label="digitization"/>
    <dc:date>2004</dc:date>
    <updated>2009-06-09T21:45:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/2004/digitalisering/presentation_04-11-04.html</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Metadata makes the world going round - en orientering om användning
    av Metadata och XML</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sara Kjellberg</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <link href="/2004/metadata_makes_the_world/"/>
    <summary>Sara Kjellberg och jag höll ett antal kurser om metadata
    o. XML. detta är vår presentation. Vi höll det inom ramen för BTJs
    kursutbud.</summary>
    <category term="XML processing" label="xmlprocessing"/>
    <category term="Metadata" label="metadata"/>
    <dc:date>2004</dc:date>
    <updated>2009-06-09T21:58:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/2004/metadata_makes_the_world/</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Vilken arkitektur ger ett nav i ett nätverk?  Om
    KB-utredningen</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <link href="/2004/navet/navet.html"/>
    <summary>En recension av KB-utredningen, SOU 2003:129</summary>
    <category term="The Library" label="thelibrary"/>
    <category term="Reviews" label="reviews"/>
    <dc:date>2004</dc:date>
    <updated>2009-06-09T22:06:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/2004/navet/navet.html</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Zornmedaljens baksida</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <summary>En diskussion av Zornmärket och
    riksspelmannainstitutionen och dess roll i svensk folkmusik</summary>
    <link href="/2004/zorn_etc/"/>
    <category term="Music, language &amp; literature" label="musiclanglit"/>
    <dc:date>2004</dc:date>
    <updated>2009-06-09T22:06:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/2004/zorn_etc/</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Ediffah</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <link href="/2005/Oct_28/"/>
    <summary>En superkort presentation om Ediffah, hållen vid
    Ediffahprojektets avslutning på Kungl. Biblioteket i Stockholm den 28
    oktober 2005</summary>
    <category term="Metadata" label="metadata"/>
    <category term="Archival description" label="archivaldescription"/>
    <dc:date>2005</dc:date>
    <updated>2009-06-09T22:06:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/2005/Oct_28/</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Digitala biblioteket</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <summary>En föreläsning om Internets historia, Det Digitala Biblioteket
    och Bibliotekets historia.</summary>
    <link href="/2005/bivil-digitala-bibliotek/"/>
    <dc:date>2005</dc:date>
    <updated>2009-06-09T22:06:00+01:00</updated>
    <category term="Digital libraries" label="digitallibraries"/>
    <category term="Internet" label="internet"/>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/2005/bivil-digitala-bibliotek/</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Digital preservation and digitization at Lund University (and
    elsewhere in Sweden)</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <link href="/2005/digital-preservation/"/>
    <summary>Notes to presentation held in Lund 7 June 2005. The audience was
    a group of people from China</summary>
    <category term="Digital preservation" label="preservation"/>    
    <category term="Digitization" label="digitization"/>
    <category term="Digital collections" label="digitalcollections"/>
    <dc:date>2005</dc:date>
    <updated>2009-06-09T22:06:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/2005/digital-preservation/</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Konkurrerar Google framgångsrikt med biblioteken?</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <link href="/2006/google/google-vs-thelibrary.html"/>
    <summary>En diskussion om Bibliotekets förhållande till sökmaskinen
    Google</summary>
    <category term="The Library" label="thelibrary"/>
    <category term="Digital libraries" label="digitallibraries"/>
    <category term="Internet" label="internet"/>
    <dc:date>2006</dc:date>
    <updated>2009-06-09T23:14:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/2006/google/google-vs-thelibrary.html</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Usage of digital resources with respect to method of publishing</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <link href="/2007/hidden_web/usage_vs_dissemination_method.html"/>
    <summary>I compared the usage of Digital material in relation to whether
    the material was hidden away in the the library opac or published on our
    web site. The result was as expected a disappointment for those who regard
    the Library catalogue as an important vehicle for dissemination of digital
    material</summary>
    <category term="The Library" label="thelibrary"/>
    <category term="Library catalogues" label="opac"/>
    <category term="Digital libraries" label="digitallibraries"/>
    <category term="Internet" label="internet"/>
    <category term="Structural web design" label="structuralwebdesign"/>
    <dc:date>2007</dc:date>
    <updated>2009-06-09T23:14:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/2007/hidden_web/</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>

    <title>What do our users expect from the search field on our top
    page?</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <link href="/2007/search-statistics/user-expectations.html"/>
    <summary>What can deduced by analyses of the search terms entered into the
    search field on the home page of a large modern library? Could we possibly
    regard this form as the digital library´s information desk, and the
    queries as the request from its patrons? If we do that, what could we then
    learn about the quality of service?  In this note we do just that. We
    regard the terms entered into the form as manifestation of our patrons
    needs and in order to find out what they need, we have performed a
    preliminary text mining exercise. We hope that this will help us designing
    a new search facility that will better answer the needs of our
    users.</summary>
    <category term="Web indexing" label="webindexing"/>
    <category term="Harvesting" label="harvesting"/>
    <category term="Library catalogues" label="opac"/>
    <category term="Structural web design" label="structuralwebdesign"/>
    <dc:date>2007</dc:date>
    <updated>2009-06-09T23:31:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/2007/search-statistics/</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>ADL i CLARIN-DK WP5</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <link href="/2008/clarin_adl/"/>
    <summary>En presentation jag höll om Arkiv før dansk litteratur (ADL)</summary>
    <category term="XML processing" label="xmlprocessing"/>
    <category term="Text encoding" label="textencoding"/>
    <category term="Digital humanities" label="ehumanities"/>
    <category term="Music, language &amp; literature" label="musiclanglit"/>
    <dc:date>2008</dc:date>
    <updated>2009-06-09T23:42:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/2008/clarin_adl/</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Digital Humanities Infrastructures</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <link href="/2008/dighum/digital_humanities.xml"/>
    <summary>This note discusses different initiatives as regards providing
    access to resources and tools aimed at researchers within the
    humanities. Since the general breakthrough of search services like Google,
    annotation and bookmarking services like del.icio.us and the like, the
    attitudes towards the application of computing within the humanities has
    changed. In addition, the concept of e-science has contributed to make
    scholars positive to apply computing to various problems within the
    humanities.  Following a discussion started around year 2000, we propose
    that it is possible to formalize many humanities computing tasks as
    pipelines between XML processing steps.</summary>
    <category term="XML processing" label="xmlprocessing"/>
    <category term="Text encoding" label="textencoding"/>
    <category term="Digital humanities" label="ehumanities"/>
    <dc:date>2008</dc:date>
    <updated>2009-06-09T23:42:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/2008/dighum/digital_humanities.xml</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Kortfattat Curriculum Vitae: Sigfrid Lundberg</title>
    <link href="/2009/cv/cv_sv.xml"/>
    <category term="About me" label="aboutme"/>
    <summary>Ett CV är väldigt tråkigt att skriva</summary>
    <dc:date>2009</dc:date>
    <updated>2009-06-09T23:54:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/2009/cv/cv_sv.xml</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>List of publications by Sigfrid Lundberg
    </title>
    <link href="/2009/cv/publications.html"/>
    <summary>Both peer reviewed articles, other articles and some
    presentations</summary>
    <dc:date>2009</dc:date>
    <updated>2009-06-09T23:57:00+01:00</updated>
    <category term="About me" label="aboutme"/>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/2009/cv/publications.html</id>
  </entry>
<entry xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>Why do I keep this site?</title>
  <link href="/entries/2009/06/why/"/>
  <summary>Having had a web site for about 15 years, I start to wonder why I
  keep it in the first place.</summary>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

      <p>A week or two ago I registered this site with Google Analytics. My
      Internet supply provider's statics is virtually useless. Then I've spent
      quite some time cutting and pasting the javascript into my olde
      stuff.</p>

      <p>I haven't cared about this site for about four years and as far as I
      can tell now, this place is hit by a one or two people per day, each of
      which stay less than a minute. Why they come I don't know, and Google
      Analytics won't tell me yet.</p>

      <p>Now, I didn't expect anything else. I use the site as a store for old
      documentation, of which just a few things could possibly be valuable for
      students of Internet history. Most likely, though, they hardly even
      deserve a footnote in the posterity.</p>

      <h3>The origins</h3>

      <p>I started this site autumn 1995. The oldest documents still in the
      public collection is from <a href="/1996">1996</a>. Now, started isn't
      really the right word. I never <em>planned</em> to build a web site
      with old documents. Basically, I started a web server on a development
      machine and devoted an area for project documentation and reports. I
      could then drop a piece of text there and send the URI to my colleagues
      or customers. That is how it started.</p>

      <p>This worked well to begin with, but about five years later the
      rudimentary structure per project was lost. I then made a backup copy,
      and created a structure year, and copied stuff from the old site into
      it. This is the way it is now.</p>

      <p>I started the current site <a href="/2005">2005</a>, when I left Lund
      university for a new job in Copenhagen. I felt that I just couldn't let
      this material just disappear.</p>

      <p>The site contains quite a few archived files. Counting them gives 241
      HTML files, 21 pdf, 84 xml and so forth. Of these I regard 37 as
      publications of some kind, in the sense that there are links to them
      that may be reached from the home page. It is still just a sample, the
      raw collection contains 2452 HTML files.</p>

      <p>I have no idea if I have benefited from the site, or if the material
      has been useful for someone else. For a few years, notably <a href="/2002">2002</a>, <a href="/2003">2003</a> and <a href="/2004">2004</a>, I did have an idea that I should make an active
      effort to maintain a web site. Some of the best texts are from that
      period.</p>

      <h3>Publish or let it perish?</h3>

      <p>I earn my livelihood as a developer for the Worldwide Web. But this
      site is not a part of what I do for my living. So, should I have it
      available here or let it perish?</p>

      <p>I pay my ISP 250 SEK per month for this, which include a Linux shell
      prompt available via secure shell and some storage. The storage side of
      it is no big deal; I have already a number of USB hard disks around. I
      have also <kbd>*.zip</kbd> and <kbd>*.tar.gz</kbd> files as attachment
      on my gmail account, which provides huge storage and good value for
      money in comparison with what I get from my ISP. But then, 250 SEK is no
      big deal either.</p>

      <p>So I'll keep it, for the time being. I don't think my stuff
      contribute very much to the digital refuse spread over the net. I've
      added an <a href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc4287">ATOM syndication
      feed</a> for the garbage I decided to keep, a subject browsing based on
      the ATOM categories. Finally I've added some texts from the last few
      years. These are basically of the same kind as the rest of my
      stuff. Reports and papers written for some specific purpose and
      republished here entirely out of context.</p>

    </div>
  </content>
  <dc:date>2009</dc:date>
  <category label="structuralwebdesign" term="Structural web design"/>
  <updated>2009-06-27T12:18:00+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/feed/why.xml</id>
</entry><entry xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>Min mor</title>
  <link href="/entries/2009/06/mor/"/>
  <summary>Min mor var 43 år gammal när hon födde mig 1956. Alltså föddes hon
  själv 1913, året innan första världskriget bröt ut. Nu är hon 96, och lever,
  som hon säger, på lånad tid. Tid, det är något som hon tar på största
  allvar. Vi talas vid per telefon varje dag. Hon ringer 20.10, nästan
  exakt. Det blir alltid ett trevligt samtal.</summary>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

      <p>Min mor var 43 år gammal när hon födde mig 1956. Alltså föddes hon
      själv 1913, året innan första världskriget bröt ut. Nu är hon 96, och
      lever, som hon säger, på lånad tid. Tid, det är något som hon tar på
      största allvar. Vi talas vid per telefon varje dag. Hon ringer 20.10,
      nästan exakt. Det blir alltid ett trevligt samtal.</p>
      
      <p style="margin-left:0.5em;float:left;">
	<img src="http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/galleri/200902-200904/smaller/cimg1150.jpg" alt="Mor i dörrent"/>
      </p>

      <p>När det är dags att säga godnatt, återkomer hon ständigt till att man
      måste vara tacksam för varje dag som gått, och att "i morgon är det en
      ny dag". Visst har Mor rätt! Det är faktiskt inte är självklart att man
      får leva hela nästa dag. Har man hunnit med ett långt liv, så är man
      mer medveten om den saken än vad vi, yngre människor, är.</p>

      <p>Jag tänker på det ibland, att hon har varit med om en stor del av
      1900-talet, och hur hon kan tala om arbetslösheten på 30-talet, om
      Krügerkraschen 1931. Då var hon en fager ung kvinna 18 år gammal. Mor
      har varit folkpensionär under i princip hela mitt yrkesverksamma liv,
      hon föddes innan ryska revolutionen och lever faktiskt fortfarande.  Hon
      arbetar fortfarande i trädgården. "Ni behöver inte vara rädda, jag kan
      inte trilla när jag sitter på marken," berättade hon nyligen.</p>

      <p>I mars i år fick hon höra på radion om SEBs nyemission nu i mars
      månad tog hon rollatorn ner till Handelsbanken. Som folkpensionär tjänar
      hon 7000 kronor i månaden, så för att köpa de femhundra hennes innehav
      berättigade henne till, fick hon höja sin checkkontokredit. Vi fick 200
      aktier var, jag och min bror. Det var för sina barns skull hon köpte
      aktierna på lånade pengar.</p>

      <h2>En ny påminnelse om vår dödlighet</h2>

      <p>I dag när vi talades vid berättade hon om gravstenen. Min far dog i
      september i fjol 93 år och tre månader gammal, men det är först nu som
      vi fått gravstenen på plats, och Mor är lycklig för det. Den är i lite
      mer äldre stil, hög och smal, inte så där bred och låg som många
      gravstenar är numera. Jag har inte sett den själv ännu, men mor säger
      att den är vacker. Huggen i grå granit från Östra Göinge, i trakten
      kring Glimåkra, där Far växte upp. Texten är i Garamond, stilen som Far
      tyckte bäst om, jämte Berling Antikva. Far var boktryckare och vi har
      nog åtskilliga hundra kilo Berling Antikva i källaren efter honom.</p>

      <p>Mor ser illa. Hon har både grå starr och gula fläcken och kan inte
      läsa inte tidningen längre. Men lyssnar hon på radio det gör hon. Jag
      tror att hon sitter där i köket och lyssnar mest hela dagen. Inte missar
      hon en nyhetssänding om hon kan undvika det. Ekot och i synnerhet
      ekonomiekot är viktigt. Radioföljetongen och radioteatern är hennes enda
      intag av skönlitteratur nuförtiden.</p>

      <p>Mor började skolan 1920. Det var inte så ovanligt på den tiden att
      flickornas utbildning försummades på bekostnad av gossarnas. För hennes
      del blev det aldrig mer än sexårig folkskola. Istället läste hon in
      nästan stora delar av en gymnasiekompetens på KOMvux mot slutet av
      60-talet och början av 70-talet. Det blev dock inte moderna språk eller
      matematik, för det var hennes förkunskaper för klena.</p>

      <p>Dagligen diskuterar vi utvecklingen i världen, och hon berättar annat
      som hon har hört på radion. Mor har stor tillit till att Barack Obama
      och hoppas på fred i mellersta östern. Nu senast har hon talat en del om
      PO Enquists som går som radioföljetong just nu, med författaren själv
      som uppläsare.</p>

      <h2>En kopp kaffe</h2>

      <p>Vi åker hem till mor var eller varannan helg, jag och min bror. Vi
      byts om för att hon skall få besök oftare.</p>

      <p>När jag är hos henne äter vi lunch tillsammans. Sedan lyssnar vi på
      lunchekot medan vi tar en kopp kaffe på maten. Sedan stänger vi av
      radion och går igenom posten, mest fönsterkuvert. Nästan varje gång ber
      hon mig att läsa jag högt ur tidningen. Börsnoteringarna för hennes
      aktier och dödsannonserna måste jag läsa varje gång vi träffas.</p>

      <p>Så är det i livet. När man är ung funderar man kanske inte så mycket
      över det, men det är ju så att man umgås väldigt mycket med människor
      som är som man själv är. Unga umgås med unga, småbarnsfamiljer med
      varandra och de diskuterar barn. När man kommer upp i medelåldern
      diskuterar man barn, barnbarn och sjuka föräldrar. När blir gammal
      gammal läser man dödsannonserna. När man är så gammal som Mor är det
      få kvar av hennes vänner att läsa om där.</p>

      <p>Efter kaffet språkar om allt möjligt. Ofta går vi en promenad, men
      oftast tycker hon bättre att gå uppför än nerför. Rollatorn rullar för
      fort och det är lätt att hon inte hinner med den i nerförsbacke.</p>

      <p>Mor tycker om poesi. Hon kan en hel massa dikter och psalmverser
      utantill som hon gärnar citerar när det passar. Hon har tränat yoga
      sedan hon fyllde 60, och hon tränar varje dag. Jag tror också att hon
      dagligen läser alla de dikter och psalmer hon kan utantill, och i
      synnerhet JO Wallins:</p>

      <blockquote>
	<em>Ack, när så mycket skönt i varje åder<br/>
	av skapelsen och livet sig förråder,<br/>
	hur skön då måste själva källan vara,<br/>
	den evigt klara</em>
      </blockquote>

      <p>Fast hon kan minst fem verser till.</p>

    </div>
  </content>
  <dc:date>2009</dc:date>
  <category label="essays" term="Essays"/>
  <updated>2009-06-28T23:33:00+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/06/mor/</id>
</entry><entry xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    <uri>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/</uri>
  </author>
  <title>My first serious experience with ATOM</title>
  <link href="/entries/2009/06/atom/"/>
  <summary>You don't really understand a document format until you've manually
  encoded some documents, and written the software to parse and use it for
  something useful. This somewhat refurbished version of my web site is to a
  large extent built upon the ATOM syndication format, and here I discuss my
  experience.</summary>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

      <p>The <a href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc4287">ATOM syndication
      format</a> has been around for almost five years. In comparison with the
      diverse fauna kept in the menagerie abbreviated to the three character
      acronym RSS, ATOM is a well kept standard and much more useful as
      well.</p>

      <p>Now, I've used ATOM before refurbishing my personal web site, but I
      haven't used <em>seriously</em>. That is, I haven't manually encoded a
      sizeable amount of text in it, validated the result, and then written
      software using the data. ATOM is the fundament for this site, since the
      used for generating the navigation system is encoded that way. I may
      return to that later on.</p>

      <h2>Designed for success</h2>

      <p>Tim Bray lists and provide a thorough discussion of a number of
      characteristics shared by successful mark-up languages (see his article
      <a href="http://web.archive.org/web/20070126140434/www.idealliance.org/proceedings/xml05/ship/175/xml2005.HTML">On
      Language Creation</a>). The list of success critera includes items such
      as extensibility, clever but not too extensive use of XML name spaces,
      the posibility of implementing the language using many, widely different,
      datamodels. From Bray's perspective, ATOM seems designed for success. I
      don't know the statistics concerning syndication format popularity, but
      if ATOM isn't yet the leader, it will become sooner or later. Possibly
      in RDF disguise.</p>

      <p>From a modelling point of view there is a few, annoying
      inconsistencies. Let us, for example, compare the <kbd>&lt;author&gt;</kbd>
      element with the <kbd>&lt;title&gt;</kbd> element. A resource may have an
      author, then the author may have a number of properties, such as a name,
      an email address and a home page. The <kbd>author</kbd> for this note is
      encoded as:</p>

      <pre>
  &lt;author&gt;
    &lt;name&gt;Sigfrid Lundberg&lt;/name&gt;
    &lt;uri&gt;http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/&lt;/uri&gt;
  &lt;/author&gt;
      </pre>

      <p>This is, in my view, a sign of good content modelling when it comes
      to metadata. A resource may have a title. A title may have different
      components, for example main title and sub-title. The main and sub parts
      are properties of the title, not of the resource. The authors of the
      ATOM spec did not see that way. A feed may have both. This is annoying
      for semantic puristic nerd like me. Entries, however, may not have
      sub-titles at all, which in my view is an inconsistency as well.</p>

      <p>The biggest flaw is the encoding of category data. A resource belongs
      to a category, i.e., this membership is a property of the resource. The
      category may have an identifier and a name, and this name is different
      depending to language. However, ATOM forces me to use the following
      construct</p>

      <pre>
  &lt;category xml:lang="en" label="structuralwebdesign" term="Structural web design" /&gt;
  &lt;category xml:lang="sv" label="structuralwebdesign" term="Structural web design" /&gt;
      </pre>

      <p>which in my view is less than excellent. I would have preferred
      something like</p>

      <pre>
  &lt;category label="structuralwebdesign"&gt;
    &lt;name xml:lang="en"&gt;Structural web design&lt;/name&gt;
    &lt;name xml:lang="sv"&gt;Strukturell webbdesign&lt;/name&gt;
  &lt;/category&gt;
      </pre>

      <p>These are shortcomings, but I can live with them. But expect changes
      in this area. The semantic web is here already, and with <a href="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/">SKOS</a> becoming a de facto
      standard on the internet, the syntactic communities will have to come up
      with something more clever for categorization of syndicated web
      resources.</p>

    </div>
  </content>
  <dc:date>2009</dc:date>
  <category label="structuralwebdesign" term="Structural web design"/>
  <category term="Metadata" label="metadata"/>
  <updated>2009-06-27T17:35:00+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/06/atom/</id>
</entry><entry xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>Why I love XSLT extension functions</title>
  <link href="/entries/2009/07/xslt_extensions/"/>
  <summary/>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

      <p>I started learning XSLT eight years ago. At the time, it was a fresh
      technology, and there was also intense discussions on the extensibility
      of the language. Since then xslt 1.1 has disappeared down the drains,
      xpath 2.0 &amp; xquery 1.0 appeared on the market. The former of these
      has had a slow start. The latter, however, has gained acceptance,
      however a bit reluctant.</p>

      <p>The stuff I want to discuss here is the writing of extension
      functions. This is regarded as an evil habit in some parts of the XML
      processing communities, but it is supported by most implementations. It
      is not to be recommended if you're producing a stand-alone application,
      but in many cases you're xslt code is an integrated part of an
      application. Most of my code is of this kind; in particular I'm writing
      xslt for xalan running in a JAVA environment. Now, why should I refrain
      from using regex, just because xalan does not support this package? I
      cannot see why. And nobody would ask me to write ANSI SQL in spite of
      the fact that we use Oracle.</p>

      <p>Now, it has been proven mathematically that xslt is a <a href="http://www.ibm.com/developerworks/library/x-xalanextensions.html">Turing
      complete</a> programming language. That means that it is possible to
      program <strong>anything</strong> which is possible to program with such
      a language. I.e., you have theoretically the same possibilities as in
      JAVA and C++. That doesn't mean that it is practical do do so. It is, in
      my view, much easier to traverse a XML tree in XSLT than in (say) JAVA,
      whereas it is much easier to connect to a database or implement a XSLT
      processor using a conventional programming language.</p>

      <p>It is here the XSLT extension functions become really useful. You can
      pass data from XSLT to your own functions written in your favourite
      programming lanuguage. I use this for tasks like indexing XML
      documents. When traversing a document, you select text and pass it to
      you're function which pass it to your indexing API. One big advantage is
      that the same software can index heterogenous collections of XML
      documents just by using different XSLT scripts. They are easy to write
      and you can a new document type without recompilation of you're indexing
      software.</p>

      <p>This ability of a fullblown functional programming language (mind
      you, its Turing complete) to interface both with a host program and from
      scripts inside it call other functions in other languages is
      powerful. This, in combination that it is really good for what it is
      designed for has made it an object for extreme affection from
      me. Besides I'll return to examples of using XSLT for indexing complex
      XML objects.</p>

    </div>
  </content>
  <dc:date>2009</dc:date>
  <category label="xmlprocessing" term="XML processing"/>
  <updated>2009-07-14T18:18:42+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/07/xslt_extensions/</id>
</entry><entry xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>The predator rests on its prey</title>
  <link href="/entries/2009/07/victory/"/>
  <summary>I've seen this image before. An excavator has demolished a
  building, and has then proudly been parked on top of the remnants.</summary>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
      <div style="float: left;margin-left: 3px;margin-right:3px;">
	<img src="http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/galleri/200907-200907/smaller/cimg1345.jpg" alt="an excavator on top of a demolished building"/>
      </div>

      <p>Is this <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Smaug">Smaug</a>
      resting on a pile of gold? Or a predator resting after a victorius
      battle with a powerful prey?</p>

      <p>Obviously neither. But I've seen this image before. An excavator has
      demolished a building, and has then proudly been parked on top of the
      remnants. The building was a petrol station from the sixties. I'll not
      miss it; it was an ugly building. The shop inside it was
      poor. That's not the point.</p>

      <p> The point is just <strong>why this gesture of aggression</strong>?
      Why is the excavator always parked on top of the remnants? Is it a
      gesture of triumph? Has the present once again earned a victory over the
      past?  It is the choice of parking place which is the question.</p>

    </div>
  </content>
  <dc:date>2009</dc:date>
  <category label="essays" term="Essays"/>
  <updated>2009-07-13T10:46:29+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/07/victory/</id>
  <!--
      $Id$
  -->
</entry><entry xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>Will the research libraries play a role in e-science</title>
  <link href="/entries/2009/07/escience/"/>
  <summary>I was asked to participate in an e-science pilot project.  The work
  in the project has been food for thought for me. Will libraries be a part of
  a future eScience infrastructure?</summary>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
      
      <p>I was asked to participate in an e-science pilot project. The pilot
      is directed towards social science, and its main goal is to find out
      what we could do in the area. Should libraries play a role in a future
      eScience infrastructure? If yes, what could we do for our patrons in
      this area?</p>

      <p>That the answer should be yes to the first question is obvious for
      anyone responsible for the strategic development of any research library
      around the globe, but the second question is clearly more difficult to
      answer.</p>

      <p>Libraries have, traditionally, been occupied with four activities:
      They collect, preserve, organize and provide access to
      information. Indeed a <a href="http://www.google.com/search?hl=en&amp;q=collect+preserve+organize+%22provide+access%22&amp;btnG=Search">search</a>
      for these four terms in Google seem to yield a search very focussed on
      mission statements for Northern American research libraries. <em>It
      isn't farfetched to conclude that we could extend this role to include
      research data in digital form</em></p>

      <h2>A happy hypertextual symbiosis</h2>

      <p>In my vision, our role may not end here. The task should involve an
      infrastructure permitting the our existing information (published in the
      form of books, journals and whatever) live in a happy hypertextual
      symbiosis with the research data it is based on.</p>

      <p>In this ecosystem of data and models scientists should be able to
      combine old stuff in new ways just and continue building the human
      knowledge by submitting new data. Every piece of data need to be
      possible to address, for the purpose of annotation as well as for
      retrieval. Every piece of data, any point in a diagram need an
      identifier. And it has to be a URI.</p>

      <p>No single organization will be able to afford to build the
      infrastructure needed by any research community. The good news is that
      no single organization need to build it. The web of data, which has to
      be the eScience infrastructure, will almost certainly be the Worldwide
      web. Nothing less, nothing more.</p>

      <p>This is the vision of <a href="http://www.w3.org/DesignIssues/LinkedData.html">linked data</a>
      and the semantic web, rephrased in the context of scientific
      information.</p>

      <p>By tradition libraries are aimed for some local community. In
      particular, the are funded by some local authority for that
      purpose. Hence they build collections suitable for that community.
      This local focus is a problem when everything else is Worldwide.</p>


      <p>The idea of the web of data as a foundation for an eScience is a good
      idea, and most likely the only one that will work. Indeed it is so
      obvious ones that any actor within the business of scientific
      information are about to adopt it; publishers, learned societies and
      libraries alike. However there are others that are interested. Google
      eScience doesn't sound too exotic to me.</p>

      <p>Google eScience is not a threat, per se. The web of data need data
      feeds. We can provide that. The problem is our local scope, and in
      particular the focus on a local community. But that boils down to the
      local funding.</p>


    </div>
  </content>
  <dc:date>2009</dc:date>
  <category label="escience" term="eScience"/>
  <updated>2009-07-15T14:53:45+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/07/escience/</id>
</entry><entry xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>XML on the web, Client Side XSLT and Google</title>
  <link href="/entries/2009/07/client_side_xslt/"/>
  <summary>The market has forced the major browser manufacturers to converge
  on standards. But why are the search engines lagging behind? Browsers are
  capable of AJAX and advanced XML processing, but the search engines are
  still basically just removing tags and presenting raw text extracts.</summary>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

      <p>The market has forced the major browser manufacturers to converge on
      standards. Microsoft cannot afford to produce a browser that won't work
      on google apps, and the Linux based netbooks and netboxes make a
      difference. If <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Software_as_a_service">software is a
      service</a>, what is the client? Obviously the web client, the
      browser. But why are the search engines lagging behind?  Browsers are
      capable of AJAX and advanced XML processing, but the search engines are
      still basically just removing tags and presenting raw text extracts.</p>

      <p>I have quite a few documents on this site that are written in raw
      XML, such as the <a href="/2008/dighum/digital_humanities.xml">Digital
      Humanities Infrastructures</a> position paper from last year. Since it
      is about digital humanities and text encoding, I wrote it in <a href="http://www.tei-c.org/">TEI</a> XML. The paper is presented using
      client side XSLT. Just view source on that note, and you'll see my
      markup. The document is a blatant show-off; it is written in nerdcore
      vanity. At the top you'll see</p>

      <pre>
	&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;
	&lt;?xml-stylesheet href="render.xsl" type="text/xsl" ?&gt;
      </pre>

      <p>The <kbd>xml-stylesheet</kbd> processing instruction is read by your
      browsser, which then retrieves the stylesheet <a href="/2008/dighum/render.xsl">render.xsl</a>. Without any further ado
      it is then transformed into html, rendered using the CSS indicated by my
      XSLT script for you to read. You can even inspect the resulting html
      using <a href="http://getfirebug.com/">firebug</a>, if you've got a
      modern installation.</p>

      <h2>What does Google do when indexing XML?</h2>

      <p>There is almost certainly a range of XML formats that is actually
      interpreted by Google. Which formats, well we don't know but in practice
      can hardly expect anything more exotic than common syndication formats
      (such as RSS and ATOM ), <a href="http://google.com/support/webmasters/bin/answer.py?hl=en&amp;answer=99170">microformats
      and RDFa</a>. I have noticed that Google has been doing OAI harvesting
      for many years, most likely for the benefit of <a href="http://scholar.google.com/">Scholar</a>.</p>

      <p>One could envisage a number of viable indexing strategies for a
      general search engine for a document like my Digital Infrastructure
      Nerdcore Vanity paper. One would be to execute a global regex search and
      replace "&lt;[^&gt;]+&gt;" with "" (which basically means: remove
      anything between angle brackets, or remove all tags).</p>

      <p>This would yield a "detagged incipit", which in this case is "Digital
      Humanities Infrastructures 2008-06-12 Digital Humanities Infrastructures
      Sigfrid Lundberg"</p> 

      <p>Another strategy would be to use the style sheet provided by the nerd
      publishing this paper. That would yield the "transformed incipit", which
      for this document is (using the HTML body only) "Digital Humanities
      Infrastructures Sigfrid Lundberg". In using the transform, Google would
      then be able to use its usual HTML indexing techniques. For instance it
      would understand the title, and be able parse all hypertext links.</p>

      <p>I made the search <a href="http://www.google.com/search?hl=en&amp;q=digital+humanities+infrastructure+%2Blundberg&amp;btnG=Search">digital
      humanities infrastructure +lundberg</a> and the results looks like
      "<strong>Digital Humanities Infrastructures 2008-06-12 Digital
      Humanities ...</strong> - Jun 5 ... Digital Humanities Infrastructures
      Sigfrid Lundberg slu@kb.dk Digital .... Also McCarty's humanities
      computing research infrastructure (or rather ..."</p>

      <p>The machine is actually using a detagged incipit as the title, which
      is what I think it uses for PDF. This is very far from the ideas in
      <a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/grddl/">Gleaning Resource Descriptions
      from Dialects of Languages (GRDDL)</a> where providers of documents
      actually provide XSLT for the benefit of robots that could use that to
      extract descriptions in RDF.</p>

    </div>
  </content>
  <dc:date>2009</dc:date>
  <category label="structuralwebdesign" term="Structural web design"/>
  <updated>2009-07-11T21:51:48+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/07/client_side_xslt/</id>
</entry><entry xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>About this site</title>
  <link href="/entries/2009/07/colophon/"/>
  <summary>I'm a terrible nerd. To use software like content management
  systems or blog software is unthinkable for me. There are many ways to build
  a site like this. I have chosen one that maximizes the use of angle
  brackets.</summary>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

      <p>I'm a terrible nerd. To use software like content management systems
      or blog software for building my web site is unthinkable for me.</p>

      <p>I have a substantial collection of old stuff written for various
      purposes in very different formats; it is a must to be able to integrate
      that material into the site. Some of this material are hard-core XML
      documents in text encoding initiative or docbook XML. There are also
      documents in legacy formats, such as RTF and (GNU) troff. I'm still
      using troff for production of new texts, usually via transform from XML
      using XSLT. The more recent XML documents are using client side XSLT for
      viewing.</p>

      <p>This material is growing. I see it as an extension of my CV, but some
      of it could be interesting for users since it is general documentation
      for how to solve certain kinds of problems. I also wanted to seemlessly
      integrate other, more lightweight, material. Like this article</p>

      <h3>Requirements</h3>

      <p>As I mentioned <a href="/entries/2009/06/why/">the other day</a>, I
      wanted a new navigation system. There are two requirements on that: (i)
      it should be easy to follow for users and (ii) the pages in it should be
      good landing pages for search engines. I felt that there was a need for
      more text that would generate hits in search engines without out being
      irrelevant for users and misrepresent the content. Finally I wanted the
      site to be somewhat like a blog. In spite of the improved look and feel
      I also wanted that all the material already published on the site should
      retain the current URIs.</p>

      <p>The old site was just plain files, I did no scripting whatsoever on
      that site. I couldn't, however, possibly manage a navigation system a
      manually, so some scripting had to be involved in generating the
      site.</p>

      <h3>Metadata and XML processing</h3>

      <p>To generate the navigation system, I have catalog all existing
      'static' material. In particular I had to index manually using keywords
      or "tags". I decided what material to include and wrote manually a
      single monolithic metadata file in XML using using <a href="/entries/2009/06/atom/">the atom syndication format</a>.</p>

      <p>Having this file it was easy to write a xslt tranform that generated
      the browse by year and subject menues appearing in the left column on
      most pages (that took 61 lines). Then there is another xslt transform
      aggregating the title, summary and link data into menus, such as the one
      in <a href="/subjects/xmlprocessing/">XML processing</a>. This took
      about 200 lines of xslt.</p>

      <p>Now, these two xslt scripts take into account only the older kind of
      static material. I also wanted a new kind of bloggish 'dynamic'
      material. I needed to integrate the two kinds of material in a single
      structure. Just as I wrote the metadata for the older set of material in
      Atom feed document, I write the bloggish kind of stuff in Atom entry
      documents. They live in a file system <kbd>/entries</kbd> under the
      document root.</p>

      <p>To integrate the two I have a nifty little perl script that does two
      things. It reads the Atom feed for the and parses it into a Document
      Object Model (DOM) object. Then it traverses the <kbd>/entries</kbd>
      file system, parses each entry. First it drops a transform into html of
      each entry. The entry itself is entered into the global DOM, which is
      finally printed into a complete Atom feed. This took 65 lines of perl
      and 84 lines of xslt.</p>

      <p>To get a blog style home page I had to sort the entire set inversely
      in temporal order, print the most recent entry on the home page and
      finally print a few pointers to more recent entries. These tasks took
      another 250 lines of xslt. In addition I have a utility which generates
      the <kbd>/entries</kbd> directories and prints a skeleton entry, which
      generates another 100 lines of perl which generates the skeleton using
      XML DOM.</p>

      <p>It takes less than a second to rebuild the entire site. Before the
      refurbishment, I used to copy all files to my server. In order to
      implement incremental update, I've created a CVS repository on my
      server. Now I check in everything using CVS after building and testing,
      and then I publish my stuff by checking out on the. This will scale up
      to a some thousand blog entries. Then I'll ingest my entries in Oracle
      Berkeley DB XML and replace most xslt with XML Query.</p>

      <p>Or I'll do that anyway, for the fun of it.</p>

    </div>
  </content>
  <dc:date>2009</dc:date>
  <category label="structuralwebdesign" term="Structural web design"/>
  <category label="colophon" term="Colophon"/>
  <updated>2009-07-06T18:16:27+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/07/colophon/</id>
</entry><entry xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>This is a dummy entry for technorati</title>
  <link href="/entries/2009/07/technorati/"/>
  <summary>uw5m38jba7
  </summary>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
uw5m38jba7
    </div>
  </content>
  <dc:date>2009</dc:date>
  <category label="structuralwebdesign" term="Structural web design"/>
  <updated>2009-07-13T10:42:06+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/07/technorati/</id>
</entry><entry xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>OpenSearch, RSS and OPML as XML Webservices for information
  retrieval</title>
  <link href="/entries/2009/07/opml/"/>
  <summary>At the Royal Library we have been working with the building of an
  infrastructure for publishing of digitized material. It is collections of
  digital images, usually with very little textual content to go with it. It
  is quite a challenge to build workflows satisfying the needs of technical
  staff running the scanners, the librararian and editorial staff doing the
  cataloging and the needs for crosswalking metadata from the OPAC and at the
  same time be able to syndicate the material in other services adhering to
  different standards.</summary>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

      <p>At the <a href="http://www.kb.dk/">Royal Library</a> we have been
      working with the building of an infrastructure for publishing of
      digitized material. It is collections of digital images, usually with
      very little textual content to go with it.</p>

      <p>The cataloging of the images has been made by library staff using the
      image database system Cumulus from <a href="http://www.canto.com/">Canto</a>.  Cumulus is designed as digital
      asset management system for people within graphical industry. Canto is
      producing an advanced Web user interface, but it is rather poor as
      regards dissemination of the collections on the web. For example, images
      published that way never ever appear in Google Images. Syndication of
      our content has not been possible, since the system have been lacking
      any concept of standardized metadata, which is essential for all
      collaboration between institutions in the library communities.</p>

    
      <div style="float: left;margin-left:5px;margin-right:5px;">
	<div style="height:350px;width:300px;">
	  <a href="http://static.grazr.com/gzpanel.html?view=s&amp;file=http://www.kb.dk/opml_category_service/danmarksbilleder/?opml_mode=shallow&amp;subject=8">
	    <img alt="Grazr" src="http://static.grazr.com/images/grazrbadge.png" style="border:none"/>
	  </a>
	  <script defer="defer" type="text/javascript" src="http://static.grazr.com/gzloader.js?view=s&amp;file=http://www.kb.dk/opml_category_service/danmarksbilleder/?opml_mode=shallow&amp;subject=8">
	  </script>
	</div>
      </div>

      <p>To take advantage of the relative ease of use for the people handling
      the images, but still be able to provide access to our collections on
      the Internet we have an entirely new web interface. For performace
      reasons, we decided that it should <em>not</em> access the cumulus
      database directly, but a mirror in our Oracle DB. Furthermore we wanted
      a REST XML web service layer.</p>

      <p>The latter goal was achieved by using two syndication services, built
      on top of Oracle. The two services were written as JAVA servlets, and
      supported Outline Processor Markup Language (<a href="http://web.archive.org/web/20071019150004/http://opml.org/">OPML</a>) and <a href="http://www.opensearch.org">OpenSearch</a>, together with RSS. The
      rationale for the latter choice of standard was that we wanted
      mainstream Internet Standards rather than typical library standards such
      as <a href="http://www.loc.gov/standards/sru/">SRU</a>. OpenSearch is
      promoted by <a href="http://a9.com">A9</a>, a subsidiary of <a href="http://www.amazon.com">Amazon</a> and there are at least pledges
      of support from other big players such as Google and Yahoo.</p>

      <p>OPML was not an as obvious choice. However, OpenSearch is basically a
      Syndication protocol and as such OPML is a candidate since its most
      common usage is to provide subject structured access to feeds. An early
      version of the system is available on our web site, the first version
      was released for about a year ago. Our technology choices makes it
      stright forward to syndicate the content. The gadget on this page is an
      example of this. It is a gadget showing the OPML and RSS from the first
      collection of images released in this way, <a href="http://www.kb.dk/images/billed/2008/maj/danmarksbilleder/">Danmarksbilleder</a>,
      a collection of historical images from a few Danish cities. The widget
      itself is "The Original Feed Widget" a nifty thing coming from <a href="http://grazr.com">grazr.com</a>. You can make one of your own by
      filling in the URI <a href="http://www.kb.dk/opml_category_service/danmarksbilleder/?opml_mode=shallow&amp;subject=8">http://www.kb.dk/opml_category_service/danmarksbilleder/?opml_mode=shallow&amp;subject=8</a>
      in the form on grazr.com.</p>

      <p>The use of truly simple de facto Internet standards is one
      advantage. But we needed a way to build traditional web contents on top
      of our two web services. Sites as <a href="http://www.kb.dk/images/billed/2008/maj/danmarksbilleder/">Danmarksbilleder</a>
      mentioned above, and its "cousins" <a href="http://www.kb.dk/images/billed/2008/sep/kistebilleder/">Kistebilleder</a>,
      <a href="http://www.kb.dk/images/billed/2008/sep/daellsvarehus/">Daells
      varehus</a> and <a href="http://www.kb.dk/images/billed/2008/sep/partiprogrammer/">Partiprogrammer</a>. All
      these are actually delivered by one single servlet, which is most
      appropriately described as a mashup-engine.</p>

      <p>The engine is written in-house, and supports multiple skins (as seen
      in the examples above -- <a href="http://www.kb.dk/images/billed/2008/maj/danmarksbilleder/">Danmarksbilleder</a> differs from <a href="http://www.kb.dk/images/billed/2008/sep/kistebilleder/">Kistebilleder</a>).</p>

      <p>In this application a skin is a XML document, which consists of the
      lay-out for the html page (it is little more than the HTML). Appart from
      html tags it also contain &lt;kb:include/&gt; tags identified by they id
      attribute. Each kb:include tag corresponds to a REST XML web service and
      is connected to a XSLT script via configuration file. The mashup engine
      reads the skin at initialization, and upon a request it retrieves the
      required OPML or RSS, transforms the content, pastes these fragments
      into the skin DOM tree and finally delivers the content to the
      client.</p>

      <p>The mashup engine is not very well written. I can do better. Also the
      current set of services requires an Oracle schema per collection
      disseminated which is wasteful. We've haven't got the time yet to fix
      the first problem, but the second problem is about to be solved since we
      have a second generation of web services in the pipe-line for release
      real soon. In this application we've just one single Oracle database for
      all editions served. I will give you a report on that one when it is
      online.</p>


    </div>
  </content>
  <dc:date>2009</dc:date>
  <category label="xmlprocessing" term="XML processing"/>
  <category label="colophon" term="Colophon"/>
  <updated>2009-07-09T18:44:44+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/07/opml/</id>
</entry><entry xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>The description and encoding of structure</title>
  <link href="/entries/2009/07/structure/"/>
  <summary>Much metadata is fairly stright forward. A book does have a title
  and an author. That's usually no big deal. We've been able to handle that
  for centuries. A digital book has chapters, and everything you might want to
  know may be in chapter two on page seventyfive. Or someone may tell you the
  solution to your problems after a quarter of an hour in some video on
  YouTube. Now, how do we cope with this?</summary>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

      <p>Many things in life can best be represented as trees. Indeed, life
      itself is a tree of various life forms. We have the animal and plant
      kingdoms, and these main categories are further sub-divided into phylae,
      classes, genera. The animal kingdom is divided into invertebrates and
      vertebrates. The latter include amphibians, reptiles, birds and
      mammals. Human knowledge is also depicted as a tree.</p>

      <p>A lot of other things are trees. Hence, philosophers, mathematicins
      and computer scientists have put quite an effort into the modelling
      stuff as trees. Within library &amp; information science we have used
      the term classification systems for centuries, I suppose, and more
      recently we have started to talk about ontologies and knowledge
      organization. There are a lot of theory and a lot of standards in this
      area. Systems like <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Topic_Maps">topic maps</a> (see also
      <a href="http://www.topicmaps.org/">topicmaps.org</a>) and more recently
      Simple Knowledge Organization System <a href="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/">SKOS</a>) are available for those
      who need a standard for knowledge organization.</p>

      <p>On a very down to earth level, I tend to think of controlled
      vocabularies as filters and navigators. The latter are trees and may
      contain many terms arranged into a tree of arbitrary depth. The filters
      are lists of controlled terms, which may be whereabout in the tree we
      are. Think of Yahoo Directory. You can browse into <a href="http://dir.yahoo.com/Regional/Countries/Italy/Regions/Tuscany/">Tuscany</a>
      and get a very long list of resources. Then there was a menu at the top
      where you can choose between "Business and Shopping", "Entertainment and
      Arts", "Recreation and Sports", "Travel and Transportation" and so
      forth. These are broader categorizations that apply to Firenze as well
      as Siena or New York city or any place you may want to visit. We in the
      Web business call them <em>filters</em> or <em>facets</em>.</p>

      <h2>Recognizing and recalling</h2>

      <p>From a user perspective, you have to take into account that there are
      two cognitive processes involved when using services which like Yahoo
      Directory employ navigators and filters. The first process one is much
      more fundamental, and is by nurture and possibly nature a part of the
      human mind: This is to say: Ah Tuscany, that is a part of Italy, isn't
      it. It's like distinguishing between a wasp and a bumble bee. On an
      evolutionary time-scale we've benefitted from being able to say, this is
      edible this is not, or this one has a sting and is likely to use
      it. This is to recognize something when you see it.</p>

      <p>The opposite is a much more difficult cognitive process: I want to
      know something about Tuscany: Ok, I then start clicking on Italy. You
      have to connect Italy with Tuscany, not only recognize Tuscany. This
      makes it more difficult to find Tuscany given Italy than Italy given
      Tuscany. Remembering might not be trivial. To know in advance things
      like "frogs are amphibians" and that "diabetes is an endocrinological
      disorder". On the other hand, to perform successful searching in Google
      is even more demanding.</p>

      <h2>Ordered hierarchies of content objects</h2>

      <p>There are structures that are inside a resource, and that require
      navigation as well. As a first approximation we can assume that digital
      resources, such as electronic books, are trees as well. This modelis
      called OHCO (ordered hierarchy of content objects). That view has been
      questioned, and it is for instance claimed that any ordinary text
      consists of many, <a href="http://www.stg.brown.edu/resources/stg/monographs/ohco.html">overlapping
      hierarchies</a>. I just love overlapping hierarchies. They are great fun.</p>

      <p>Anyway, if your search the scientific literature on the theory of
      text, you'll find everything you want to know about post-structuralistic
      deconstruction of the OCHO model. Theoretically, I can understand the
      problems. But for me they are more often than not purely academical.</p>

      <p>If you instead search Google books for some real content, <a href="http://books.google.com/books?spell=1&amp;q=nightingale+lark+balcony&amp;as_brr=1">nightingale
      lark balcony</a> you'll find Romeo &amp; Juliet in her bed room. Scene V
      in Act III of Romeo and Juliet, on page <a href="http://books.google.com/books?id=09qTVKsjwSwC&amp;lpg=PA190&amp;dq=nightingale%20lark%20balcony&amp;as_brr=1&amp;pg=PA189">189</a>,

      <a href="http://books.google.com/books?id=H_EjAAAAMAAJ&amp;dq=nightingale%20lark%20balcony&amp;as_brr=1&amp;pg=PA160">160</a>
      and a lot of other page numbers, dependent on which edition. In the
      world accoring to me, you may have a lot of hierarchies and they may
      overlap, and OHCO may be false. But if you want to be able to address
      content in a more clever way than the one chosen by Google books, then
      you cannot do without a content model that looks like, well, a tree.</p>

    </div>
  </content>
  <dc:date>2009</dc:date>
  <category label="structuralwebdesign" term="Structural web design"/>
  <category label="metadata" term="Metadata"/>
  <updated>2009-07-17T17:11:49+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/07/structure/</id>
  <!-- $Id$ -->
</entry></feed>
