<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>Sigfrid Lundberg's Stuff</title>
  <id>http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/files.atom</id>
  <link rel="self" href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/SigfridLundbergsStuff?format=xml"/>
  <updated>2006-06-08T00:03:00+01:00</updated>
  <!--
      $Revision$, last modified $Date$
      $Id$
  -->
  <entry>
    <title>NWI — En nordisk söktjänst för World Wide Web</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Anders Ardö</name>
    </author>
    <link href="/1996/nwi/press_release.html"/>
    <summary>Ett konsortium av nordiska forskningsbibliotek och nätverksorgan
    presenterar Nordiskt Webindex, en nordisk söktjänst utvecklad i norden för
    en nordisk publik. I dag finns en experimentell tjänst offentligt
    tillgänglig på nätet på URL http://nwi.ub2.lu.se.</summary>
    <category term="Web indexing" label="webindexing"/>
    <category term="Harvesting" label="harvesting"/>
    <dc:date>1996</dc:date>
    <updated>2006-06-08T00:03:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/1996/nwi/nwi.pdf</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>A proposal for metadata formats for use in the Swedish Enviro-Net</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <link href="/1997/SMN_metadata/smn_metadata.pdf"/>
    <summary>This paper outlines a combination of the Dublin Core metadata
    embedded in HTML metadata tags and the GILS Z39.50 profile used for
    information retrieval. It is a combination would solve the distributed
    indexing, search and retrieval problems within a network of environmental
    authorities. The Swedish Enviro-Net lived for a few years at the end of
    1990ties.</summary>
    <category term="Web indexing" label="webindexing"/>
    <category term="Metadata" label="metadata"/>
    <category term="Z39.50" label="z3950"/>
    <dc:date>1997</dc:date>
    <updated>2006-06-08T00:04:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/1997/SMN_metadata/smn_metadata.pdf</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Kulturnät Sverige</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <link href="/1997/kultur_naet_sverige/"/>
    <summary>En recension av IT i kulturens tjänst, SOU 1997:14 som i mina
    ögon vid den tidpunkten var en fullständigt överflödig utredning. Här
    fanns alla möjligheter att börja arbeta för en konvergens när det gäller
    beskrivningsstandard och protokoll för informationsretrieval mellan olika
    grenar av kultursektorn. En tjock bok som ledde fram till en numera
    nerlagd ämnesportal.</summary>
    <dc:date>1997</dc:date>
    <updated>2009-06-08T00:05:00+01:00</updated>
    <category term="Digital collections" label="digitalcollections"/>
    <category term="Reviews" label="reviews"/>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/1997/kultur_naet_sverige/</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Kulturarw3 archiving format</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg, Lund University</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Allan Arvidson, The Royal Library</name>
    </author>
    <link href="/1998/KulturArw3/archive-format-1.rtf"/>
    <summary>This note describes a file format intended for the joint storage of
    objects retrieved from the World Wide Web and various kinds of meta
    information on those objects. The information includes the HTTP response
    header but may also contain information needed for version control etc
    within the archive. Kulturarw3 project proposes an archiving record format
    based on open standards, namely that objects are stored as HTTP MIME
    multpart/mixed messages (cf. RFC2068 and RFC1521 respectively).</summary>
    <dc:date>1997</dc:date>
    <updated>2006-06-08T00:07:00+01:00</updated>
    <category term="Digital preservation" label="preservation"/>
    <category term="Harvesting" label="harvesting"/>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/1998/KulturArw3/archive-format-1.rtf</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>NWI II, An Enhanced Nordic Web index: Final report</title>
    <author><name>Anders Ardö</name></author>
    <author><name>Allan Arvidson</name></author>
    <author><name>Sebastian Hammer</name></author>
    <author><name>Kenneth Holmlund</name></author>
    <author><name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name></author>
    <link href="/1998/nwi2/"/>
    <summary>The Nordic Web Index (NWI) project is a collaborative effort
    across the Nordic countries, aiming at providing a free Worldwide Web
    search service to the general public in the countries involved. NWI has
    been fruitful for several reasons: First and foremost we are today
    providing access to databases covering the WWW in four of the Nordic
    countries and, as of September 1998, five service points in six languages
    Denmark, Finland, Sweden, Norway and Iceland.</summary>
    <category term="Web indexing" label="webindexing"/>
    <category term="Harvesting" label="harvesting"/>
    <category term="Metadata" label="metadata"/>
    <category term="Z39.50" label="z3950"/>
    <dc:date>1998</dc:date>
    <updated>2006-06-08T00:08:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/1998/nwi2/</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>En arkitektur för ett distribuerat system för spridning av
    forskningsinformation</title>
    <link href="/1998/safari/cris.pdf"/>
    <summary>Arkitekturen för ett nätverk av tjänster för spridning av
    forskningsinformation beskrivs. Nätverket tillåter distribuerat underhåll
    av såväl data som metadata. Till nätverket kan anslutas såväl
    bibliografiska databaser som helt WWWbaserade metadataberikade
    tjänster. Metadataproduktionen följer standarden Dublin Core. De förra
    typerna av tjänster inkorporeras i nätverket genom interoperabilitet på
    sökprotokollsnivå, medan metadata och fulltext från de senare göres
    sökbara genom en WWWrobot.  Kommunikation inom nätverket utnyttjar
    standardiserade Internet protokoll som HTTP, och för
    informationsåtervinning Z39.50</summary>
    <category term="Web indexing" label="webindexing"/>
    <category term="Harvesting" label="harvesting"/>
    <category term="Metadata" label="metadata"/>
    <category term="Z39.50" label="z3950"/>
    <dc:date>1998</dc:date>
    <updated>2006-06-08T00:10:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/1998/safari/cris.pdf</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>A regional distributed WWW search and indexing service - the DESIRE
    way</title>
    <link href="/1998/www7/"/>
    <summary>In an attempt to implement a regional search engine we have
    created an open, metadata aware system for distributed, collaborative
    WWW-indexing. The system has three main components: a harvester (for
    collecting information), a database (for making the collection
    searchable), and a user interface (for making the information
    available). All components can be distributed across networked computers,
    thus supporting scalability. The system is metadata aware and thus allows
    searches on several fields including title, document author, and
    URL. Nordic Web Index (NWI) is an application using this system to create
    a regional Nordic web-indexing service. NWI is built using five
    collaborating service points within the Nordic countries. The NWI
    databases can be used to build additional services. Services today include
    special metadata databases, multimedia databases, and statistics about the
    Nordic Web.</summary>
    <category term="Web indexing" label="webindexing"/>
    <category term="Harvesting" label="harvesting"/>
    <category term="Metadata" label="metadata"/>
    <category term="Z39.50" label="z3950"/>
    <dc:date>1998</dc:date>
    <updated>2008-06-08T00:10:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/1998/www7/</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Noble Art of Being Indexed or the Webmaster's Guide to
    Harvesting Robots</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Lars Nooden</name>
    </author>
    <link href="/1999/web_masters_guide/"/>
    <summary>As the title indicates, this is a note on how to be indexed by
    search engines. It is obsolete. Please note that it does not contain
    anything about search engine optimization in the modern evil
    sense. Instead it pinpoints what harvesting robots did understand, and what
    they didn't at the turn of the last century.</summary>
    <category term="Web indexing" label="webindexing"/>
    <category term="Metadata" label="metadata"/>
    <category term="Structural web design" label="structuralwebdesign"/>
    <dc:date>1999</dc:date>
    <updated>2006-06-09T00:11:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/1999/web_masters_guide/</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Metadata harvesting</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <link href="/2000/delft/"/>
    <summary>This is unfortunately unpublished, but it presents most one of
    the most extensive datasets on the content of HTML embedded metadata which
    I collected while working with the Nordic Webindex.</summary>
    <category term="Web indexing" label="webindexing"/>
    <category term="Harvesting" label="harvesting"/>
    <category term="Metadata" label="metadata"/>
    <category term="Z39.50" label="z3950"/>
    <dc:date>2000</dc:date>
    <updated>2006-06-09T15:11:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/2000/delft/</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Technical description of the Studera.Nu search engine Harvesting
    policies, maintenance and software used</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <link href="/2001/studera.nu/documentation/studera.pdf"/>
    <summary>This is a description of the Studera.NU search engine in the very
    first version. The search engine carries focused information, all of which is
    indexed manually by content providers. The indexing information is
    embedded into web pages using meta tags, and the service is built using a
    harvesting robot.  This article documents the functions of the search
    engine Studera.NU, its robot, search software etc. It aims at providing
    necessary background information both for staff involved in system
    management and future developers. A second aim is to give pinpoint areas
    for future developments of the service.</summary>
    <category term="Web indexing" label="webindexing"/>
    <category term="Harvesting" label="harvesting"/>
    <category term="Metadata" label="metadata"/>
    <dc:date>2001</dc:date>
    <updated>2009-06-09T00:18:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/2001/studera.nu/documentation/studera.pdf</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Lecture notes: S:t Laurentius Digital Manuscript Library</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <link href="/2002/DRH2002/toc.html"/>
    <summary>In this lecture, I discussed the
    experiences gained by the development of a specific service, which, using
    a collection of detailed XML descriptions, provides its users access to a
    collection of digitized medieval manuscripts.  Secondly, I discussed the
    database used from the point of view of both retrieval of the intellectual
    content (the texts) of these manuscripts and of the retrieval of the
    manuscripts as unique entities. Finally, I turned to the possibilities for
    searching a collection of complex XML documents using a full text
    retrieval engine used together with the Z39.50 information retrieval
    protocol.</summary>
    <dc:date>2002</dc:date>
    <category term="XML processing" label="xmlprocessing"/>
    <category term="Metadata" label="metadata"/>
    <category term="Digital humanities" label="ehumanities"/>
    <category term="Digitization" label="digitization"/>
    <updated>2009-06-11T00:06:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/2002/DRH2002/toc.html</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>S:t Laurentius Digital Manuscript Library: An excursion along the
    border between resource discovery and resource description</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <link href="/2002/Laurentius/laurentius.pdf"/>
    <summary>This note has three aims. First it discusses the experiences
    gained by the development of a specific service, which, using a collection
    of detailed XML descriptions, provides its users access to a collection
    of digitized medieval manuscripts.  Secondly, it discusses the database
    used from the point of view of both retrieval of the intellectual content
    (the texts) of these manuscripts and of the retrieval of the manuscripts
    as unique entities. Finally, it explores the possibilities for searching
    a collection of complex XML documents using a full text retrieval engine
    used together with the Z39.50 information retrieval protocol.</summary>
    <dc:date>2002</dc:date>
    <category term="XML processing" label="xmlprocessing"/>
    <category term="Text encoding" label="textencoding"/>
    <category term="Metadata" label="metadata"/>
    <category term="Digital humanities" label="ehumanities"/>
    <category term="Digitization" label="digitization"/>
    <updated>2009-06-11T00:19:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/2002/Laurentius/laurentius.pdf</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Förslag till policy för digitaliseringsprojekt inom Lunds
    Universitets Bibliotek</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <link href="/2002/DigitaliseringsPolicy/digitaliserings_policy.pdf"/>
    <summary>Digital arkivering är att bereda serverplats för information om
    oss, vår tid och vår historia för våra barn och deras efterkommande. Detta
    dokument beskriver förutsättningarna för digitalisering, lagring och
    arkivering samt elektronisk publicering av olika samlingar inom Lunds
    universitet och dess bibliotek. Särskild vikt läggs vid att utveckla en
    nansieringsmodell för lagring, tillgängliggörande och bevarande.</summary>
    <dc:date>2002</dc:date>
    <category term="Digitization" label="digitization"/>
    <category term="Digital collections" label="digitalcollections"/>
    <updated>2009-06-11T00:18:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/2002/DigitaliseringsPolicy/digitaliserings_policy.pdf</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Metadata model in Scripta Academica Lundensis</title>
    <author>
      <name>Colm Doyle</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Jörgen Eriksson</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Sara Kjellberg</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Tomas Schönthal</name>
    </author>
    <link href="/2002/Scripta/"/>
    <summary>This document specifies the metadata once used in the Lund university
    dissertation database.</summary>
    <category term="Digital collections" label="digitalcollections"/>
    <category term="XML processing" label="xmlprocessing"/>
    <category term="Metadata" label="metadata"/>
    <dc:date>2002</dc:date>
    <updated>2009-06-12T00:20:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/2002/Scripta/</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>XML -- en mjuk start för biblioteksfolk Mitt ständigt ofärdiga
    undervisningsmaterial (...och en del annat)</title>
    <link href="/2003/XMLforLibrarians/"/>

    <summary>Denna text syftar till att ge en överblick över vissa områden av
    det digitala biblioteksområdet vilka är stadda i snabb utveckling. En
    utveckling som i hög grad katalyseras av utvecklingen av olika
    tillämpningar av eXtensible Markup Language, XML, som i år fyller fem år.
    Utöver användningen av XML inom det digitala biblioteksväsendet ges en
    överblick över modernt tänkande när det gäller metadata, hur XML kan
    tänkas påverka hur vi tar del av, och hanterar elektroniska texter både i
    form av digitalt bevarande och publicering av t ex
    forskningsrapporter.</summary>

    <category term="XML processing" label="xmlprocessing"/>
    <category term="Text encoding" label="textencoding"/>
    <category term="Metadata" label="metadata"/>
    <dc:date>2002</dc:date>
    <updated>2006-06-11T00:21:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/2003/XMLforLibrarians/</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Implementering av OAI-PMH i ett bibliotekssystem -- Några ord på
    vägen</title>
    <link href="/2003/axiell-oai/oai-opac.pdf"/>
    <summary>Syftet med denna text är att ge lite kött på benen om vad OAI-PMH
    är, vad det kan användas till och hur det skulle kunna integreras i ett
    bibliotekssystem. Det är inte en ersättning för andra dokument utan skall
    ses som några ord på vägen för organisationer som planerar att eller är i
    färd med att implementera OAI-PMH. Texten skrevs på uppdrag av
    http://www.axiell.se/bookit</summary>
    <updated>2009-06-09T08:08:00+01:00</updated>
    <dc:date>2003</dc:date>
    <category term="Harvesting" label="harvesting"/>
    <category term="Metadata" label="metadata"/>
    <category term="Library catalogues" label="opac"/>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/2003/axiell-oai/oai-opac.pdf</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Teknisk samverkan mellan svenska ämnesportaler - Test och
    utvärdering av portalprogramvaran TKL</title>
    <author>
      <name>Colm Doyle</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Jörgen Eriksson</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Tomas Schönthal</name>
    </author>
    <summary>En utvärdering av digital library produkten Keystone DLS (TKL)</summary>
    <link href="/2003/def-test/"/>
    <updated>2009-06-09T08:23:00+01:00</updated>
    <dc:date>2003</dc:date>
    <category term="Digital collections" label="digitalcollections"/>
    <category term="Metadata" label="metadata"/>
    <category term="Reviews" label="reviews"/>
    <category term="XML processing" label="xmlprocessing"/>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/2003/def-test/</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Vad är ett PEK?</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <summary>Här rapporterar jag en konvergent språklig utveckling mellan
    forskare och internerna på Långholmen. I båda kategorierna används ordet
    "pek" för att beskriva en kommunikation, bland akademiker var det på
    1980-talet slang för "uppsats" och på Långholmen var det en text som
    skickades med linbana längs med fängelsemurarna.</summary>
    <link href="/2003/pek/"/>
    <dc:date>2003</dc:date>
    <updated>2009-06-09T20:25:00+01:00</updated>
    <category term="Music, language &amp; literature" label="musiclanglit"/>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/2003/pek/</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Pesistent länkning och digitala bibliotek</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <summary>Åtskillig uppmärksamhet har nyligen riktats mot problemen
    förknippade med att uppnå en stabilare webb. Det konstateras, helt
    korrekt, att mängder med dokument bara försvinner från sina ursprungliga
    platser. Vad skall man då göra åt saken? Vad är det för grundläggande
    designproblem som gör att organisationer vilka underhåller länksamlingar
    av olika slag tvingas bära en allt tyngre börda?</summary>
    <link href="/2003/urnar_och_digitala_bibliotek/"/>
    <dc:date>2003</dc:date>
    <updated>2009-06-09T20:36:00+01:00</updated>
    <category term="Digital libraries" label="digitallibraries"/>
    <category term="Metadata" label="metadata"/>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/2003/urnar_och_digitala_bibliotek/</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Ediffah – En digital infrastruktur för forskningsbibliotekens
    arkiv- och handskriftssamlingar</title>
    <link href="/2004/arkiv_bibliotek/"/>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <summary>Projektet syftar till att göra det möjligt att att skapa skapa
    allmänt tillgängliga kataloger och arkivbeskrivningar över bibliotekens
    handskriftssamlingar och personarkiv. Systemet skall vara enkelt, och
    innehålla ett arbetsflöde sådant att posterna som genereras också med
    automatik kan återfinnas i Nationella arkivdatabasen NAD, vårt
    gemensamma bibliotekssystem LIBRIS, såväl som i lokala
    databaser.</summary>
    <dc:date>2004</dc:date>
    <category term="Archival description" label="archivaldescription"/>
    <category term="Metadata" label="metadata"/>
    <category term="XML processing" label="xmlprocessing"/>
    <updated>2009-06-09T20:36:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/2004/arkiv_bibliotek/</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Vad händer med biblioteket när dess samlingar finns överallt och
    ingen särskild stans?</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <link href="/2004/biblioteket/"/>
    <summary>Biblioteken existerar för att det finns användare som är beredda
    att betala för deras tjänster. Visserligen betalar man i regel via
    skattesedeln och inte med sitt betalkortet, men principen är densamma.
    Under vilka förutsättningar är användarna, eller deras valda
    representanter, redo att betala för bibliotekens tjänster? Går det att
    finansiera lokalt bibliotek när biblioteksresurserna finns överallt och
    ingen särskild stans? Vilken kommun eller vilket universitet kan
    finansiera ett bibliotek som bara har en katalog, men inga samlingar? Och
    när allt kommer omkring, vem vill ha samlingar och varför? De är ju dyra
    och tar plats.</summary>
    <dc:date>2004</dc:date>
    <category term="The Library" label="thelibrary"/>
    <category term="Digital libraries" label="digitallibraries"/>
    <category term="Internet" label="internet"/>
    <updated>2009-06-09T21:01:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/2004/biblioteket/</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Vad en bra samling av digital text bör kunna</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <link href="/2004/digitalisering/position.pdf"/>
    <summary>En diskussion av vilka funktioner ett bra textarkiv bör, och vad
    digitalisering bör innebära.</summary>
    <category term="Digital libraries" label="digitallibraries"/>
    <category term="Metadata" label="metadata"/>
    <category term="Digital collections" label="digitalcollections"/>
    <dc:date>2004</dc:date>
    <updated>2009-06-09T21:10:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/2004/digitalisering/position.pdf</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Digitalisering i Lund</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <summary>En presentation om digitalisering och digitalt bevarande i
    Lund. Jag tror att jag höll den vid ett stort möte på Kungl. Biblioteket i
    Stockholm.</summary>
    <link href="/2004/digitalisering/presentation_04-11-04.html"/>
    <category term="Digital preservation" label="preservation"/>
    <category term="Digitization" label="digitization"/>
    <dc:date>2004</dc:date>
    <updated>2009-06-09T21:45:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/2004/digitalisering/presentation_04-11-04.html</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Metadata makes the world going round - en orientering om användning
    av Metadata och XML</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sara Kjellberg</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <link href="/2004/metadata_makes_the_world/"/>
    <summary>Sara Kjellberg och jag höll ett antal kurser om metadata
    o. XML. detta är vår presentation. Vi höll det inom ramen för BTJs
    kursutbud.</summary>
    <category term="XML processing" label="xmlprocessing"/>
    <category term="Metadata" label="metadata"/>
    <dc:date>2004</dc:date>
    <updated>2009-06-09T21:58:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/2004/metadata_makes_the_world/</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Vilken arkitektur ger ett nav i ett nätverk?  Om
    KB-utredningen</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <link href="/2004/navet/navet.html"/>
    <summary>En recension av KB-utredningen, SOU 2003:129</summary>
    <category term="The Library" label="thelibrary"/>
    <category term="Reviews" label="reviews"/>
    <dc:date>2004</dc:date>
    <updated>2009-06-09T22:06:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/2004/navet/navet.html</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Zornmedaljens baksida</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <summary>En diskussion av Zornmärket och
    riksspelmannainstitutionen och dess roll i svensk folkmusik</summary>
    <link href="/2004/zorn_etc/"/>
    <category term="Music, language &amp; literature" label="musiclanglit"/>
    <dc:date>2004</dc:date>
    <updated>2009-06-09T22:06:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/2004/zorn_etc/</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Ediffah</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <link href="/2005/Oct_28/"/>
    <summary>En superkort presentation om Ediffah, hållen vid
    Ediffahprojektets avslutning på Kungl. Biblioteket i Stockholm den 28
    oktober 2005</summary>
    <category term="Metadata" label="metadata"/>
    <category term="Archival description" label="archivaldescription"/>
    <dc:date>2005</dc:date>
    <updated>2009-06-09T22:06:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/2005/Oct_28/</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Digitala biblioteket</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <summary>En föreläsning om Internets historia, Det Digitala Biblioteket
    och Bibliotekets historia.</summary>
    <link href="/2005/bivil-digitala-bibliotek/"/>
    <dc:date>2005</dc:date>
    <updated>2009-06-09T22:06:00+01:00</updated>
    <category term="Digital libraries" label="digitallibraries"/>
    <category term="Internet" label="internet"/>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/2005/bivil-digitala-bibliotek/</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Digital preservation and digitization at Lund University (and
    elsewhere in Sweden)</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <link href="/2005/digital-preservation/"/>
    <summary>Notes to presentation held in Lund 7 June 2005. The audience was
    a group of people from China</summary>
    <category term="Digital preservation" label="preservation"/>    
    <category term="Digitization" label="digitization"/>
    <category term="Digital collections" label="digitalcollections"/>
    <dc:date>2005</dc:date>
    <updated>2009-06-09T22:06:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/2005/digital-preservation/</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Konkurrerar Google framgångsrikt med biblioteken?</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <link href="/2006/google/google-vs-thelibrary.html"/>
    <summary>En diskussion om Bibliotekets förhållande till sökmaskinen
    Google</summary>
    <category term="The Library" label="thelibrary"/>
    <category term="Digital libraries" label="digitallibraries"/>
    <category term="Internet" label="internet"/>
    <dc:date>2006</dc:date>
    <updated>2009-06-09T23:14:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/2006/google/google-vs-thelibrary.html</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Usage of digital resources with respect to method of publishing</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <link href="/2007/hidden_web/usage_vs_dissemination_method.html"/>
    <summary>I compared the usage of Digital material in relation to whether
    the material was hidden away in the the library opac or published on our
    web site. The result was as expected a disappointment for those who regard
    the Library catalogue as an important vehicle for dissemination of digital
    material</summary>
    <category term="The Library" label="thelibrary"/>
    <category term="Library catalogues" label="opac"/>
    <category term="Digital libraries" label="digitallibraries"/>
    <category term="Internet" label="internet"/>
    <category term="Structural web design" label="structuralwebdesign"/>
    <dc:date>2007</dc:date>
    <updated>2009-06-09T23:14:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/2007/hidden_web/</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>

    <title>What do our users expect from the search field on our top
    page?</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <link href="/2007/search-statistics/user-expectations.html"/>
    <summary>What can deduced by analyses of the search terms entered into the
    search field on the home page of a large modern library? Could we possibly
    regard this form as the digital library´s information desk, and the
    queries as the request from its patrons? If we do that, what could we then
    learn about the quality of service?  In this note we do just that. We
    regard the terms entered into the form as manifestation of our patrons
    needs and in order to find out what they need, we have performed a
    preliminary text mining exercise. We hope that this will help us designing
    a new search facility that will better answer the needs of our
    users.</summary>
    <category term="Web indexing" label="webindexing"/>
    <category term="Harvesting" label="harvesting"/>
    <category term="Library catalogues" label="opac"/>
    <category term="Structural web design" label="structuralwebdesign"/>
    <dc:date>2007</dc:date>
    <updated>2009-06-09T23:31:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/2007/search-statistics/</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>ADL i CLARIN-DK WP5</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <link href="/2008/clarin_adl/"/>
    <summary>En presentation jag höll om Arkiv før dansk litteratur (ADL)</summary>
    <category term="XML processing" label="xmlprocessing"/>
    <category term="Text encoding" label="textencoding"/>
    <category term="Digital humanities" label="ehumanities"/>
    <category term="Music, language &amp; literature" label="musiclanglit"/>
    <dc:date>2008</dc:date>
    <updated>2009-06-09T23:42:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/2008/clarin_adl/</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Digital Humanities Infrastructures</title>
    <author>
      <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    </author>
    <link href="/2008/dighum/digital_humanities.xml"/>
    <summary>This note discusses different initiatives as regards providing
    access to resources and tools aimed at researchers within the
    humanities. Since the general breakthrough of search services like Google,
    annotation and bookmarking services like del.icio.us and the like, the
    attitudes towards the application of computing within the humanities has
    changed. In addition, the concept of e-science has contributed to make
    scholars positive to apply computing to various problems within the
    humanities.  Following a discussion started around year 2000, we propose
    that it is possible to formalize many humanities computing tasks as
    pipelines between XML processing steps.</summary>
    <category term="XML processing" label="xmlprocessing"/>
    <category term="Text encoding" label="textencoding"/>
    <category term="Digital humanities" label="ehumanities"/>
    <dc:date>2008</dc:date>
    <updated>2009-06-09T23:42:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/2008/dighum/digital_humanities.xml</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Kortfattat Curriculum Vitae: Sigfrid Lundberg</title>
    <link href="/2009/cv/cv_sv.xml"/>
    <category term="About me" label="aboutme"/>
    <summary>Ett CV är väldigt tråkigt att skriva</summary>
    <dc:date>2009</dc:date>
    <updated>2009-06-09T23:54:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/2009/cv/cv_sv.xml</id>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>List of publications by Sigfrid Lundberg
    </title>
    <link href="/2009/cv/publications.html"/>
    <summary>Both peer reviewed articles, other articles and some
    presentations</summary>
    <dc:date>2009</dc:date>
    <updated>2009-06-09T23:57:00+01:00</updated>
    <category term="About me" label="aboutme"/>
    <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/2009/cv/publications.html</id>
  </entry>

<entry xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>Add footnotes to my pages -- a prototype text annotation
  interface</title>
  <link href="/footnotes/"/>
  <summary>I've had a javascript based forum with thread for each entry. That
  seemed boring to me. Why should users be restricted to commenting entire
  articles. Why not letting them add footnotes to arbitrary positions in a
  text. In this entry I experiment with this feature.</summary>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

      <p>In order to understand what's going on here, you have have to <a href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/footnotes/">visit the
      resource</a>. There is a some scripting going on which cannot be
      syndicated. If you're reading this, you are on the wrong
      page. Sorry.</p>

      <h2>What you can do here</h2>

      <p>There is a link at the top of this page (if you're reading the HTML
      version <a href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/footnotes/">directly from my
      site</a>, that is). It says "Show anchors". It's not a very user
      friendly description of what it does, but I cannot figure out a better
      term right now. If you click on it, there will appear a link after most
      words in the text. These are the annotation anchors of this text.</p>

      <p>When visible, the anchors appears as a clickable asterisk '*', and a
      click on one of them activates the usual <a href="disqus.com">disqus.com
      forum</a>. This is by some client side DOM programming.</p>

      <p>Submitting a footnote works, but the script never get the
      acknowledgement from the disqus.com server. I don't know why, but it
      seems that the form doesn't like to live in an iframe.</p>

      <p id="anchor55576b680.592539918884886">My server retrieves the
      annotations from the disqus.com web services and print a list of notes
      at the end of the page. This is done server side, shuch that the
      discussions within the footnotes will be visible by search engines. The
      place of the annotation is marked as a note with a link to the
      notes. You may read the annotation when your mouse is over the link.</p>

      <p>Is this a good idea? Do you like it? Should all my pages have user
      supplied foot notes?</p>
      
      <h2>How is it done</h2>

      <p id="anchor55018b510.584488500647474">In order to add footnotes to a
      text, we need to be able to address individual positions in it. These
      positions are what I'd like to call annotation anchors. I've already
      briefly discussed the problem on how to create identifiers (see a <a href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/08/quotations/">A
      quotation is much more than an extract</a>). For this entry I've
      extended the xslt script such that it can <a href="http://exslt.org/str/functions/tokenize/">tokenize</a> html text
      embedded in atom entry documents. It can also add anchors (id
      attributes) on each individual word (produced by the tokenize function)
      in the whole text. We also implement a javascript which expose these
      anchors to users, and allow them to comment more or less arbitrary point
      in the text.</p>

      <p id="anchor55402b10.359095368701543">There is a <strong>big</strong>
      drawback in this procedure; once you have processed your text and the
      anchors are there, then you <strong>must not</strong> change them. Each
      word has become a resource on the internet. Please view the source of
      this document, before you use the stylesheet <kbd><a href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/footnotes/atom_anchor_id.xsl">atom_anchor_id.xsl</a></kbd>.</p>

      <pre>
	&lt;span id="anchor54764"&gt;Would&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span id="anchor54766"&gt;you&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span id="anchor54768"&gt;like&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span id="anchor54770"&gt;to&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span id="anchor54772"&gt;edit&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span id="anchor54774"&gt;this&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span id="anchor54778"&gt;text?&lt;/span&gt;
      </pre>

      <p>See what I mean? I cannot author prose like that in my XML
      editor. You wouldn't suffer as much using WYSIWYG tools, but on the hand
      it would presumably destroy the ID-strings.</p>

      <p>When preparing this text, I felt that I had to prepare some
      annotations of my own, and in order to do that I compiled the text,
      published it, made my annotation and then pasted the ID back into the
      source XML in order to be able to continue writing. Formbased proof
      reading of an existing digital text wouldn't be any problem, though.</p>

      <h2>Javascript &amp; DOM scripting</h2>

      <p>You can find the possible anchors by clicking on the link
      <strong>Show anchors</strong>, and hide them again by clicking on
      <strong>Hide anchors</strong> at the same place (there is a
      toggle). There are two javascript functions handling the toggling. The
      possibly most interesting, but also, the most vulnerable, feature is the
      generation of javascript from rss for handling the readable
      notes.</p>

      <pre>
      &lt;script type="text/javascript"&gt;
	    var usedAnchorIds = new Array();
	    var noteTexts     = new Array();
	    
	    usedAnchorIds[0]="anchor55402b10.359095368701543";

	    noteTexts[0]='I had problems obtaining unique id strings from the'
	    +'generate-id() function in XSLT. (siggelundberg, Fri, 18 Sep 2009'
	    +'17:46:27 -0000)';

	    usedAnchorIds[1]="anchor55018b510.584488500647474";

	    noteTexts[1]='This is an arbitrary point in my text. I find this'
	    +'really suitable for adding a footnote. (siggelundberg, Fri, 18 Sep
	    +'2009 03:27:16 -0000)';

	    printNotes(usedAnchorIds,noteTexts);

    &lt;/script&gt;
      </pre>

      <p>The rest of the features are readily visible on this page. You have
      to reaload the page to see the new footnote -- if I implement this I'll
      will refresh those asynchronously.</p>

    </div>
  </content>
  <dc:date>2009</dc:date>
  <category label="structuralwebdesign" term="Structural web design"/>
  <category label="xmlprocessing" term="XML Processing"/>
  <updated>2009-09-19T15:13:49+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/footnotes/</id>

</entry>


<entry xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>Twelve weeks</title>
  <link href="/entries/2009/09/twelveweeks/"/>
  <summary>It is twelve weeks since i refurbished and redecorated this
  site. It is time for an evaluation...</summary>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">


      <p>It is about twelve weeks since i refurbished and redecorated this
      site. It is time for an evaluation. I do ask myself more or less daily
      if I can continue to say that this is worthwhile? My answer has been yes
      so far. I also ask myself if I do a good enough job, and to that my
      answer has been: Yes, I believe that some of my entries are good
      enough.</p>


      <div style="float: left; width: 50%; margin-left:0.5em;margin-right:0.5em;">

	<a href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/09/twelveweeks/usage.pdf">
	  <img src="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/09/twelveweeks/usage.png" alt="About 12 weeks usage statistics for my site." width="100%" border="0"/>
	</a>

	<p>
	  <small>Figure 1. Average number of visits per week for my site
	  sigfrid-lundberg.se (in blue) and the average time (in seconds)
	  people stay there (in red). Week 1 in the graph is the starting June
	  14, 2009. The last week is August 23 to 29.</small>
	</p>
      </div>

      <p>The number of visitors has been growing steadily from only a few
      individual visitors per week, to about two dozen. But on the other hand
      the time spend reading have declined dramatically (Figure 1). I do have
      a handful of visitors staying for a couple of minutes reading my weekly
      entry. This is easy to tell from the google statistics. I have no graphs
      on this, but distribution of time spent per visit is bimodal. A majority
      stays less than ten seconds, very few stay for a minute but a larger
      minority stay for three to five minutes, perhaps reading one entry and
      skimming another.</p>

      <p>My most successful entry is <a href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/08/trends/">On Divorce and
      Unemployment Benefit Societies</a>. I do think it deserves it, but the
      key to its success is that I wrote a comment on Google Research Blog, <a href="http://googleresearch.blogspot.com/2009/07/posted-by-hal-varian-chief-economist.html">the
      place</a> that inspired me to write in the first place. Just yesterday I
      got 26 visitors through that blog entry.</p>

      <p>That entry was also the one that took most time to write, followed by
      my text <a href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/07/commuting/">On being an
      international commuter</a> where the actual wordsmithing took an awful
      amount of time. Two people has told me that they thought it was funny.</p>

      <h2>Subject matters</h2>

      <p>I've mentioned earlier that I started all this by adding categories
      to all material that existed here before (mind you, this site is fifteen
      years old). I've hardly used any of them. Why should I. I'd rather not
      wright anything about harvesting or Z39.50. (I've done both the last
      three years, but these topics doesn't interest me anymore.)</p>

      <p>I suppose I should figure out a new system to categorize my material,
      but then why should I?</p>

      <h2>It does take time</h2>

      <p>All this writing takes time, and energy. I feel that I have to
      publish something every week. I mostly use the time I spend on train
      between Lund and Copenhagen, but I also use several hours on evenings
      and weekends on this. You cannot start a project which is time consuming
      without side effects. I read less novels and literature just for the fun
      of it. I've hardly touched my flute and <a href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/images/Degeberga_duo.shtml" title="me       and my son Erik cooking porridge while playing a polska">recorders</a>
      during this period.</p>

      <p>I've read somewhere that it takes about half a year to establish a
      blog, and I suppose that's about it. I won't write about web statistics
      until then.</p>


    </div>
  </content>
  <dc:date>2009</dc:date>
  <category label="essays" term="Essays"/>
  <updated>2009-09-05T13:10:12+01:00</updated>
  <published>2009-09-01T17:42:45+01:00</published>
  <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/09/twelveweeks/</id>
  <!-- $Id$ -->
</entry><entry xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>Att tjäna den demokratiska kulturnationens minne</title>
  <link href="/entries/2009/09/msb/"/>
  <summary>Jag har arbetat med att programmera digitala bibliotek i ungefär 15
  år. När jag läser debatten om biblioteket i Sydsvenskan känner jag att jag
  borde säga något. Jag vet inte i vilken utsträckning mitt perspektiv kommer
  att kännas relevant för alla de som känner sig kallade att yttra sig, men
  jag har en hel del erfarenheter som nog de flesta andra saknar.</summary>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

      <p>Det har varit en lång debatt om vad biblioteket är till för i
      Sydsvenskan, nu senast av Per Svensson: <a href="http://sydsvenskan.se/kultur-och-nojen/article551225/Viva-Las-Vegas.html">Viva
      Läs Vegas</a>. Här kommer min version av varför jag tycker vi behöver
      bibliotek.</p>

      <p>Biblioteket bygger på två principer. När jag säger biblioteket menar
      jag inget särskilt bibliotek, vare sig Library of Congress, Umberto Ecos
      klosterbibliotek i <q>Rosens namn</q> eller för den delen Malmö
      Stadsbibliotek, utan biblioteket som idé. Jag syftar på alla bibliotek i
      kollektiv singularis. För att över huvud taget förstå varför det finns
      bibliotek, måste man ta hänsyn till de två prinicperna.</p>

      <p>Den första principen är att det är lönsamt för de som läser och
      studerar att dela böcker. Böcker har varit sällsynta, dyrbara och
      platskrävande. Under en stor del av den civiliserade mänsklighetens
      historia har det funnits bibliotek som den boksynte gärna tagit en omväg
      för att kunna besöka. Den andra principen är att man gjort ett undantag
      i upphovsrätten som gör just denna delning möjlig i en
      marknadsekonomi. Författare får en viss ersättning per utlån.</p>

      <p>Förnyarna i biblioteksdebatten ser säkert denna inledning som
      ytterligt konservativ. <em>À la bon heur.</em> Det enda sättet att få en
      träff på i princip enbart mission statements för större Nordamerikanska
      bibliotek är att söka på <a href="http://www.google.com/search?hl=en&amp;q=collect+preserve+organize+provide+access&amp;start=0&amp;sa=N">collect
      preserve organize provide access</a> i Google. Det smyger sig in en del
      arkiv i träffmängden, med det är flest bibliotek.</p>

      <h2>Public service search engines</h2>

      <p>Jag har arbetat med att programmera digitala bibliotek i ungefär 15
      år. Jag startade min första webbserver 1994 och började arbeta
      professionellt med forskning &amp; utveckling på
      digitalabiblioteksområdet mindre än ett år senare. Mitt personliga mål
      har hela tiden varit att <em>inte</em> arbeta med problem vars lösning
      går att köpa, att hela tiden ligga vid någon front. Under nittiotalet
      låg biblioteken faktiskt i framkant i IT-utvecklingen. Vi arbetade med
      att testa var gränserna går. Vårt arbetsområde var information. Böckerna
      var bara en källa. Vid NetLab vid Lunds universitet arbetade vi med att
      bygga sökrobotar och såg det som en naturlig uppgift för oss att
      organisera hela Internet enligt public service-principen. När vi började
      arbetet kunde sökmaskinen Lycos, som hade monopol just då, inte indexera
      dokument med europeiska tecken.</p>

      <p>Ödet ville att vi skulle släppa Nordiskt Webbindex månaden efter Alta
      Vista släppte sin sökmaskin. De kunde, precis som vi, faktiskt söka på
      <em>ål and öl</em>, och att <a href="http://www7.scu.edu.au/1900/com1900.htm">vi skulle presentera
      oss</a> vid the <a href="http://www7.scu.edu.au/">Seventh International
      Worldwide Web Conference 1998</a>, samma konferens där två unga
      studenter från Kalifornien, <a href="http://www7.scu.edu.au/1921/com1921.htm">Lawrence Page och Sergey
      Brin</a>, presenterade en ny sökmaskin som de kallade Google.</p>

      <p>Jag ägnade mig åt att sälja insamling, bevarande, organisering och
      tillgängliggörande av Internet ytterligare något år, sedan fick andra ta
      över. Det finns ingen som vill finansiera organisering av informationen
      på Internet enligt public service-modellen. Jag programmerar fortfarande
      digitala bibliotek, men det är en annan historia.</p>

      <h2>Biblioteket i Chris Anderson's värld</h2>

      <p>Som biblioteksperson tillhör jag den minoritet som <em>aldrig</em>
      arbetat med annat än digital library R&amp;D. Som sådan kan jag inte
      förstå varför inte Chris Andersons böcker <em>The Long Tail</em> och
      <em>Free</em> inte nämnts en enda gång i Sydsvenskan. Åtminstone inte i
      de artiklar som jag har läst.</p>

      <p>Det traditionella biblioteket är inklämt mellan Akademibokhandeln, å
      ena sidan, och Amazoogle å den andra. Google har som uttalat mål att
      organisera <a href="http://www.wired.co.uk/wired-magazine/archive/2009/08/features/the-unstoppable-google.aspx">all  information
      i världen</a>.</p>

      <p>Boklådorna säljer hitlistornas material, och Amazoogle distribuerar
      resten.</p>

      <p>Information väger ingenting längre, den är inte dyr och tar inte så
      mycket plats. Inte ens fysiska böcker är dyrbara att lagra om man har
      ett magasin långt ute in the middle of nowhere. Med rätt logistik
      fungerar det ändå.  25% av Amazon's försäljning är titlar som ligger
      utanför deras 100,000 toppsäljare. De har ett helt nätverk av
      antikvariat bakom sig för att kunna tillfredsställa de mest esoteriska
      önskemål. Vad Malmö Stadsbibliotek betraktar som hyllvärmare är big
      business för Amazoogle.</p>

      <p>I massdigitaliseringens årtionde är de utgallrade böckerna
      hårdvaluta.</p>

      <h2>En demokratisk kulturnations minne</h2>

      <p>Skall vi ha hus med böcker? Det inte är uppenbart att vi behöver
      sådana hus. Problemet är likartat som när René Descartes betvivlade sin
      egen existens. Det gäller att hitta en punkt där vi kan nysta upp 
      den härva av argument vi sett för Biblioteket. Det finns
      faktiskt en sak som bara bibliotek gör, och det är att bevara
      kulturnationens minne. OK, Malmö Stadsbibliotek slänger en del. Men tro
      mig, de skulle inte slänga sista examplaret av en titel, om den råkade
      finnas i samlingarna där.</p>

      <p>Små som stora bibliotek samlar och bevarar. Det finns lokalsamlingar
      ute vid folkbiblioteken. De stora nationalbiblioteken gör sådant som att
      bevara Worldwide Web. Det görs vid Kungl. Biblioteket i Humlegården och
      vi gör det vid Det Konglige Bibliotek i København.</p>

      <p>Allt detta samlande utgör den demokratiska kulturnationens minne. Vi
      kan inte överlåta denna uppgift till någon annan. Vare sig till
      Akademibokhandeln eller Amazoogle. Inte ens till <a href="http://www.archive.org">Internet Archive</a>. Om vi börjar vid
      denna punkt kan vi förstå att vi faktiskt inte skulle klara oss utan
      biblioteken.</p>

      <p>Varje kommun, region och nation måste samla, bevara, organisera och
      tillgängliggöra. Den som inte gör det kommer att förlora en viktig del
      av sig själv. Minnet. Vi måste tillhandahålla unikt material via webben
      i våra digitala bibliotek, vi måste ha en rent fysisk infrastruktur i
      form av läsesalar där studenter tentamensläser och raggar. Varje
      målgrupp måste ha sina faciliteter.</p>

      <p>Ja, och så kan vi bygga vidare. Och då har vi snart mentalt byggt ett
      hus med böcker, och dessutom insett att vi behöver det. Även om somliga
      köper sina Stieg Larsson och Camilla Läckberg på ICA, och sin De
      Consolatione Philosophie via amazon.com.</p>

      <p>Problemet är närmast när vi inom biblioteksväsendet börjar skämmas
      för att vi faktiskt tjänar den demokratiska kulturnationens
      minne.</p>

    </div>
  </content>
  <dc:date>2009</dc:date>
  <category label="thelibrary" term="The Library"/>
  <category label="internet" term="Internet"/>
  <updated>2009-09-20T15:55:13+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/09/msb/</id>
</entry><entry xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>Why do I keep this site?</title>
  <link href="/entries/2009/06/why/"/>
  <summary>Having had a web site for about 15 years, I start to wonder why I
  keep it in the first place.</summary>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

      <p>A week or two ago I registered this site with Google Analytics. My
      Internet supply provider's statics is virtually useless. Then I've spent
      quite some time cutting and pasting the javascript into my olde
      stuff.</p>

      <p>I haven't cared about this site for about four years and as far as I
      can tell now, this place is hit by a one or two people per day, each of
      which stay less than a minute. Why they come I don't know, and Google
      Analytics won't tell me yet.</p>

      <p>Now, I didn't expect anything else. I use the site as a store for old
      documentation, of which just a few things could possibly be valuable for
      students of Internet history. Most likely, though, they hardly even
      deserve a footnote in the posterity.</p>

      <h3>The origins</h3>

      <p>I started this site autumn 1995. The oldest documents still in the
      public collection is from <a href="/1996">1996</a>. Now, started isn't
      really the right word. I never <em>planned</em> to build a web site
      with old documents. Basically, I started a web server on a development
      machine and devoted an area for project documentation and reports. I
      could then drop a piece of text there and send the URI to my colleagues
      or customers. That is how it started.</p>

      <p>This worked well to begin with, but about five years later the
      rudimentary structure per project was lost. I then made a backup copy,
      and created a structure by year, and copied stuff from the old site into
      it. This is the way it is now.</p>

      <p>I started the current site <a href="/2005">2005</a>, when I left Lund
      university for a new job in Copenhagen. I felt that I just couldn't let
      this material just disappear.</p>

      <p>The site contains quite a few archived files. Counting them gives 241
      HTML files, 21 pdf, 84 xml and so forth. Of these I regard 37 as
      publications of some kind, in the sense that there are links to them
      that may be reached from the home page. It is still just a sample, the
      raw collection contains 2452 HTML files.</p>

      <p>I have no idea if I have benefited from the site, or if the material
      has been useful for someone else. For a few years, notably <a href="/2002">2002</a>, <a href="/2003">2003</a> and <a href="/2004">2004</a>, I did have an idea that I should make an active
      effort to maintain a web site. Some of the best texts are from that
      period.</p>

      <h3>Publish or let it perish?</h3>

      <p>I earn my livelihood as a developer for the Worldwide Web. But this
      site is not a part of what I do for my living. So, should I have it
      available here or let it perish?</p>

      <p>I pay my ISP 250 SEK per month for this, which include a Linux shell
      prompt available via secure shell and some storage. The storage side of
      it is no big deal; I have already a number of USB hard disks around. I
      have also <kbd>*.zip</kbd> and <kbd>*.tar.gz</kbd> files as attachment
      on my gmail account, which provides huge storage and good value for
      money in comparison with what I get from my ISP. But then, 250 SEK is no
      big deal either.</p>

      <p>So I'll keep it, for the time being. I don't think my stuff
      contribute very much to the digital refuse spread over the net. I've
      added an <a href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc4287">ATOM syndication
      feed</a> for the garbage I decided to keep, a subject browsing based on
      the ATOM categories. Finally I've added some texts from the last few
      years. These are basically of the same kind as the rest of my
      stuff. Reports and papers written for some specific purpose and
      republished here entirely out of context.</p>

    </div>
  </content>
  <dc:date>2009</dc:date>
  <category label="structuralwebdesign" term="Structural web design"/>
  <updated>2009-06-27T12:18:00+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/feed/why.xml</id>
</entry><entry xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>Min mor</title>
  <link href="/entries/2009/06/mor/"/>
  <summary>Min mor var 43 år gammal när hon födde mig 1956. Alltså föddes hon
  själv 1913, året innan första världskriget bröt ut. Nu är hon 96, och lever,
  som hon säger, på lånad tid. Tid, det är något som hon tar på största
  allvar. Vi talas vid per telefon varje dag. Hon ringer 20.10, nästan
  exakt. Det blir alltid ett trevligt samtal.</summary>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

      <p>Min mor var 43 år gammal när hon födde mig 1956. Alltså föddes hon
      själv 1913, året innan första världskriget bröt ut. Nu är hon 96, och
      lever, som hon säger, på lånad tid. Tid, det är något som hon tar på
      största allvar. Vi talas vid per telefon varje dag. Hon ringer 20.10,
      nästan exakt. Det blir alltid ett trevligt samtal.</p>
      
      <p style="margin-left:0.5em;float:left;">
	<img src="http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/galleri/200902-200904/smaller/cimg1150.jpg" alt="Mor i dörrent"/>
      </p>

      <p>När det är dags att säga godnatt, återkomer hon ständigt till att man
      måste vara tacksam för varje dag som gått, och att "i morgon är det en
      ny dag". Visst har Mor rätt! Det är faktiskt inte är självklart att man
      får leva hela nästa dag. Har man hunnit med ett långt liv, så är man
      mer medveten om den saken än vad vi, yngre människor, är.</p>

      <p>Jag tänker på det ibland, att hon har varit med om en stor del av
      1900-talet, och hur hon kan tala om arbetslösheten på 30-talet, om
      Krügerkraschen 1931. Då var hon en fager ung kvinna 18 år gammal. Mor
      har varit folkpensionär under i princip hela mitt yrkesverksamma liv,
      hon föddes innan ryska revolutionen och lever faktiskt fortfarande.  Hon
      arbetar fortfarande i trädgården. "Ni behöver inte vara rädda, jag kan
      inte trilla när jag sitter på marken," berättade hon nyligen.</p>

      <p>I mars i år fick hon höra på radion om SEBs nyemission nu i mars
      månad tog hon rollatorn ner till Handelsbanken. Som folkpensionär tjänar
      hon 7000 kronor i månaden, så för att köpa de femhundra hennes innehav
      berättigade henne till, fick hon höja sin checkkontokredit. Vi fick 200
      aktier var, jag och min bror. Det var för sina barns skull hon köpte
      aktierna på lånade pengar.</p>

      <h2>En ny påminnelse om vår dödlighet</h2>

      <p>I dag när vi talades vid berättade hon om gravstenen. Min far dog i
      september i fjol 93 år och tre månader gammal, men det är först nu som
      vi fått gravstenen på plats, och Mor är lycklig för det. Den är i lite
      mer äldre stil, hög och smal, inte så där bred och låg som många
      gravstenar är numera. Jag har inte sett den själv ännu, men mor säger
      att den är vacker. Huggen i grå granit från Östra Göinge, i trakten
      kring Glimåkra, där Far växte upp. Texten är i Garamond, stilen som Far
      tyckte bäst om, jämte Berling Antikva. Far var boktryckare och vi har
      nog åtskilliga hundra kilo Berling Antikva i källaren efter honom.</p>

      <p>Mor ser illa. Hon har både grå starr och gula fläcken och kan inte
      läsa inte tidningen längre. Men lyssnar hon på radio det gör hon. Jag
      tror att hon sitter där i köket och lyssnar mest hela dagen. Inte missar
      hon en nyhetssänding om hon kan undvika det. Ekot och i synnerhet
      ekonomiekot är viktigt. Radioföljetongen och radioteatern är hennes enda
      intag av skönlitteratur nuförtiden.</p>

      <p>Mor började skolan 1920. Det var inte så ovanligt på den tiden att
      flickornas utbildning försummades på bekostnad av gossarnas. För hennes
      del blev det aldrig mer än sexårig folkskola. Istället läste hon in
      nästan stora delar av en gymnasiekompetens på KOMvux mot slutet av
      60-talet och början av 70-talet. Det blev dock inte moderna språk eller
      matematik, för det var hennes förkunskaper för klena.</p>

      <p>Dagligen diskuterar vi utvecklingen i världen, och hon berättar annat
      som hon har hört på radion. Mor har stor tillit till att Barack Obama
      och hoppas på fred i mellersta östern. Nu senast har hon talat en del om
      PO Enquists som går som radioföljetong just nu, med författaren själv
      som uppläsare.</p>

      <h2>En kopp kaffe</h2>

      <p>Vi åker hem till mor var eller varannan helg, jag och min bror. Vi
      byts om för att hon skall få besök oftare.</p>

      <p>När jag är hos henne äter vi lunch tillsammans. Sedan lyssnar vi på
      lunchekot medan vi tar en kopp kaffe på maten. Sedan stänger vi av
      radion och går igenom posten, mest fönsterkuvert. Nästan varje gång ber
      hon mig att läsa jag högt ur tidningen. Börsnoteringarna för hennes
      aktier och dödsannonserna måste jag läsa varje gång vi träffas.</p>

      <p>Så är det i livet. När man är ung funderar man kanske inte så mycket
      över det, men det är ju så att man umgås väldigt mycket med människor
      som är som man själv är. Unga umgås med unga, småbarnsfamiljer med
      varandra och de diskuterar barn. När man kommer upp i medelåldern
      diskuterar man barn, barnbarn och sjuka föräldrar. När blir gammal
      gammal läser man dödsannonserna. När man är så gammal som Mor är det
      få kvar av hennes vänner att läsa om där.</p>

      <p>Efter kaffet språkar om allt möjligt. Ofta går vi en promenad, men
      oftast tycker hon bättre att gå uppför än nerför. Rollatorn rullar för
      fort och det är lätt att hon inte hinner med den i nerförsbacke.</p>

      <p>Mor tycker om poesi. Hon kan en hel massa dikter och psalmverser
      utantill som hon gärnar citerar när det passar. Hon har tränat yoga
      sedan hon fyllde 60, och hon tränar varje dag. Jag tror också att hon
      dagligen läser alla de dikter och psalmer hon kan utantill, och i
      synnerhet JO Wallins:</p>

      <blockquote>
	<em>Ack, när så mycket skönt i varje åder<br/>
	av skapelsen och livet sig förråder,<br/>
	hur skön då måste själva källan vara,<br/>
	den evigt klara</em>
      </blockquote>

      <p>Fast hon kan minst fem verser till.</p>

    </div>
  </content>
  <dc:date>2009</dc:date>
  <category label="essays" term="Essays"/>
  <updated>2009-06-28T23:33:00+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/06/mor/</id>
</entry><entry xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
    <uri>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/</uri>
  </author>
  <title>My first serious experience with ATOM</title>
  <link href="/entries/2009/06/atom/"/>
  <summary>You don't really understand a document format until you've manually
  encoded some documents, and written the software to parse and use it for
  something useful. This somewhat refurbished version of my web site is to a
  large extent built upon the ATOM syndication format, and here I discuss my
  experience.</summary>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

      <p>The <a href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc4287">ATOM syndication
      format</a> has been around for almost five years. In comparison with the
      diverse fauna kept in the menagerie abbreviated to the three character
      acronym RSS, ATOM is a well kept standard and much more useful as
      well.</p>

      <p>Now, I've used ATOM before refurbishing my personal web site, but I
      haven't used <em>seriously</em>. That is, I haven't manually encoded a
      sizeable amount of text in it, validated the result, and then written
      software using the data. ATOM is the fundament for this site, since the
      data used for generating the navigation system is encoded that way. I
      may return to that later on.</p>

      <h2>Designed for success</h2>

      <p>Tim Bray lists and provide a thorough discussion of a number of
      characteristics shared by successful mark-up languages (see his article
      <a href="http://web.archive.org/web/20070126140434/www.idealliance.org/proceedings/xml05/ship/175/xml2005.HTML">On
      Language Creation</a>). The list of success critera includes items such
      as extensibility, clever but not too extensive use of XML name spaces,
      the posibility of implementing the language using many, widely different,
      datamodels. From Bray's perspective, ATOM seems designed for success. I
      don't know the statistics concerning syndication format popularity, but
      if ATOM isn't yet the leader, it will become sooner or later. Possibly
      in RDF disguise.</p>

      <p>From a modelling point of view there is a few, annoying
      inconsistencies. Let us, for example, compare the <kbd>&lt;author&gt;</kbd>
      element with the <kbd>&lt;title&gt;</kbd> element. A resource may have an
      author, then the author may have a number of properties, such as a name,
      an email address and a home page. The <kbd>author</kbd> for this note is
      encoded as:</p>

      <pre>
  &lt;author&gt;
    &lt;name&gt;Sigfrid Lundberg&lt;/name&gt;
    &lt;uri&gt;http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/&lt;/uri&gt;
  &lt;/author&gt;
      </pre>

      <p>This is, in my view, a sign of good content modelling when it comes
      to metadata. A resource may have a title. A title may have different
      components, for example main title and sub-title. The main and sub parts
      are properties of the title, not of the resource. The authors of the
      ATOM spec did not see that way. A feed may have both. This is annoying
      for semantic puristic nerd like me. Entries, however, may not have
      sub-titles at all, which in my view is an inconsistency as well.</p>

      <p>The biggest flaw is the encoding of category data. A resource belongs
      to a category, i.e., this membership is a property of the resource. The
      category may have an identifier and a name, and this name is different
      depending to language. However, ATOM forces me to use the following
      construct</p>

      <pre>
  &lt;category xml:lang="en" label="structuralwebdesign" term="Structural web design" /&gt;
  &lt;category xml:lang="sv" label="structuralwebdesign" term="Structurell webbdesign" /&gt;
      </pre>

      <p>which in my view is less than excellent. I would have preferred
      something like</p>

      <pre>
  &lt;category label="structuralwebdesign"&gt;
    &lt;name xml:lang="en"&gt;Structural web design&lt;/name&gt;
    &lt;name xml:lang="sv"&gt;Strukturell webbdesign&lt;/name&gt;
  &lt;/category&gt;
      </pre>

      <p>These are shortcomings, but I can live with them. But expect changes
      in this area. The semantic web is here already, and with <a href="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/">SKOS</a> becoming a de facto
      standard on the internet, the syntactic communities will have to come up
      with something more clever for categorization of syndicated web
      resources.</p>

    </div>
  </content>
  <dc:date>2009</dc:date>
  <category label="structuralwebdesign" term="Structural web design"/>
  <category term="Metadata" label="metadata"/>
  <updated>2009-06-27T17:35:00+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/06/atom/</id>
</entry><entry xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>Why I love XSLT extension functions</title>
  <link href="/entries/2009/07/xslt_extensions/"/>
  <summary>xslt extensions allow you to define xpath functions and extension
  elements. That makes it easy for you to perform tasks within xslt that are
  just only theoretically possible to do.</summary>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

      <p>I started learning XSLT eight years ago. At the time, it was a fresh
      technology, and there was also intense discussions on the extensibility
      of the language. Since then xslt 1.1 has disappeared down the drains,
      xpath 2.0 &amp; xquery 1.0 appeared on the market. The former of these
      has had a slow start. The latter, however, has gained acceptance,
      however a bit reluctant.</p>

      <p>The stuff I want to discuss here is the writing of extension
      functions. This is regarded as an evil habit in some parts of the XML
      processing communities, but it is supported by most implementations. It
      is not to be recommended if you're producing a stand-alone application,
      but in many cases you're xslt code is an integrated part of an
      application. Most of my code is of this kind; in particular I'm writing
      xslt for xalan running in a JAVA environment. Now, why should I refrain
      from using regex, just because xalan does not support this package? I
      cannot see why. And nobody would ask me to write ANSI SQL in spite of
      the fact that we use Oracle.</p>

      <p>Now, it has been proven mathematically that xslt is a <a href="http://www.ibm.com/developerworks/library/x-xalanextensions.html">Turing
      complete</a> programming language. That means that it is possible to
      program <strong>anything</strong> which is possible to program with such
      a language. I.e., you have theoretically the same possibilities as in
      JAVA and C++. That doesn't mean that it is practical do do so. It is, in
      my view, much easier to traverse a XML tree in XSLT than in (say) JAVA,
      whereas it is much easier to connect to a database or implement a XSLT
      processor using a conventional programming language.</p>

      <p>It is here the XSLT extension functions become really useful. You can
      pass data from XSLT to your own functions written in your favourite
      programming lanuguage. I use this for tasks like indexing XML
      documents. When traversing a document, you select text and pass it to
      you're function which pass it to your indexing API. One big advantage is
      that the same software can index heterogenous collections of XML
      documents just by using different XSLT scripts. They are easy to write
      and you can a new document type without recompilation of you're indexing
      software.</p>

      <p>This ability of a fullblown functional programming language (mind
      you, its Turing complete) to interface both with a host program and from
      scripts inside it call other functions in other languages is
      powerful. This, in combination that it is really good for what it is
      designed for has made it an object for extreme affection from
      me. Besides I'll return to examples of using XSLT for indexing complex
      XML objects.</p>

    </div>
  </content>
  <dc:date>2009</dc:date>
  <category label="xmlprocessing" term="XML processing"/>
  <updated>2009-07-21T18:01:19+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/07/xslt_extensions/</id>
  <!-- $Id$ -->
</entry><entry xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>On being an international commuter</title>
  <link href="/entries/2009/07/commuting/"/>
  <summary>The last four years I've spent more than two hours a day on
  trains. And usually, but not always less than three. Furthermore, I go from
  one nation to another and participate in the in the digital dissemination of
  cultural heritage of a country which isn't my own.</summary>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">


      <img src="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/07/commuting/102-0039s.jpg" style="margin-left:0.5em;float:right;margin-right:0.5em; width:50%" alt="Sigfrid Lundberg as an international commuter"/>

      <p>[Update: My friend and former colleague <a href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/images/Tomas_and_Sigfrid.shtml">Tomas</a>
      took a day off from his work at Lund university and went to
      Copenhagen. Tomas is documenting just about everything he does, and
      here's his documentation of me as an international commuter.]</p>

      <p>In both Lund and Copenhagen there are a lot of people riding
      bicycles. They behave very differently, however, and their spatial
      distribution is different. In Copenhagen the riders have a much more
      aggregated distribution. They ride at high speed in squadrons, somewhat
      like Mongolian cavalry. Before their mounted assaults on the pedestrians
      on H.C. Andersens Boulevard, their prime target, the Copenhagen bicycle
      riders congregate at any of the many traffic lights in the area.</p>

      <p>In Lund, where the traffic lights are more scarce, there are few
      natural meeting points. Hence, bicycle riders in Lund are forced to
      operate in much smaller units, or even solitarily. Great speed and
      bravery is nevertheless needed, as Lund's bicycle riders are well known
      for their suicidal attacks upon much larger four-wheeled vehicles.</p>

      <p>Normally I leave home and mount my bike ten past seven in the
      morning. That gives me ample time to patrol the area between my home and
      the railway station before I have to catch the 07.39 train from Lund to
      Copenhagen. That trip is uneventful, except for occasional encounters
      with an increasing number of power walking young ladies. The power
      walkers stride along in a frenzy, their eyes fixed on a point far
      way. Neither their faces nor their eyes reveal any emotion whatsoever.
      They don't seem to like walking. I think that they are all in a
      hurry home for a shower and a nice slow breakfast.</p>

      <p>I haven't yet seen any power walkers striding along H.C. Andersens
      Boulevard or elsewhere in central Copenhagen, but I reckon it is due to
      the successful operations of the bicycle riders.</p>

      <h2>A parking place</h2>

      <img src="http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/galleri/200907-200907/smaller/cimg1352.jpg" style="margin-left:0.5em;float:left;margin-right:0.5em;" alt="Secure locking is essential"/>

      <p>I have one serious problem. That is to find a secure parking place
      for my bike at the railway station. A lot of people who park there have
      lost their vehicles. There are stories about thieves coming there with
      lorries, bringing loads of bicycles for export to Poland. I've recently
      acquired a new bike, since my previous one was stolen. Apart from
      finding a parking place, the temporal bottle-neck is to lock the
      thing. I've got two really solid locks, and try to park where I can use
      one of them for locking the bike to the iron structure provided by the
      local council for the benefit for of paranoid bicycle owners (see the
      image).</p>

      <p>I've been told that bicycle theft is very common in Copenhagen. And
      that the shortage of parking places is a real problem as well, in
      particular around the Central Station. I take the bus, or walk carefully
      avoiding HC Andersen's Boulevard.</p>

      <h2>Two cultures</h2>

      <p>Swedes &amp; Danes are cousins. Both tribes are viking
      grandchildren. So are off course the Icelanders and Norwegians, but it
      is only the Icelanders who have kept their old language. The rest of us
      has diverged, but still there has been some force that has kept us
      together linguistically as well as culturally. I've been told that
      people from Algeria cannot talk to people from Egypt, in spite of the
      fact that they all speak Arabic. Now, I speak Swedish and my colleagues
      all speak Danish. And we can all laugh at a good joke.</p>

      <p>I won't say that language doesn't pose any problems, but none I can't
      live with. Collaborative writing is a problem, though. My Danish is a
      joke, like the speech of the Swedish chef in the Muppet
      show. Collaborative writing is worst, since that forces colleagues to
      translate my gibberish. I usually write documentation in English, and
      everything else in Swedish. Both will be understood.</p>

      <p>Many Danes think that Swedes are formal, moralistic and more prone to
      bureaucracy than Danes. This is because in Sweden everything that make
      life worth living, such as tobacco, alcohol and visiting prostitutes,
      are either prohibited, restricted or somehow controlled by the
      government. More recently, some Danes have been accusing us for being
      afflicted by some unhealthy psychological disorder making us inclined to
      deny any problems concerning immigration and integration. I cannot
      understand why; just wait a year and we will also have a solid racist
      representation in our parliament, as in Denmark.</p>

      <p>Many Swedes who have little personal experience of Denmark actually
      believe that everything that makes life worth-while is more free in
      Denmark and that it is a much more cosy place. All Swedish commuters
      I've talked to about the cultural differences between Danes and Swedes
      tell a story which is quite the opposite from the Danish self image. The
      amount of bureaucracy is less in Sweden and the Danish society is more
      hierarchical. On the other hand, I think it is true that we Swedes are a
      moralistic lot, at least when it comes to life in Denmark.</p>

      <p>One thing that surprises me is our ever ongoing discussions on
      responsibility. People here say "this is not our job" more often than in
      Sweden. Delegation of responsibilities is more widespread in Sweden than
      in Denmark. As a consequence leaders in Denmark are extremely busy. We
      also have an endless number of committees in Denmark, which I think is a
      surrogate for responsible people. That is, when no individual takes
      responsibility, it has to unwillingly be shared by committees.</p>

      <h2>A slightly more endless number of shorter meetings</h2>

      <p>When I started my work, the Danish meeting culture was a relief. In
      both countries there will be an agenda for a meeting. The difference is
      that in Denmark we allocate a fixed amount of time, and the meeting ends
      regardless whether we've been through the agenda or not. It felt as if I
      had finally escaped from the country of endless meetings. Indeed I
      had. I had come to the country of an endless number of meetings.</p>

      <p>When I think of it, the number of meetings seemed endless in Sweden
      too, but the number of meetings is more endless in Denmark.</p>

      <p>If the Vatican had been situated in Copenhagen, I doubt that they had
      ever been able to elect a new pope. The College of Cardinals would
      declare that the meeting is over before they reached that point on the
      agenda. It is, sometimes, an advantage to lock in committees and tell
      them that they'll get lunch when they completed their task.</p>

      <p>After seven hours and twenty-four minutes I'm free to return to my
      home country, half an hour for lunch included. In Sweden we work eight
      hours, and that excludes half an hour for lunch. And if you're in a
      meeting you'll almost certainly miss it anyway.</p>

      <h2>Then comes the afternoon</h2>

      <img src="http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/galleri/200907-200907/smaller/cimg1348.jpg" style="margin-left:0.5em;float:right;margin-right:0.5em;" alt="Secure locking is essential"/>

      <p>In the afternoon I take the train back home. I embark the train and
      sit there reading something, or possibly writing texts like this one. I
      sit there passively being transported. Then I disembark. All of a sudden
      I'm standing on a platform at Lund Central, having the strange feeling
      that I cannot recall what happened on the train. I cannot even recall
      what I thought about while on the train. This frightens me. "I Think
      Therefore I Exist", Descartes wrote. The central question for me in my
      life as a commuter is: Do I really exist while I'm on the train.</p>

      <p>Ordinary people exist twenty-four hours a day. It's a gift. Is this
      true for us commuters? I doubt that this is so. I suppose that we
      commuters live, on the average, as long as other people when the length
      of our lives is measured in years, but much less if we measure longevity
      in hours.</p>

      <p>When I return to my bike I usually find that some other bicycle
      riders have lent their bikes on mine, and usually artfully intertwined
      their handlebars with the wires of my handlebar gear and brake (see
      image). It is a nuisance, but I regard it as a helpful defense measure
      against bicycle theft. I thank my fellow bicycle riders and again unlock
      my two solid locks. I don't envy those who commute to Lund from
      elsewhere keeping a bike at Lund Central in order to save time --
      they'll arrive late to their meetings and miss their their lunches.</p>

      <p>In the evening I again patrol the area between Lund Central and my
      home. The trip is as uneventful as the one in the morning, but the power
      walking young ladies has been replaced by much older female dog owners,
      strolling leisurely through the city on their way towards the parks. I
      suppose power walkers don't like dogs.</p>
      
    </div>
  </content>
  <dc:date>2009</dc:date>
  <category label="essays" term="Essays"/>
  <published>2009-07-27T14:26:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2009-12-10T08:25:37+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/07/commuting/</id>
  <!-- $Id$ -->
</entry><entry xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>The predator rests on its prey</title>
  <link href="/entries/2009/07/victory/"/>
  <summary>I've seen this image before. An excavator has demolished a
  building, and has then proudly been parked on top of the remnants.</summary>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
      <div style="float: left;margin-left: 3px;margin-right:3px;">
	<img src="http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/galleri/200907-200907/smaller/cimg1345.jpg" alt="an excavator on top of a demolished building"/>
      </div>

      <p>Is this <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Smaug">Smaug</a>
      resting on a pile of gold? Or a predator resting after a victorius
      battle with a powerful prey?</p>

      <p>Obviously neither. But I've seen this image before. An excavator has
      demolished a building, and has then proudly been parked on top of the
      remnants. The building was a petrol station from the sixties. I'll not
      miss it; it was an ugly building. The shop inside it was
      poor. That's not the point.</p>

      <p> The point is just <strong>why this gesture of aggression</strong>?
      Why is the excavator always parked on top of the remnants? Is it a
      gesture of triumph? Has the present once again earned a victory over the
      past?  It is the choice of parking place which is the question.</p>

    </div>
  </content>
  <dc:date>2009</dc:date>
  <category label="essays" term="Essays"/>
  <updated>2009-07-13T10:46:29+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/07/victory/</id>
  <!--
      $Id$
  -->
</entry><entry xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>Will the research libraries play a role in e-science</title>
  <link href="/entries/2009/07/escience/"/>
  <summary>I was asked to participate in an e-science pilot project.  The work
  in the project has been food for thought for me. Will libraries be a part of
  a future eScience infrastructure?</summary>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
      
      <p>I was asked to participate in an e-science pilot project. The pilot
      is directed towards social science, and its main goal is to find out
      what we could do in the area. Should libraries play a role in a future
      eScience infrastructure? If yes, what could we do for our patrons in
      this area?</p>

      <p>That the answer should be yes to the first question is obvious for
      anyone responsible for the strategic development of any research library
      around the globe, but the second question is clearly more difficult to
      answer.</p>

      <p>Libraries have, traditionally, been occupied with four activities:
      They collect, preserve, organize and provide access to
      information. Indeed a <a href="http://www.google.com/search?hl=en&amp;q=collect+preserve+organize+%22provide+access%22&amp;btnG=Search">search</a>
      for these four terms in Google seem to yield a search very focussed on
      mission statements for Northern American research libraries. <em>It
      isn't farfetched to conclude that we could extend this role to include
      research data in digital form</em></p>

      <h2>A happy hypertextual symbiosis</h2>

      <p>In my vision, our role may not end here. The task should involve an
      infrastructure permitting the our existing information (published in the
      form of books, journals and whatever) live in a happy hypertextual
      symbiosis with the research data it is based on.</p>

      <p>In this ecosystem of data and models scientists should be able to
      combine old stuff in new ways just and continue building the human
      knowledge by submitting new data. Every piece of data need to be
      possible to address, for the purpose of annotation as well as for
      retrieval. Every piece of data, any point in a diagram need an
      identifier. And it has to be a URI.</p>

      <p>No single organization will be able to afford to build the
      infrastructure needed by any research community. The good news is that
      no single organization need to build it. The web of data, which has to
      be the eScience infrastructure, will almost certainly be the Worldwide
      web. Nothing less, nothing more.</p>

      <p>This is the vision of <a href="http://www.w3.org/DesignIssues/LinkedData.html">linked data</a>
      and the semantic web, rephrased in the context of scientific
      information.</p>

      <p>By tradition libraries are aimed for some local community. In
      particular, the are funded by some local authority for that
      purpose. Hence they build collections suitable for that community.
      This local focus is a problem when everything else is Worldwide.</p>


      <p>The idea of the web of data as a foundation for an eScience is a good
      idea, and most likely the only one that will work. Indeed it is so
      obvious ones that any actor within the business of scientific
      information are about to adopt it; publishers, learned societies and
      libraries alike. However there are others that are interested. Google
      eScience doesn't sound too exotic to me.</p>

      <p>Google eScience is not a threat, per se. The web of data need data
      feeds. We can provide that. The problem is our local scope, and in
      particular the focus on a local community. But that boils down to the
      local funding.</p>


    </div>
  </content>
  <dc:date>2009</dc:date>
  <category label="escience" term="eScience"/>
  <updated>2009-07-15T14:53:45+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/07/escience/</id>
</entry><entry xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>XML on the web, Client Side XSLT and Google</title>
  <link href="/entries/2009/07/client_side_xslt/"/>
  <summary>The market has forced the major browser manufacturers to converge
  on standards. But why are the search engines lagging behind? Browsers are
  capable of AJAX and advanced XML processing, but the search engines are
  still basically just removing tags and presenting raw text extracts.</summary>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

      <p>The market has forced the major browser manufacturers to converge on
      standards. Microsoft cannot afford to produce a browser that won't work
      on google apps, and the Linux based netbooks and netboxes make a
      difference. If <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Software_as_a_service">software is a
      service</a>, what is the client? Obviously the web client, the
      browser. But why are the search engines lagging behind?  Browsers are
      capable of AJAX and advanced XML processing, but the search engines are
      still basically just removing tags and presenting raw text extracts.</p>

      <p>I have quite a few documents on this site that are written in raw
      XML, such as the <a href="/2008/dighum/digital_humanities.xml">Digital
      Humanities Infrastructures</a> position paper from last year. Since it
      is about digital humanities and text encoding, I wrote it in <a href="http://www.tei-c.org/">TEI</a> XML. The paper is presented using
      client side XSLT. Just view source on that note, and you'll see my
      markup. The document is a blatant show-off; it is written in nerdcore
      vanity. At the top you'll see</p>

      <pre>
	&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?&gt;
	&lt;?xml-stylesheet href="render.xsl" type="text/xsl" ?&gt;
      </pre>

      <p>The <kbd>xml-stylesheet</kbd> processing instruction is read by your
      browsser, which then retrieves the stylesheet <a href="/2008/dighum/render.xsl">render.xsl</a>. Without any further ado
      it is then transformed into html, rendered using the CSS indicated by my
      XSLT script for you to read. You can even inspect the resulting html
      using <a href="http://getfirebug.com/">firebug</a>, if you've got a
      modern installation.</p>

      <h2>What does Google do when indexing XML?</h2>

      <p>There is almost certainly a range of XML formats that is actually
      interpreted by Google. Which formats, well we don't know but in practice
      can hardly expect anything more exotic than common syndication formats
      (such as RSS and ATOM ), <a href="http://google.com/support/webmasters/bin/answer.py?hl=en&amp;answer=99170">microformats
      and RDFa</a>. I have noticed that Google has been doing OAI harvesting
      for many years, most likely for the benefit of <a href="http://scholar.google.com/">Scholar</a>.</p>

      <p>One could envisage a number of viable indexing strategies for a
      general search engine for a document like my Digital Infrastructure
      Nerdcore Vanity paper. One would be to execute a global regex search and
      replace "&lt;[^&gt;]+&gt;" with "" (which basically means: remove
      anything between angle brackets, or remove all tags).</p>

      <p>This would yield a "detagged incipit", which in this case is "Digital
      Humanities Infrastructures 2008-06-12 Digital Humanities Infrastructures
      Sigfrid Lundberg"</p> 

      <p>Another strategy would be to use the style sheet provided by the nerd
      publishing this paper. That would yield the "transformed incipit", which
      for this document is (using the HTML body only) "Digital Humanities
      Infrastructures Sigfrid Lundberg". In using the transform, Google would
      then be able to use its usual HTML indexing techniques. For instance it
      would understand the title, and be able parse all hypertext links.</p>

      <p>I made the search <a href="http://www.google.com/search?hl=en&amp;q=digital+humanities+infrastructure+%2Blundberg&amp;btnG=Search">digital
      humanities infrastructure +lundberg</a> and the results looks like
      "<strong>Digital Humanities Infrastructures 2008-06-12 Digital
      Humanities ...</strong> - Jun 5 ... Digital Humanities Infrastructures
      Sigfrid Lundberg slu@kb.dk Digital .... Also McCarty's humanities
      computing research infrastructure (or rather ..."</p>

      <p>The machine is actually using a detagged incipit as the title, which
      is what I think it uses for PDF. This is very far from the ideas in
      <a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/grddl/">Gleaning Resource Descriptions
      from Dialects of Languages (GRDDL)</a> where providers of documents
      actually provide XSLT for the benefit of robots that could use that to
      extract descriptions in RDF.</p>

    </div>
  </content>
  <dc:date>2009</dc:date>
  <category label="structuralwebdesign" term="Structural web design"/>
  <updated>2009-07-11T21:51:48+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/07/client_side_xslt/</id>
</entry><entry xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>Wagging the long tail</title>
  <link href="/entries/2009/07/indexing_philosophy/"/>
  <summary>The problem with providing an OK Amazoogle experience is that we
  might fail in providing advanced services to patrons that have special
  needs.</summary>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

      <p>By and large we in the library world have, finally, accepted the
      reality. We do no longer regard the online catalogue's poor usability as
      an <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Information_literacy">information
      literacy problem</a>. As such, there was a remedy: User education. The
      roots of education are bitter, but the fruit is sweet. The path towards
      mastering the online catalogue is like a very long session in the
      gym. You feel better the day after tomorrow.</p>

      <p>After (rougly) 2003, there was a general acceptance that the our
      patrons deserved an easier to use interface, and the concept of the
      integrated library system was born. The <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_next-generation_catalogs">new
      kind of system</a> should be so easy to use that new generations used to
      <a href="http://orweblog.oclc.org/archives/000562.html">Amazoogle and
      Googlezon</a> should not be frustrated by the complications of the
      typical scanlists generated by the library opac upon the entering of a
      long and complicated query in <a href="http://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Common_Command_Language">CCL</a>.</p>

      <p>The user preferences have been known for a long time. For instance,
      all users of the <a href="http://www.tbray.org/ongoing/When/200x/2003/06/17/SearchUsers">Open
      Text search engine</a> used the simple form, except those that
      didn't. They used the advanced one, and they amounted to about 0.5% of
      the grand total. Such users belong to the tip of some <a href="http://www.thelongtail.com/">long tail</a>, and they do know what
      they want to know, but knowing that might not help if we cannot
      deliver.</p>

      <p>I heard a story from a librarian at The Royal Library. A student
      appeared at the information desk at one of our reading rooms requesting
      a list of contemporary Japanese literature translated into Danish for
      some paper in translation studies. Our nice ILS <a href="http://www.exlibrisgroup.com/category/PrimoOverview">Primo</a>
      provides an OK Amazoogle experience. But, well... An user hostile
      boolean fielded search in the rusty old OPAC did the job.</p>

      <p>The good news is that the advanced search form is much cheaper to
      build than simple one. That one is still the real challange. Even for
      Google.</p>

    </div>
  </content>
  <dc:date>2009</dc:date>
  <category label="opac" term="Library catalogues"/>
  <updated>2009-07-29T18:01:56+01:00</updated>
  <published>2009-07-29T08:49:23+01:00</published>
  <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/07/indexing_philosophy/</id>
  <!-- $Id$ -->
</entry><entry xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>About this site</title>
  <link href="/entries/2009/07/colophon/"/>
  <summary>I'm a terrible nerd. To use software like content management
  systems or blog software is unthinkable for me. There are many ways to build
  a site like this. I have chosen one that maximizes the use of angle
  brackets.</summary>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

      <p>I'm a terrible nerd. To use software like content management systems
      or blog software for building my web site is unthinkable for me.</p>

      <p>I have a substantial collection of old stuff written for various
      purposes in very different formats; it is a must to be able to integrate
      that material into the site. Some of this material are hard-core XML
      documents in text encoding initiative or docbook XML. There are also
      documents in legacy formats, such as RTF and (GNU) troff. I'm still
      using troff for production of new texts, usually via transform from XML
      using XSLT. The more recent XML documents are using client side XSLT for
      viewing.</p>

      <p>This material is growing. I see it as an extension of my CV, but some
      of it could be interesting for users since it is general documentation
      for how to solve certain kinds of problems. I also wanted to seemlessly
      integrate other, more lightweight, material. Like this article</p>

      <h3>Requirements</h3>

      <p>As I mentioned <a href="/entries/2009/06/why/">the other day</a>, I
      wanted a new navigation system. There are two requirements on that: (i)
      it should be easy to follow for users and (ii) the pages in it should be
      good landing pages for search engines. I felt that there was a need for
      more text that would generate hits in search engines without out being
      irrelevant for users and misrepresent the content. Finally I wanted the
      site to be somewhat like a blog. In spite of the improved look and feel
      I also wanted that all the material already published on the site should
      retain the current URIs.</p>

      <p>The old site was just plain files, I did no scripting whatsoever on
      that site. I couldn't, however, possibly manage a navigation system a
      manually, so some scripting had to be involved in generating the
      site.</p>

      <h3>Metadata and XML processing</h3>

      <p>To generate the navigation system, I have catalog all existing
      'static' material. In particular I had to index manually using keywords
      or "tags". I decided what material to include and wrote manually a
      single monolithic metadata file in XML using using <a href="/entries/2009/06/atom/">the atom syndication format</a>.</p>

      <p>Having this file it was easy to write a xslt tranform that generated
      the browse by year and subject menues appearing in the left column on
      most pages (that took 61 lines). Then there is another xslt transform
      aggregating the title, summary and link data into menus, such as the one
      in <a href="/subjects/xmlprocessing/">XML processing</a>. This took
      about 200 lines of xslt.</p>

      <p>Now, these two xslt scripts take into account only the older kind of
      static material. I also wanted a new kind of bloggish 'dynamic'
      material. I needed to integrate the two kinds of material in a single
      structure. Just as I wrote the metadata for the older set of material in
      Atom feed document, I write the bloggish kind of stuff in Atom entry
      documents. They live in a file system <kbd>/entries</kbd> under the
      document root.</p>

      <p>To integrate the two I have a nifty little perl script that does two
      things. It reads the Atom feed for the and parses it into a Document
      Object Model (DOM) object. Then it traverses the <kbd>/entries</kbd>
      file system, parses each entry. First it drops a transform into html of
      each entry. The entry itself is entered into the global DOM, which is
      finally printed into a complete Atom feed. This took 65 lines of perl
      and 84 lines of xslt.</p>

      <p>To get a blog style home page I had to sort the entire set inversely
      in temporal order, print the most recent entry on the home page and
      finally print a few pointers to more recent entries. These tasks took
      another 250 lines of xslt. In addition I have a utility which generates
      the <kbd>/entries</kbd> directories and prints a skeleton entry, which
      generates another 100 lines of perl which generates the skeleton using
      XML DOM.</p>

      <p>It takes less than a second to rebuild the entire site. Before the
      refurbishment, I used to copy all files to my server. In order to
      implement incremental update, I've created a CVS repository on my
      server. Now I check in everything using CVS after building and testing,
      and then I publish my stuff by checking out in the servers document
      root. This will scale up to a some thousand blog entries. Then I'll
      ingest my entries in Oracle Berkeley DB XML and replace most xslt with
      XML Query.</p>

      <p>Or I'll do that anyway, for the fun of it.</p>

    </div>
  </content>
  <dc:date>2009</dc:date>
  <category label="structuralwebdesign" term="Structural web design"/>
  <category label="colophon" term="Colophon"/>
  <updated>2009-07-06T18:16:27+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/07/colophon/</id>
</entry><entry xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>OpenSearch, RSS and OPML as XML Webservices for information
  retrieval</title>
  <link href="/entries/2009/07/opml/"/>
  <summary>At the Royal Library we have been working with the building of an
  infrastructure for publishing of digitized material. It is collections of
  digital images, usually with very little textual content to go with it. It
  is quite a challenge to build workflows satisfying the needs of technical
  staff running the scanners, the librararian and editorial staff doing the
  cataloging and the needs for crosswalking metadata from the OPAC and at the
  same time be able to syndicate the material in other services adhering to
  different standards.</summary>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

      <p>At the <a href="http://www.kb.dk/">Royal Library</a> we have been
      working with the building of an infrastructure for publishing of
      digitized material. It is collections of digital images, usually with
      very little textual content to go with it.</p>

      <p>The cataloging of the images has been made by library staff using the
      image database system Cumulus from <a href="http://www.canto.com/">Canto</a>.  Cumulus is designed as digital
      asset management system for people within graphical industry. Canto is
      producing an advanced Web user interface, but it is rather poor as
      regards dissemination of the collections on the web. For example, images
      published that way never ever appear in Google Images. Syndication of
      our content has not been possible, since the system have been lacking
      any concept of standardized metadata, which is essential for all
      collaboration between institutions in the library communities.</p>

    
      <div style="float: left;margin-left:5px;margin-right:5px;">
	<div style="height:350px;width:300px;">
	  <a href="http://static.grazr.com/gzpanel.html?view=s&amp;file=http://www.kb.dk/opml_category_service/danmarksbilleder/?opml_mode=shallow&amp;subject=8">
	    <img alt="Grazr" src="http://static.grazr.com/images/grazrbadge.png" style="border:none"/>
	  </a>
	  <script defer="defer" type="text/javascript" src="http://static.grazr.com/gzloader.js?view=s&amp;file=http://www.kb.dk/opml_category_service/danmarksbilleder/?opml_mode=shallow&amp;subject=8">
	  </script>
	</div>
      </div>

      <p>To take advantage of the relative ease of use for the people handling
      the images, but still be able to provide access to our collections on
      the Internet we have an entirely new web interface. For performace
      reasons, we decided that it should <em>not</em> access the cumulus
      database directly, but a mirror in our Oracle DB. Furthermore we wanted
      a REST XML web service layer.</p>

      <p>The latter goal was achieved by using two syndication services, built
      on top of Oracle. The two services were written as JAVA servlets, and
      supported Outline Processor Markup Language (<a href="http://web.archive.org/web/20071019150004/http://opml.org/">OPML</a>) and <a href="http://www.opensearch.org">OpenSearch</a>, together with RSS. The
      rationale for the latter choice of standard was that we wanted
      mainstream Internet Standards rather than typical library standards such
      as <a href="http://www.loc.gov/standards/sru/">SRU</a>. OpenSearch is
      promoted by <a href="http://a9.com">A9</a>, a subsidiary of <a href="http://www.amazon.com">Amazon</a> and there are at least pledges
      of support from other big players such as Google and Yahoo.</p>

      <p>OPML was not an as obvious choice. However, OpenSearch is basically a
      Syndication protocol and as such OPML is a candidate since its most
      common usage is to provide subject structured access to feeds. An early
      version of the system is available on our web site, the first version
      was released for about a year ago. Our technology choices makes it
      stright forward to syndicate the content. The gadget on this page is an
      example of this. It is a gadget showing the OPML and RSS from the first
      collection of images released in this way, <a href="http://www.kb.dk/images/billed/2008/maj/danmarksbilleder/">Danmarksbilleder</a>,
      a collection of historical images from a few Danish cities. The widget
      itself is "The Original Feed Widget" a nifty thing coming from <a href="http://grazr.com">grazr.com</a>. You can make one of your own by
      filling in the URI <a href="http://www.kb.dk/opml_category_service/danmarksbilleder/?opml_mode=shallow&amp;subject=8">http://www.kb.dk/opml_category_service/danmarksbilleder/?opml_mode=shallow&amp;subject=8</a>
      in the form on grazr.com.</p>

      <p>The use of truly simple de facto Internet standards is one
      advantage. But we needed a way to build traditional web contents on top
      of our two web services. Sites as <a href="http://www.kb.dk/images/billed/2008/maj/danmarksbilleder/">Danmarksbilleder</a>
      mentioned above, and its "cousins" <a href="http://www.kb.dk/images/billed/2008/sep/kistebilleder/">Kistebilleder</a>,
      <a href="http://www.kb.dk/images/billed/2008/sep/daellsvarehus/">Daells
      varehus</a> and <a href="http://www.kb.dk/images/billed/2008/sep/partiprogrammer/">Partiprogrammer</a>. All
      these are actually delivered by one single servlet, which is most
      appropriately described as a mashup-engine.</p>

      <p>The engine is written in-house, and supports multiple skins (as seen
      in the examples above -- <a href="http://www.kb.dk/images/billed/2008/maj/danmarksbilleder/">Danmarksbilleder</a> differs from <a href="http://www.kb.dk/images/billed/2008/sep/kistebilleder/">Kistebilleder</a>).</p>

      <p>In this application a skin is a XML document, which consists of the
      lay-out for the html page (it is little more than the HTML). Appart from
      html tags it also contain &lt;kb:include/&gt; tags identified by they id
      attribute. Each kb:include tag corresponds to a REST XML web service and
      is connected to a XSLT script via configuration file. The mashup engine
      reads the skin at initialization, and upon a request it retrieves the
      required OPML or RSS, transforms the content, pastes these fragments
      into the skin DOM tree and finally delivers the content to the
      client.</p>

      <p>The mashup engine is not very well written. I can do better. Also the
      current set of services requires an Oracle schema per collection
      disseminated which is wasteful. We've haven't got the time yet to fix
      the first problem, but the second problem is about to be solved since we
      have a second generation of web services in the pipe-line for release
      real soon. In this application we've just one single Oracle database for
      all editions served. I will give you a report on that one when it is
      online.</p>


    </div>
  </content>
  <dc:date>2009</dc:date>
  <category label="xmlprocessing" term="XML processing"/>
  <category label="colophon" term="Colophon"/>
  <updated>2009-07-09T18:44:44+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/07/opml/</id>
</entry><entry xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>What does Free mean for The Library</title>
  <link href="/entries/2009/07/blogging/"/>
  <summary>Blogging is out, and the new trend is to tweet in
  Twitters. Syndication is out as well, since Google steals your content and
  you cannot make money on journalism. How can we survive when all media are
  free?</summary>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

      <p>Chris Anderson's book has finally appeared. The new one,
      <em>Free</em>, much discussed already before it was printed, and, off
      course, much hyped in the <a href="http://www.wired.com">Wired
      magazine</a>. I've just ordered it from Amazon, but I've been walking
      around thinking about Internet business models, open access and the
      like. I've also <a href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/2004/biblioteket/">written at length
      about this</a> (in Swedish, I'm afraid).</p>

      <p>How is <em>Free</em> related to the situation for <em>The
      Library</em>?  Well...  I'd say: in just about any way you may
      imagine. However, let me start at an entirely different angle. Blog and
      Wiki software were at the time the first easy ways to really take
      advantage of the new medium based on hypertext, a simple protocol and a
      global network.  Through additions such as syndication and pings
      (notifications that new content have appeared) and automatic
      cross-linking (based on pings) to enable discussions across blogs, it
      goes beyond hypertext.</p>

      <h2>Built for interaction and transactions</h2>

      <p>This gave us basically a new medium built for transaction and human
      interaction.</p>

      <p>When a blog really takes off, the traffic generated is enough for
      letting the ads pay your rent and buy milk for your kids. Obviously some
      quality is required or it won't take off in the first place. (Quality
      which is in the eye of the beholder). Content which is hard to get
      elsewhere. That is what gives the attention needed for the transactions
      to take place.</p>

      <p>Blogging is cheap. You write about what's around you that you
      know. You benefit from from the transaction and attention economy which
      feeds the Internet. Syndication, aggregation and harvesting will move
      you're content around, and you'll mostly benefit from it.</p>

      <h2>Syndication, harvesting and leeches</h2>

      <p>On the other hand, much of the user's navigation will take place
      elsewhere, and many user's will not be exposed to your ads but Google's.
      This lead to Jakob Nielsen's out-cry where he labelled them as <a href="http://www.useit.com/alertbox/search_engines.html">leeches</a>
      already a few years ago.</p>

      <p><a href="http://www.nybooks.com/authors/71">Michael Massing</a>
      discusses this and other issues in a <a href="http://www.nybooks.com/articles/22960">recent article</a> in The
      New York Review of Books. He quotes David Simon's statement in a
      testimony in front of the US Senate:</p>
      
      <blockquote>[Internet] <em>leeches... reporting from mainstream news
      publications, whereupon aggregating web-sites and bloggers contribute
      little more than repetition, commentary and froth. Meanwhile, readers
      acquire news from the aggregators and abandon its point of origin—namely
      the newspapers themselves. In short, the parasite is slowly killing the
      host.</em></blockquote>

      <p>There is a problem deep in this statement. It assumes that there
      would be no news without the traditional media. Since the traditional
      media are on the decline, We can be almost certain that this is not the
      case. Massing continues:</p>

      <blockquote>... <em>such statements seem as outdated as they are
      defensive. Over the past few months alone, a remarkable amount of
      original, exciting, and creative (if also chaotic and maddening)
      material has appeared on the Internet. The practice of journalism, far
      from being leeched by the Web, is being reinvented there, with a variety
      of fascinating experiments in the gathering, presentation, and delivery
      of news. And unless the editors and executives at our top papers begin
      to take note, they will hasten their own demise.</em></blockquote>

      <p>Do we really need these big media institutions? What use do we have
      for Reuters, CNN, AFP etc. They are good to have, but I'd say we could
      do without them. For example, the notion that we cannot get proper
      information from distant places without having expensive foreign
      correspondents travelling there seems extremely arrogant to me, on the
      verge of being racist.</p>

      <h2>Adaption and struggle for existence</h2>

      <p>This is not to say that we don't need journalism. Indeed we do. But
      as Massing states, it is currently reinventing itself on the Internet. A
      new one which has adapted itself to the medium. One which is part of the
      transaction &amp; interaction based technology and economy.</p>

      <p>Now, let us return to <em>The Library</em>.</p>

      <p>The business model <em>The Library</em> is based upon is the idea
      that it will save money to share media. It started with scholars sharing
      papyrus scrolls two thousand years ago. Continued with libraries within
      monastic societies during the middle age, where books were extremely
      valuable assets. Then, today, we're licensing electronic material which
      is meant to save money as an alternative to pay per view.</p>

      <p>Those who invented <em>The Library</em> had clearly in mind
      collections of stuff that were not <em>Free</em>. Stuff that are scarce
      and only legal to copy for fair use. Produced by organizations that
      think that Google is stealing their content.</p>

      <p>In Chris Anderson's world, and in Google's, the value of information
      is declining. Material which is <em>Free</em> or open access have the
      price corresponding to a zero marginal cost of producing one additional
      copy.</p>

      <p>Who will fund each University library's fumbling and overlapping
      attempts to collect, preserve, organize and provide access to virtually
      the same digital resources through very similar integrated library
      systems? And do these resources belong at <em>The Library</em> at all if
      they are <em>Free</em>?</p>

      <p>I leave these questions as an exercise to the reader (hint: think
      about the economics of blogging). And end this by quoting Google CEO <a href="http://www.wired.co.uk/wired-magazine/archive/2009/08/features/the-unstoppable-google.aspx">Eric Schmidt</a></p>

      <blockquote>
	<em>“We don’t have a big picture. We don’t have a five-year plan, we
	don’t have a two-year plan, we don’t have a one-year plan. We have a
	mission and a strategy, and the mission is… you know, [to organise]
	all the world’s information. And the strategy is to do it through
	innovation. It doesn’t bother us if something doesn’t work. Because we
	understand that something else will work.”</em>
      </blockquote>

    </div>
  </content>
  <dc:date>2009</dc:date>
  <category label="media" term="Media"/>
  <category label="thelibrary" term="The Library"/>
  <category label="internet" term="Internet"/>
  <updated>2009-08-03T17:57:08+01:00</updated>
  <published>2009-07-31T07:48:53+01:00</published>
  <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/07/blogging/</id>
  <!-- $Id$ -->
</entry><entry xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>The description and encoding of structure</title>
  <link href="/entries/2009/07/structure/"/>
  <summary>Much metadata is fairly stright forward. A book does have a title
  and an author. That's usually no big deal. We've been able to handle that
  for centuries. A digital book has chapters, and everything you might want to
  know may be in chapter two on page seventyfive. Or someone may tell you the
  solution to your problems after a quarter of an hour in some video on
  YouTube. Now, how do we cope with this?</summary>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

      <p>Many things in life can best be represented as trees. Indeed, life
      itself is a tree of various life forms. We have the animal and plant
      kingdoms, and these main categories are further sub-divided into phylae,
      classes, genera. The animal kingdom is divided into invertebrates and
      vertebrates. The latter include amphibians, reptiles, birds and
      mammals. Human knowledge is also depicted as a tree.</p>

      <p>A lot of other things are trees. Hence, philosophers, mathematicins
      and computer scientists have put quite an effort into the modelling
      stuff as trees. Within library &amp; information science we have used
      the term classification systems for centuries, I suppose, and more
      recently we have started to talk about ontologies and knowledge
      organization. There are a lot of theory and a plethora of standards in
      this area. Systems like <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Topic_Maps">topic maps</a> (see also
      <a href="http://www.topicmaps.org/">topicmaps.org</a>) and more recently
      Simple Knowledge Organization System <a href="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/">SKOS</a>) are available for those
      who need a standard for knowledge organization.</p>

      <p>On a very down to earth level, I tend to think of controlled
      vocabularies as filters and navigators. The latter are trees and may
      contain many terms arranged into a tree of arbitrary depth. The filters
      are lists of controlled terms, which may be whereabout in the tree we
      are. Think of Yahoo Directory. You can browse into <a href="http://dir.yahoo.com/Regional/Countries/Italy/Regions/Tuscany/">Tuscany</a>
      and get a very long list of resources. Then there is a menu at the top
      where you can choose between "Business and Shopping", "Entertainment and
      Arts", "Recreation and Sports", "Travel and Transportation" and so
      forth. These are broader categorizations that apply to Firenze as well
      as Siena or New York city or any place you may want to visit. We in the
      Web business call them <em>filters</em> or <em>facets</em>.</p>

      <h2>Recognizing and recalling</h2>

      <p>From a user perspective, you have to take into account that there are
      two cognitive processes involved when using services which like Yahoo
      Directory employ navigators and filters. The first process is more
      fundamental, and is by nurture and possibly nature a part of the human
      mind: This is to say: Ah Tuscany, that is a part of Italy, isn't
      it. It's like distinguishing between a wasp and a bumble bee. On an
      evolutionary time-scale we've benefitted from being able to say, this is
      edible this is not, or this one has a sting and is likely to use
      it. This is to recognize something when you see it.</p>

      <p>The opposite is a much more difficult cognitive process: I want to
      know something about Tuscany: Ok, I then start by clicking on Italy. You
      have to connect Italy with Tuscany, not only recognize the word Tuscany
      when you see it. This makes it more difficult to find Tuscany given
      Italy than Italy given Tuscany (in Yahoo it's in the bread crumb
      path). Remembering might not be trivial. To know in advance things like
      "frogs are amphibians" and that "diabetes is an endocrinological
      disorder". On the other hand, to perform successful searching in Google
      is even more demanding, in spite of google suggest and spell checking
      tools that have improved the search comfort for many users.</p>

      <h2>Ordered Hierarchies of Content Objects</h2>

      <p>There are structures that are inside a resource, and that require
      navigation as well. As a first approximation we can assume that all
      digital resources, such as electronic books, are trees as well. In the
      theory of text this model is called OHCO (ordered hierarchy of content
      objects). That view has been questioned, and it is for instance claimed
      that any ordinary text consists of many, <a href="http://www.stg.brown.edu/resources/stg/monographs/ohco.html">overlapping
      hierarchies</a>. I just love overlapping hierarchies. They are great
      fun.</p>

      <p>Anyway, if you search the scientific literature on the theory of
      text, you'll find everything you want to know about post-structuralistic
      deconstruction of the OHCO model. Theoretically, I can understand the
      problems. But for me they are purely academical.</p>

      <p>If you instead search Google books for some real content, <a href="http://books.google.com/books?spell=1&amp;q=nightingale+lark+balcony&amp;as_brr=1">nightingale
      lark balcony</a> you'll find Romeo &amp; Juliet in her bed room. Scene V
      in Act III of Romeo and Juliet, on page <a href="http://books.google.com/books?id=09qTVKsjwSwC&amp;lpg=PA190&amp;dq=nightingale%20lark%20balcony&amp;as_brr=1&amp;pg=PA189">189</a>,

      <a href="http://books.google.com/books?id=H_EjAAAAMAAJ&amp;dq=nightingale%20lark%20balcony&amp;as_brr=1&amp;pg=PA160">160</a>
      and a lot of other page numbers, dependent on which edition. In the
      world according to me, you may have a lot of hierarchies and they may
      overlap, and OHCO may be false. But if you want to be able to address
      content in a more clever way than the one chosen by Google books, then
      you cannot do without a content model that looks like, well, very much
      like a tree.</p>

    </div>
  </content>
  <dc:date>2009</dc:date>
  <category label="structuralwebdesign" term="Structural web design"/>
  <category label="metadata" term="Metadata"/>
  <updated>2009-07-21T17:10:49+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/07/structure/</id>
  <!-- $Id$ -->
</entry><entry xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>The specification and the TODO-list</title>
  <link href="/entries/2009/10/programming/"/>
  <summary>Through the web, a software vendor and a service provider could all
  of a sudden compete on the same market. The software vendor use the
  traditional specification, but a service implies software which is in
  continuous development. Strictly speaking, there are no projects anymore,
  just different activities. No specifications anymore, but TODO lists
  containing incidents, bugs and requests for features ranked by
  importance.</summary>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

      <p>People within any profession or trade should continuously be involved
      in discussions of quality. I describe my profession as <em>web
      developer</em> and my trade as <em>digital libraries</em>. These areas
      are no exception.</p>

      <p>Like many web developers I spend a better part of my day on coding
      and other activities related to software development. But so do people
      involved in non-linear oscillation simulators. The web is an
      <em>application area</em>, but like non-linear systems it is also an
      area of research on its own right, and so is digital library
      research.</p>

      <p>There is more to digital libraries than just software
      development. There are all research concerning resource description, and
      how it relates to usability. There are also extensive standardization
      work going on. Now, how much digital library knowledge would a
      programmer need to know in order to build a good service?</p>

      <h2>The specification and the TODO-list</h2>

      <p>In theory nothing. If the specification is good enough, then the
      product should be good enough and this could, again in theory, ensured
      by unit tests.</p>

      <p>The problems here are, first, the quality of the specification, and,
      secondly, the <a href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/11/twocultures/">Two
      Cultures</a> (developers and editorial staff do not always understand
      each other).  The two problems are related to each other.</p>

      <p>The specification is a part of the agreement between the programmer
      and his or her customer. The work is completed when everything in the
      spec is in place. Programmer's need to know when they can send the
      bill.</p>

      <p>We who write software, we're a kind of mathematical people. We will
      feel secure if we know that the axioms are in place, that the theorems
      are there as well, and that the deductions are correct.</p>

      <p>For instance, if a piece of software is intended to assist an
      aircraft both at take-off and landing, then the specification should say
      so. Even if we thus kind of state the obvious, or if could imagine that
      there is no space in the sky for all planes that wouldn't be able to
      land.</p>

      <h2>The web and software as services</h2>

      <p>The web changed this. Not entirely but to a very large
      extent. There's a fundamental difference between being a vendor and
      being a service provider. The service provider try to get more users all
      the time which calls for continuous development.</p>

      <p>Through the web, a software vendor and a service provider could all
      of a sudden compete on the same market. The software vendor use the
      traditional specification, but a service implies software which is in
      continuous development. Strictly speaking, there are no projects
      anymore, just different activities. No specifications anymore, but TODO
      lists containing incidents, bugs and requests for features ranked by
      importance.</p>

      <p>And there is a continuous need for innovation.</p>


    </div>
  </content>
  <dc:date>2009</dc:date>
  <category label="programming" term="Programming"/>
  <updated>2009-11-01T15:39:44+01:00</updated>
  <published>2009-10-28T08:19:08+01:00</published>
  <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/10/programming/</id>
  <!-- $Id$ -->
</entry><entry xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>Aggravated autumn depression</title>
  <link href="/entries/2009/10/nicotine/"/>
  <summary>I've felt miserable for a month, at least. Here is the
  explanation...</summary>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

      <p>The last few weeks I've not felt as good as I used to. As a matter of
      fact I've been really miserable.</p>

      <p>It started in August. You see, when I am about to complete any
      substantial <a href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/07/opml/">piece of
      work or project</a>, I looked forward to the delivery with certain level
      of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Separation_anxiety_disorder">separation
      anxiety</a>. And then, after all deliverables are completed and a new
      <a href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/08/opensearch/">service
      is in place</a>, I get a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Postpartum_depression">postpartum
      depression</a>.</p>

      <p>This autumn all this was aggravated by severe <a href="http://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000953.htm">nicotine
      withdrawal</a> symptoms. I'd say, don't even try giving up <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SA7ljAYX6kE">wet snuff</a>, unless
      you've prepared yourself for a passage through hell.</p>


    </div>
  </content>
  <dc:date>2009</dc:date>
  <category label="aboutme" term="About me"/>
  <updated>2009-10-15T07:56:59+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/10/nicotine/</id>
</entry><entry xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>What about the HECS platforms?</title>
  <link href="/entries/2009/10/webdevelopment/"/>
  <summary>I've used fortran, pascal, C, perl, php and java in addition to
  more specialized tools such as SQL and XSLT. There is currently a lot of
  discussions on what platform will be the next winner.</summary>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

      <p>Anyone who has stayed in the same business for some years, have seen
      the recurrent changes in fashion. You'll also experience how people try
      to sell you the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Little_black_dress">little black
      dress</a> as something new. People invent a lot of things. Some of them
      are not that innovative. Some ideas required further development before
      they could take off. Some ideas were right, but the time wasn't.</p>

      <p>The <a href="http://www.tbray.org/ongoing/When/200x/2009/10/14/OOW-Take-aways#p-2">legacy</a>
      is something that is accumululating behind you. What someone (usually
      someone else) acquired or developed. You don't like the legacy, in
      particular not its documentation, but you have to maintain it.</p>

      <p>Once upon a time just about every script on the internet was written
      in the PERL programming language. Then just about every introductory
      programming course choose java as the prime example of an OO
      language. Just about any project should have some object oriented
      modelling, and J2EE was the name of the game. There were noone available
      for the legacy.</p>

      <h2>The HECS platforms</h2>

      <p>Then things happen again. PHP had been there all along. Many of the
      largest sites hade been using it for years for front-end work. The
      back-end could be written in JAVA but C, C++, perl and python are
      used. For newer sites there are languages like <a href="http://haskell.org/">Haskell</a> and <a href="http://erlang.org/">Erlang</a>, H and E in HECS. The remaining
      characters are C as in <a href="http://clojure.org/">Clojure</a> and S
      for <a href="http://www.scala-lang.org/">Scala</a></p>

      <p>Mankind is stratified into those who are early adopters and those
      that are more hesitant. Some of the early adopters buy the little black
      dress over and over again. In a sense I belong to the hesitant ones;
      novelty per se does not add to my interest. On the other hand I can get
      very enthusiastic to learn about ideas and technologies that I find
      elegant and new <em>to me</em>. One such idea, which is a true design
      classic, is functional programming. It isn't strictly speaking new to
      me. I've studied the Scheme programming language, and I'm using
      XSLT and Xquery.</p>

      <p>I'm very impressed by the elegance of the Haskell programming
      language, and the community that has been built around it. <a href="http://hackage.haskell.org/">Hackage</a> is Haskell's answer to
      PERL's <a href="http://cpan.org/">cpan</a>, PHP's <a href="http://pear.php.net/">PEAR</a> and Python's <a href="http://pypi.python.org/pypi">pypi</a>. The Haskell developers
      seems to be most advanced when it comes to building an open-source
      community. I do believe that Erlang is the platform which has the best
      track record; it has been used in Ericsson's Open Telecom Platform, for
      building ATM switches, <a href="http://couchdb.apache.org/">couchDB</a>
      -- a modern cloud computing classic.</p>

      <p>Still, I'm going for Haskell. I want a language which isn't using any
      virtual machine. The <a href="http://www.haskell.org/haskellwiki/Referential_transparency">referential
      transparency</a> (purity) is just a wonderful idea. I want something
      really new and elegant, such as a little black dress.</p>


    </div>
  </content>
  <dc:date>2009</dc:date>
  <category label="programming" term="Programming"/>
  <updated>2009-10-17T17:50:56+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/10/webdevelopment/</id>
</entry><entry xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>The two Cultures</title>
  <link href="/entries/2009/11/twocultures/"/>
  <summary>Do you know the second law of thermodynamics?</summary>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

      <p> C.P. Snow quoted G.H. Hardy</p>

      <blockquote style="font-style:italic;font-size:98%;">
	<p>“I remember G. H. Hardy once remarking to me in mild puzzlement,
	some time in the 1930s, Have you noticed how the word "intellectual"
	is used nowadays? There seems to be a new definition which certainly
	doesn't include Rutherford or Eddington or Dirac or Adrian or me? It
	does seem rather odd, don't y'know. (<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Two_Cultures#C._P._Snow_quotations">C. P. Snow</a>)”</p>
      </blockquote>

      <p>in his book <em>The Two Cultures</em>. Another one:</p>

      <blockquote style="font-style:italic;font-size:98%;">
	<p>“A good many times I have been present at gatherings of people who,
	by the standards of the traditional culture, are thought highly
	educated and who have with considerable gusto been expressing their
	incredulity at the illiteracy of scientists.”</p>

	<p>“Once or twice I have been provoked and have asked the company how
	many of them could describe the Second Law of Thermodynamics. The
	response was cold: it was also negative.”</p>

	<p>“Yet I was asking something which is the scientific equivalent of:
	Have you read a work of Shakespeare’s?”</p>
      </blockquote>

      <p>C.P. Snows book appeared <a href="http://tech.mit.edu/V129/N26/shu.html">fifty years</a> ago. I've
      studied science and technology for a better part of my life, and I've no
      idea how many times I've got remarks like “that's a technical
      detail.” It has happened this year.</p>

      <p>Do you know what a markup language is? You may, or may not know the
      answer, but I suppose it's still more important to read Shakespeare if
      you're to be regarded as an educated person.</p>

      <p>I do know the laws of thermodynamics, and I've read more than one
      work by Shakespeare. However, we software developers usually don't write
      like <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shakespeare_(programming_language)">Shakespeare</a>. We
      may be good hackers anyway.</p>


    </div>
  </content>
  <dc:date>2009</dc:date>
  <category label="programming" term="Programming"/>
  <updated>2009-11-01T15:31:26+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/11/twocultures/</id>
  <!-- $Id$ -->
</entry><entry xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>Fifteen polar bears and one architecture</title>
  <link href="/entries/2009/11/kbmetadta/"/>
  <summary>Today I gave a presentation on our metadata work. My experience of
  that turned out to be about images.</summary>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

      <p>Today I gave a presentation on our metadata work. It was meant to be
      about METS and MODS, but it became more of a justification for our work
      than about. As usual I had <a href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/2009/nov30/presentation.xml">too many
      slides</a>. My main idea was to use google images instead of slides, but
      then I had to add some slides anyway because the navigation overhead was
      too high and I had difficulties to remember which images to click on.</p>

      <p>The google searches are interesting. The visual result sets give you
      an overview very different from the text search. The visual search
      engines (see, for example <a href="http://www.search-cube.com/">Search
      Cube</a>) base their navigation on some kind of canned screen dumps.
      That's nice but it isn't the images produced by the author, but an image
      of the text.</p>

      <p>Please find below an annotated list of links to searches I like:</p>

      <div style="float: left; width: 50%; margin-left:0.5em;margin-right:0.5em;">
	<a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/webarch/" title="Architecture of the worldwide web"><img src="http://www.w3.org/2001/tag/2004/webarch-20041021/uri-res-rep.png" width="90%" border="0" alt="URI &amp; representations &amp; resources"/></a>
	<p><small>Figure 1</small></p>

      </div>

      <h2><a href="http://images.google.com/images?gbv=2&amp;hl=en&amp;um=1&amp;sa=1&amp;q=architecture+of+the+worldwide+web&amp;aq=f&amp;oq=&amp;aqi=&amp;start=0">Architecture of the worldwide web</a></h2>

      <p>First hit is Figure 1, from <a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/webarch/">the appropriate W3
      recommendation</a>. Then there are fifteen polar bears belonging to the
      cover of <q>Information Architecture for the World Wide Web</q>, a title
      that I think I should read when I get the opportunity.</p>

      <h2><a href="http://images.google.com/images?gbv=2&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=1&amp;q=library+catalog&amp;aq=f&amp;oq=&amp;aqi=g1&amp;start=0">Library
      catalog</a></h2>

      <p>This one isn't as spectacular as the architecture, but it
      gives you an idea on what people know and believe they know when it
      comes to what libraries and cataloging is about.</p>

      <div style="float: right; width: 50%; margin-left:0.5em;margin-right:0.5em;">
	<a href="http://www.library.nd.edu/daiad/morgan/musings/ngc/" title="Eric Lease Morgan's musings on next generation catalog">
	  <img src="http://www.library.nd.edu/daiad/morgan/musings/ngc/ngo.gif" width="100%" border="0" alt="Eric Lease Morgan's musings on next generation catalog"/>
	  </a>
	  <p><small>Figure 2. Eric Lease Morgan's musing on the Next
	  Generation Opac</small></p>

      </div>

      <p>There is a wonderful image (Figure 2) showing what we were all
      thinking about around 2006. When I think of it, we still are. The range
      of protocols to support, and the list of metadata formats are the
      same. The ideas doesn't change that fast.</p>

      <h2><a href="http://images.google.com/images?gbv=2&amp;hl=en&amp;q=circulation+desk&amp;sa=N&amp;start=0&amp;ndsp=20">Circulation desk</a></h2>

      <p>All libraries I know have a circulation desk. Searching for it in
      Google images yields 978000 hits. Adding quotation marks reduces the
      number to 34400. None of them are particularly interesting, except
      perhaps the one at <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/army_arch/2691906687/">Doheny
      Library</a>.</p>

      <p>My fascination is more due to fact that they are all there, all these
      desks. I mean, how interesting is a circulation desk?</p>

      <div style="float: right; width: 50%; margin-left:0.5em;margin-right:0.5em;">
	<a href="http://library.web.cern.ch/library/Webzine/10/papers/1/">
	  <img src="http://library.web.cern.ch/library/Webzine/10/papers/1/figure3.jpg" width="90%" border="0" alt="Works, expressions, manifestations and relations"/>
	</a>

	<p><small>Figure 3. Knut Hegna (2004) <q>Using FRBR</q></small></p>

      </div>

      <h2><a href="http://images.google.com/images?hl=en&amp;source=hp&amp;q=work+expression+manifestation+item&amp;gbv=2&amp;aq=f&amp;oq=&amp;aqi=">work expression manifestation item</a></h2>

      <p>This one hard core information science. <em>Work</em> is the
      ontological work, before it is expressed in a manuscript. The platonic
      blog entry, before it hits the web.</p>

      <p>There are other hard core ones, such as <a href="http://images.google.com/images?gbv=2&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=1&amp;q=collect+preserve+organize+provide+access&amp;aq=f&amp;oq=&amp;aqi=&amp;start=0">collect
      preserve organize provide access</a>. As a <a href="http://www.google.com/search?gbv=2&amp;hl=en&amp;q=collect%20preserve%20organize%20provide%20access&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;sa=N&amp;tab=iw&amp;start=0">web
      search</a>, it yields hits mainly in library &amp; archive mission
      statements.</p>



    </div>
  </content>
  <dc:date>2009</dc:date>
  <category label="metadata" term="Metadata"/>
  <updated>2009-12-01T07:30:21+01:00</updated>
  <published>2009-11-30T16:47:21+01:00</published>
  <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/11/kbmetadta/</id>
</entry><entry xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>Five years that formed the digital library as we know it:
  1997-2001</title>
  <link href="/entries/2009/08/threeyears/"/>
  <summary>It appeared to me that many the standards and technologies
  underpinning the digital library as we know it were formed during five years
  around the turn of the century.</summary>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

      <p>I sat there looking up references for a text. Then I realized that
      there were these five years, 1997-2001. They were decisive for the
      coming nine to ten years digital library development. For the fun of I
      looked up some events that occured during these five years</p>

      <table border="0" style="border:none;">
	<tr style="border:none;">
	  <td style="border:none;"><strong>year</strong></td>
	  <td style="border:none;"><strong>event</strong></td>
	</tr>
	<tr style="border:none;">
	  <td style="border:none;">February 1998</td>
	  <td style="border:none;"><a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/1998/REC-xml-19980210">XML became
	  recommendation</a></td>
	</tr>
	<tr style="border:none;">
	  <td style="border:none;">1998</td>
	  <td style="border:none;"><a href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2413.txt">Dublin Core
	  Metadata for Resource Discovery published as RFC 2413</a></td>
	</tr>
	<tr style="border:none;">
	  <td style="border:none;">1998</td>
	  <td style="border:none;"><a href="http://www.loc.gov/ead/tglib1998/index.html">Encoded
	  Archival Description tag lib published</a></td>
	</tr>
	<tr style="border:none;">
	  <td style="border:none;">January 1999</td>
	  <td style="border:none;"><a href="http://www.tei-c.org/About/history.xml">the University
	  of Virginia and the University of Bergen (Norway) </a> proposes the
	  formation of TEI consortium.</td>
	</tr>
	<tr style="border:none;">
	  <td style="border:none;">22 February 1999</td>
	  <td style="border:none;"><a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/1999/REC-rdf-syntax-19990222/">RDF
	  model and Syntax</a> specification appeared</td>
	</tr>
	<tr style="border:none;">
	  <td style="border:none;"> 16 November 1999</td>
	  <td style="border:none;"><a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xslt">XSL Transformations (XSLT)
	  Version 1.0 W3C Recommendation</a></td>
	</tr>
	<tr style="border:none;">
	  <td style="border:none;">January 2001</td>
	  <td style="border:none;"><a href="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/1.0/openarchivesprotocol.htm">OAI-PMH
	  version 1.0</a></td>
	</tr>
	<tr style="border:none;">
	  <td style="border:none;">February, 2001</td>
	  <td style="border:none;">The development of <a href="http://www.loc.gov/standards/mets/">METS</a> <a href="http://www.lib.berkeley.edu/digicoll/bestpractices/mets_history.html">starts</a></td>
	</tr>
      </table>

      <p>Almost all of these events were triggered by XML. If I remember
      correctly, We released <a href="http://laurentius.ub.lu.se">S:t
      Laurentius Digital Manuscript Library</a> 2001 which included my first
      serious XSLT scripting, but before that I made some serious work using
      perl and the expat XML parser.</p>

    </div>
  </content>
  <dc:date>2009</dc:date>
  <category label="metadata" term="Metadata"/>
  <updated>2009-08-24T21:09:02+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/08/threeyears/</id>
</entry><entry xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>What is a book, and does it matter?</title>
  <link href="/entries/2009/08/whatisabook/"/>
  <summary>Lorcan Dempsey of OCLC research, is involved in among lots of
  things, statistical analyses of media use. In that work they are forced to
  make operational definitions of the 'book'.</summary>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
      <p>Lorcan Dempsey of OCLC research, is involved in among lots of things,
      statistical analyses of media use. In that work he and his colleagues
      are forced to make som operational definitions of the 'book'. Definitions
      that inspired Lorcan to make some <a href="http://orweblog.oclc.org/archives/002000.html">interesting
      reflections on books</a>.</p>

      <p>I once had a chat with a book historian. Her view is was that a book
      is defined by its binding. The binding is the most important part of a
      book. Without it, it's just a pile of paper.</p>

      <p>My answer was as follows: Assume that an author is writing a
      book. While working on it there is a mansuscript -- which is a computer
      file. After a year or so, the book is completed and is accepted for
      publication.</p>

      <p>In my view it is now a book. After all <em>the book has been accepted
      for publication</em>. When you send it to the printers workshop, then I
      suppose it is manuscript. On the other hand, when you download the thing
      from <a href="http://www.amazon.com/">amazon.com</a> to your kindle,
      then it's a book.</p>
    </div>
  </content>
  <dc:date>2009</dc:date>
  <category label="essays" term="Essays"/>
  <category label="media" term="Media"/>
  <updated>2009-08-26T08:09:45+01:00</updated>
  <published>2009-08-26T07:51:07+01:00</published>
  <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/08/whatisabook/</id>
  <!-- $Id$ -->
</entry><entry xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>The predigital library</title>
  <link href="/entries/2009/08/diglib/"/>
  <summary>What is the strategic goal for a library web site? Could it be to
  put the library on the web, or is it basically to the library's resources
  visible to users anywhere on the globe?</summary>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

      <p><q cite="http://web.media.mit.edu/~nicholas/Wired/WIRED6-12.html">The
      digital revolution is over</q> wrote <a href="http://web.media.mit.edu/~nicholas/Wired/WIRED6-12.html">Nicholas
      Negroponte already 1998</a>. According to <a href="http://escherman.wordpress.com/2008/03/12/the-digital-revolution-is-over-nicholas-negroponte-in-1998/">one
      source</a>, whose credibility I have not evaluated, Douglas Adams once
      described Nicholas Negroponte as someone who <q cite="http://escherman.wordpress.com/2008/03/12/the-digital-revolution-is-over-nicholas-negroponte-in-1998/">writes
      about the future with the authority of someone who has spent a great
      deal of time there.</q> The declaration of victory for the digital
      appeared in Negroponte's last regular column in the Wired Magazine. He
      might've thougth: <em>We've won, and now is time for giving one lap top
      to every child on the globe.</em> That would indeed consolidate the
      victory.</p>

      <p style="text-align:center;">
	<br/>*
      </p>

      <p>After the digital revolution, it was natural for the library
      community to create a vision of moving <em>The Library</em> onto the
      Internet. The libraries were rising new buildings all over the globe
      called digital libraries. One particularly good one is <a href="http://www.cdlib.org/">California Digital Library</a>. CDL was
      founded 1997, i.e., the year before the digital revolution ended. The
      CDL web site is very typical in many ways. In particular its home
      page. It starts with a corporate site, and on it there is a list of
      services <q>powered by CDL</q>. For example:
      <a href="http://www.calisphere.universityofcalifornia.edu/">Calisphere</a>,

      <a href="http://content.cdlib.org/escholarship/">eScholarship
      Editions</a>,

      <a href="http://repositories.cdlib.org/escholarship/">eScholarship
      Repository</a>,

      <a href="http://www.marktwainproject.org/homepage.html">Mark Twain Project
      Online</a> 

      and 

      <a href="http://www.oac.cdlib.org/">Online Archive of California
      (OAC)</a>.
      </p>

      <p>There is much more available. I just took those from the top
      page. Most of these services are brilliant, they about the best you can
      find from any library on the globe.</p>

      <p>We see here the main method of moving the library to the Internet:
      The creation of repositories. Just as we have structured the library
      into collections, the major ones may have seperate reading rooms, the
      digital library is split into seperate services. The information
      resources from California Digital Library are spread over many,
      different domains. I'm not critizing my colleagues over there. Rather
      I'm just stating a fact that more or less all digital libraries -- even
      the best ones -- are suffering from the same problems, of which the most
      important one is that <strong>all of us are building a new repository
      whenever we start a new project</strong>.</p>

      <p style="text-align:center;">
	<br/>*
      </p>

      <p>We see now a shift from the repository is the gravitational center
      for the digital library towards the resources themselves. There should
      be no need to go to the digital library, its content should be on the
      Web. There is no need to move the library to Facebook to be where the
      users are. It is sufficient to have the library resources on the Web --
      which isn't the same as having the library there.</p>

      <p>Carl Lagoze et al. uses this shift as a justification for proposing
      the new standard OAI-ORE. When discussing the differences between the
      old OAI-PMH and the new OAI-ORE, they formulate the trend in a very
      clear way:</p>

      <blockquote style="margin-left:+5%;font-style:italic;" cite="http://arxiv.org/abs/0804.2273v1">

	<p>It <span style="font-style:normal;">[OAI-ORE]</span> also reflects
	a recognition of the position of digital libraries vis-à-vis the Web
	that sometimes seem to co-exist in a curiously parallel conceptual and
	architectural space.</p>

	<p>We exist in a world where information is synonymous not with
	<q>library</q> but with the Web and the applications that are rooted
	in it. In this world, the Web Architecture is the lingua franca for
	information interoperability, and applications such as most digital
	libraries must exist within the capabilities and constraints of that
	Web Architecture. Because of the virtual hegemony of Web browsers as
	an information access tool and Google as a discovery tool, failure to
	heed to Web Architecture principles, and therefore requiring somewhat
	special treatment by these <q>monopoly applications</q> (which is
	rarely if ever granted), effectively means falling into an information
	black hole.</p>
	<p style="text-align:right;font-style:normal"><a href="http://arxiv.org/abs/0804.2273v1">http://arxiv.org/abs/0804.2273v1</a></p>
      </blockquote>

    </div>
  </content>
  <dc:date>2009</dc:date>
  <category label="structuralwebdesign" term="Structural web design"/>
  <updated>2009-08-31T07:41:21+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/08/diglib/</id>
</entry><entry xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>A quotation is much more than an extract</title>
  <link href="/entries/2009/08/quotations/"/>
  <summary>In my last entry, on cool URIs, I discussed the identification of
  documents. The conclusion from that is that people in the library world are
  obsessed by being able to find documents. I take that more serious than most
  other library folk. I'd say that it is our mission to help our patrons find
  a single word in a text, a rectangle in an image and so forth. The time is
  gone when we could tell users: The answer to your question might be in any
  of the books on that shelf.</summary>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

      <p><em>'We quote,'</em> <a href="http://books.google.com/books?id=duUQAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA54&amp;ci=164%2C315%2C723%2C168&amp;source=bookclip">writes Isaac
      D'Israeli</a>, <em>'to save proving what has been demonstrated, referring
      to where the proofs may be found.'</em> How much wisdom isn't embedded
      in this single line! If we did not quote, then we had to explore or
      invent everything anew ourselves. We do need methods of referring our
      readers to the source. Worldwide web provides eminent facilities for
      this, such as the hypertext link.</p>

      <p>With a quote we can make our lives as writers more comfortable. We
      can, as D'Israeli continues, <em>'screen ourselves from the odium of
      doubtful opinions, which the world would not willingly accept from
      ourselves'</em>. How wonderful! I can thus market ideas that noone would
      find credible when coming from me, or refer to ones that I would not
      myself dare to publicize. The actual stylistic use of referencing belong
      to the art of writing, which is distinct from the art of hypertext.</p>

      <p>Google books provide writers with exellent facilities for hypertext
      linking. For instance, you can cut a piece of text and put into your own
      page. Like this:</p>

      <a title="Quotation like much better things has its abuses One may quote till one compiles." href="http://books.google.com/books?id=duUQAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA54&amp;ci=150%2C1240%2C753%2C64&amp;source=bookclip" style="margin-left:10%;text-align:center;">
      <img src="http://books.google.com/books?id=duUQAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA54&amp;img=1&amp;zoom=3&amp;hl=en&amp;sig=ACfU3U18wMKXLnxI-TBSM7IJ4VUTCz8bhQ&amp;ci=150%2C1240%2C753%2C64&amp;edge=0" border="0" alt="Quotation, like much better things, has its abuses. One may quote till one compiles."/>
      </a>

      <p>There are dangers of quoting, as D'Israeli makes clear. When you you
      cut and paste too much, you're no longer authoring. You're
      compiling.</p>

      <h2>The annotation anchor</h2>

      <p>If you've followed my links above you've seen how one can link to a
      page in a text, how we can highlight an area in an image and also quote
      by cutting a snippet out of an image. The single points, areas or ranges
      in an object which can be used for referencing is in my world called
      <a href="http://scholar.google.se/scholar?q=%22annotation+anchor%22&amp;hl=en&amp;btnG=S%C3%B6k">annotation anchor</a>s.</p>

      <p>In text we anchor a reference by using a unique sequence of tokens.
      In this particular text, <em>unique sequence of tokens</em> could have
      served the purpose, if I hadn't it repeated here. The position of a
      footnote could have been persistently anchored just by that sequence. In
      hypertext, we typically use mark-up for the purpose. There is a drawback
      in that, a user can only anchor his or her reference in the predefined
      positions. However, if the text is completely tokenized each single word
      is available for the purpose (see <a href="#ps">below</a>). </p>

      <h2>Persistence</h2>

      <p>Any user interface for searching and navigating parts of an object
      requires new thinking when it comes to persistence policies.  The
      libraries' HTTP hostile resolution procedures fails utterly. There is
      also much less research in the area <a href="http://scholar.google.se/scholar?q=%22annotation+anchor%22+persistence&amp;hl=en&amp;btnG=Sök">persistence
      and annotation anchors</a>.</p>

      <p>Very competent search and navigation systems, such as the <a href="http://www.cdlib.org/inside/projects/xtf/">eXtensible Text
      Framework</a> (XTF) from California Digital Library, allow users to
      search, navigate and link to arbitrary parts of a document. XTF is used
      to deliver the following document: <a href="http://ark.cdlib.org/ark:/13030/ft8r29p2ss">http://ark.cdlib.org/ark:/13030/ft8r29p2ss</a>.</p>

      <p>Now, here we have <em>extremely good</em> facilities for navigation
      and search, facilities that goes far beyond what can be delivered by
      Google. But, alas, the <a href="http://www.cdlib.org/inside/diglib/ark/">ark based</a> persistent
      identification layer isn't used for those facilities, and any linking or
      quotations or references pointing into the document might die
      with this particular implementation.</p>

      <p>The PI people lives with ideal of delivering documents, in the same
      way as they were delivered at the lending counter 25 years ago.</p>

      <h2>Linked data</h2>

      <p>I don't think anyone involved in current web development has escaped
      the linked data bandwagon. Linked data and the semantic web is believed
      by many to become the core of Web 3.0. Tim Berners-Lee <a href="http://www.w3.org/DesignIssues/LinkedData.html">lists four
      characteristics</a> of the web of data.</p>

      <em>
	<ol>
	  <li>Use URIs as names for things</li> 
	  <li>Use HTTP URIs so that people can look up those names.</li>
	  <li>When someone looks up a URI, provide useful information, using the
	  standards (RDF, SPARQL)</li>
	  <li>Include links to other URIs. so that they can discover more
	  things.</li>
	</ol>
      </em>

      <p>Anyone who wants to jump the bandwagon by means anything else on than
      than good old cool URIs does so at his or her own risk, and I
      won't. For, <a href="http://books.google.com/books?id=duUQAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA59&amp;ci=137%2C351%2C711%2C137&amp;source=bookclip">as
      D'Israeli puts it,</a> <em>'the art of quotation requires more delicacy
      in the practice than those conceive, who can see nothing more in a
      quotation than an extract.'</em></p>

      <h2 id="ps">PS</h2>

      <p>If you're interested in experimenting with mark-up based anchors,
      I'll give you a <a href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/08/quotations/add-id.xsl">XSLT-script</a>
      which basically copies a XML document but while doing so it adds an id
      attribute to every element in your document. I find this extremely
      useful. You can extend it to <a href="http://exslt.org/str/functions/tokenize/">tokenize text</a> and
      add anchors on individual words.</p>

      <p>I use such a script when creating search and navigation systems
      involving XML text. Beware though that a document type may use the
      generic xml:id attribute. Also, a DTD or schema may have another name
      for id attribute and also it may not be permissible on all elements.</p>

    </div>
  </content>
  <dc:date>2009</dc:date>
  <category label="structuralwebdesign" term="Structural web design"/>
  <updated>2009-08-21T21:13:49+01:00</updated>
  <published>2009-08-17T22:37:28+01:00</published>
  <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/08/quotations/</id>
  <!-- $Id$ -->
</entry><entry xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>Changed URI for my feed, and a forum for discussions</title>
  <link href="/entries/2009/08/features/"/>
  <summary>Having actively maintained my site for some, I've decided make a
  few changes...</summary>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
      <p>Dear Reader!</p>

      <p>I've got <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/SigfridLundbergsStuff?format=xml">a
      new URI</a> for my ATOM feed. I appologize for the inconvenience. This
      entry will be the only one available at the original one. Feed burner
      provides so many advantages that I cannot ignore them. Just click on the
      link above and subscribe, and you'll get my scribbles as usual. However,
      I've got another new feature as well.</p>

      <p>The really substantial responses I've got on this site I got from my
      <a href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/images/jacob.shtml">colleague
      Jacob</a> and <a href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/images/Gertrud_berger.shtml">my wife
      Gertrud</a></p>

      <p>Both agree that my note on <a href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/07/commuting/">commuting
      is brilliant</a>. I'm grateful for that, but as far I can tell from the
      download stats, they are the only ones who like it. Then Jacob told me I
      ought to have a forum for discussions in relation to my scribbles. Well,
      then... I've added one of those nifty javascript based ones, <a href="http://disqus.com/">disqus.com</a>. Then Gertrud said: You'll
      never find the time to moderate that. We'll see.</p>

      <p>I guess it's more likely that it will be yet another of those
      pathetic empty discussion things on the net.</p>

    </div>
  </content>
  <dc:date>2009</dc:date>
  <category label="colophon" term="Colophon"/>
  <updated>2009-08-11T08:15:39+01:00</updated>
  <published>2009-08-11T07:23:23+01:00</published>
  <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/08/features/</id>
  <!-- $Id$ -->
</entry><entry xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>Forgive me, Father, for I have sinned... I have moved a
  document</title>
  <link href="/entries/2009/08/cooluris/"/>
  <summary>The initiatives behind the persistent linking is trying to change
  the status of old documents. From 404 to 200. We've had some success with
  books and journals using ISBN and ISSN numbers. Why not try to copy this to
  the web? But, alas!, library people have in general too little understanding
  of the Worldwide Web. In particular those who advocate persistent
  identifiers.</summary>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

      <p>This comes to you as an afterthought. I killed other peoples' links
      when <a href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/08/features/">I
      last week moved a document</a>. I've felt guilt for this for a week
      now.</p>

      <p>Status 404 is a pain in the arse. You've found that link.  Apparently
      it contained some vital information for you. And then it's gone...
      We've all seen this. And since the end of the last century there have
      been people working on it, many of them coming to from the library world
      where I belong as well. The Germans seem to be most ardent. Followed by
      the Finnish and us Swedes.</p>

      <p>I full well understand people who try do something against URI rot.
      Mind you, I've spent six years of my life maintaining harvesting robots.
      However, I've hated URNs intensely since the end of the last century
      when I realized that people who hardly knew anything about HTTP,
      hypertext and markup commissioned technical solutions, such as URNs and
      URN resolvers as futile fixes to human and organizational problems.</p>

      <p>Those who know me also know that I have very strong emotions about
      persistence. These emotions started long before I had read Tim
      Berners-Lee's brilliant paper <a href="http://www.w3.org/Provider/Style/URI">Cool URIs don't
      change</a>. Tim did get one thing wrong in that paper: <em>URI's never
      ever change, people move (or remove) the documents.</em></p>

      <p>Once you've formulated a URI, it will exist until the end of
      networked information as we know it (or until the end of the world,
      whichever happens first).</p>

      <p>By the end of the nineties, the <a href="http://www.kansalliskirjasto.fi/extra/muut/meta/">Nordic Metadata
      Project</a> had commissioned a technical solution where we in the Nordic
      Web index should identify all pages with DCMI metadata and in particular
      those that where using encoding scheme URN for identifier.</p>

      <p>As a matter of fact, I found a couple of thousands such &lt;meta&gt;
      tags searching my databases. The only snag was that they all appeared on
      two sites. <a href="http://www.runeberg.org/">Project Runeberg</a> had a
      very neat collection with digitized books, each with a unique URN
      embedded in the cover page, and then <kbd>isPartOf</kbd> elements for
      each chapter.</p>

      <p><a href="http://aronsson.se/">Lars Aronsson</a>, the main architect
      behind Project Runeberg, had made his homework. However, most of the
      DCMI identifiers with encoding scheme URN were found on the web site of
      the <a href="http://www.kb.se/">Swedish National Library</a>. The only
      snag here was that all of them contained the same value.</p>

      <p>I worked for a couple of weeks with this, but result was useless
      because of the incompetence of the very people who marketed these ideas
      in Sweden. For some years to come, I sat on many meetings listening to
      them talking about the status of URN:NBN in Sweden, and for each time I
      heard about it my anger increased.</p>

      <p>One document colleagues have wanted to discuss with me the last few
      years has the following URI:</p>

      <pre>
	<a href="http://nbn-resolving.de/urn:nbn:de:gbv:7-isbn-90-6984-508-3-8">http://nbn-resolving.de/urn:nbn:de:gbv:7-isbn-90-6984-508-3-8</a>
      </pre>

      <p>It leads to Hans-Werner Hilse and Jochen Kothe, 2006.
      <em>Implementing Persistent Identifiers</em>, published by <a href="http://www.cerl,org/">Consortium of European Research Libraries,
      London</a> and <a href="http://www.knaw.nl/ecpa">European Commission on
      Preservation and Access</a>.</p>

      <p>Sending a HTTP HEAD request to the URI above yields the following
      response:</p>

      <pre>
	HEAD <a href="http://nbn-resolving.de/urn:nbn:de:gbv:7-isbn-90-6984-508-3-8">http://nbn-resolving.de/urn:nbn:de:gbv:7- ...-8</a> --&gt; 302 Found
	HEAD <a href="http://resolver.sub.uni-goettingen.de/purl/?isbn-90-6984-508-3">http://resolver ... 508-3</a> --&gt; 307 Temporary Redirect
	HEAD <a href="http://webdoc.sub.gwdg.de/edoc/ah/2006/hilse_kothe/urn%3Anbn%3Ade%3Agbv%3A7-isbn-90-6984-508-3-8.pdf">http://webdoc.sub. ...3-8.pdf</a> --&gt; 200 OK
	Connection: close
	Date: Sat, 15 Aug 2009 11:16:15 GMT
	Accept-Ranges: bytes
	ETag: "7499f564-92b7f-f0dca280"
	Server: Apache
	Content-Length: 600959
	Content-Type: application/pdf
	Last-Modified: Tue, 12 Dec 2006 15:28:58 GMT
	Client-Date: Sat, 15 Aug 2009 11:16:01 GMT
	Client-Peer: 134.76.9.3:80
	Client-Response-Num: 1
      </pre>

      <p>Obviously people in Germany love maintaining resolution
      services. First there is this global one at DNB, Deutsche
      Nationalbibliothek, and then the local one at Göttingen.</p>

      <p>It does not help them very much, though. I've been through <a href="http://www.google.com/search?hl=en&amp;q=link%3Anbn-resolving.de%2Furn%3Anbn%3Ade%3Agbv%3A7-isbn-90-6984-508-3-8&amp;btnG=Search">all
      links pointing to this booklet</a>. Only four out of fifteen points to
      the canonical source. To put this another way: Whenever Gesellschaft für
      wissenschaftliche Datenverarbeitung moves their documents, three quarter
      of the links pointing to them are gone.</p>

      <p>I have tried for hours to find any document in Google Scholar with a
      reference pointing to the Finnish URN:NBN resolver. If there are any,
      I ensure you that they never appear in papers with any impact.</p>

      <p>The money spent on maintaining the resolvers doesn't help. A complete
      waste of both time and Euros if you ask me. The PI is a dead concept,
      promoted by organizations who fail to learn from experience. It is
      completely incompatible with modern thinking on web technologies, and in
      particular semantic web and annotation and navigation of complex digital
      resources. Sorry, I felt the anger boiling up inside me again.</p>

      <p>Forgive me, Father, for I have sinned... I have moved a document.</p>

    </div>
  </content>
  <dc:date>2009</dc:date>
  <category label="structuralwebdesign" term="Structural web design"/>
  <updated>2009-08-15T14:11:54+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/08/cooluris/</id>
</entry><entry xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>Syndication and Simple REST XML web services in a library context</title>
  <link href="/entries/2009/08/opensearch/"/>
  <summary>Some time ago I demonstrated our navigation services. In that entry
  I promised to tell you more about these services when they are are more
  mature. Here is the story on the architecture of some of our new
  digitization services.</summary>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

      <p>Some time ago I discussed our architecture for <a href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/07/opml/">presenting some
      of our digitized material</a>. We use a combination of <a href="http://www.opml.org/">opml</a> and <a href="http://www.opensearch.org/">OpenSearch</a> for letting our users
      search and navigate our <a href="http://www.kb.dk/editions/any/2009/jul/editions/en/">Digital
      Editions</a>.  Opml is used for dissemination of the subject structure
      and for hierarchical tables of contents. Result set navigation is using
      open search. The system could be described as having two major
      architectural components, the database layer (<a href="#fig1">Fig. 1</a>) and the presentation layer (<a href="#fig2">Fig. 2</a>).</p>

      <div style="float: left; width: 70%; margin-left:0.5em;margin-right:0.5em;" id="fig1">
	<a href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/08/opensearch/architecture.png">
	  <img src="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/08/opensearch/architecture.png" width="100%" alt="Fig. 1." border="0"/>
	</a>
	<p>
	  <small>Fig. 1. Database layer. The export controller pulls data out
	  of our Cumulous Digital Asset Management system, normalizes them to
	  a single syntactical and semantical system, namely <a href="http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/">Metadata Object
	  Description Schema (MODS)</a>. From that format it is further
	  transformed into RSS 2.0 and Dublin Core. Finally these metadata
	  objects are stored in our Oracle as XML fragments.</small>

	  <small>The normalization rules are implemented as a set of XSLT
	  scripts with a supporting set of xpath functions implemented in
	  java.</small>
	</p>
      </div>

      <h2>Metadata processing</h2>

      <p>A couple of weeks ago, I accidentally searched the Web for "metadata
      processing". "Google suggest" invites you to that kind of
      serendipity. I've previously not been able to give a name to the
      discipline of one of my main areas of expertise; here we go. It's
      metadata processing. This phrase yields <a href="http://www.google.com/search?hl=en&amp;q=%22metadata+processing%22&amp;btnG=Search">about
      10.600 hits</a> in a Google search, which makes it a smaller disciplin
      than <a href="http://www.google.com/search?hl=en&amp;q=%22sewage+processing%22&amp;btnG=Search">sewage
      processing</a>.</p>

      <p>The database layer is all about metadata processing. Our <a href="http://www.canto.com/">Cumulus</a> installation contains a
      multitude of metadata fields invented by people for particular purposes
      in the past. The main objective has been to get a job done and images
      into a database, not out on the web in an efficient way and not to get
      the metadata across to other services.</p>


      <div style="float: right; width: 60%; margin-left:0.5em;margin-right:0.5em;" id="fig2">
	<a href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/08/opensearch/architecture2.png">
	  <img src="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/08/opensearch/architecture2.png" width="100%" alt="Fig. 2." border="0"/>
	</a>
	<p>
	  <small>Fig. 2. Presentation layer. The presentation layer is really
	  two layers, one Web service layer and one user step further away a
	  graphical user interface which we refer to as an OpenSearch
	  gateway. This is because OpenSearch is its main communication
	  protocol with the web service layer.</small>
	</p>
      </div>

      <p>In this project our goal was to be able to present this material in a
      single framework, using a homogenous metadata profile. The metadata core
      is built around Metadata Object Description Schema (MODS). The Export
      controller (<a href="#fig1">Fig. 1</a>) consists of two loosely
      connected components; the Exporter and the Digester. The former
      basically dumps data from Cumulus using its <a href="http://www.canto.com/en/docs/documentation/PDF_JCR_ReadMe_750_Z.pdf">java
      API</a>, the latter basically transforms those data into a range of XML
      fragment formats described in <a href="#tab1">Table 1</a>.</p>

      <p>The basic idea is to avoid any stage where we have to generate XML
      from scratch later on in the process; processing of semi-manufactured
      XML objects is computationally much cheaper than the generation of new
      ones.</p>

      <h2>Web services</h2>

      <p>The web service layer (<a href="#fig2">Fig. 2</a>) does search and
      retrieval and operates basically by retrieving the XML fragments
      generated by the Digester (see above). The design goal has been to
      minimize the cost of XML processing here to a minimum. For the
      processing that occur there we use the <a href="http://stax.codehaus.org/Home">Streaming API for XML (StAX)</a>
      (JSR-173). StAX is standard from java sdk 1.6. It wasn't trivial to get
      it running for java 5.</p>

      <p>When you just want to make modest stream editing of XML,
      this is an excellent tool. I doubt that you can ever get an as fast DOM
      based XML tool, so whenever possible use this. There are a few cases
      where we were forced to introduced XML and XSLT for more extensive
      editing, but in general here we use ligh-weight XML technology. We
      access Oracle through <a href="http://www.hibernate.org/">Hibernate</a>,
      which was a pleasure when the mappings were in place -- but it is a
      nightmare to make the hibernate mappings if you're a beginner.</p>

      <p>OpenSearch is my favourate XML protocol for searching, since it is
      much easier to use than <a href="http://www.loc.gov/standards/sru/">SRU</a>.  You can direct test
      an OpenSearch implementation on <a href="http://www.a9.com/-/opensearch/">on a9.com</a>. You paste the URI
      of an opensearch description into their form and you'll then get back an
      interpretation of your data and a search form. <a href="http://www.a9.com/-/opensearch/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.kb.dk%2Fcop%2Fdescription%2Fimages%2Fbilled%2F2008%2Fsep%2Fkistebilleder&amp;x=39&amp;y=11">Please
      try it!</a>. Don't search for the suggested search term esbjerg, try
      something like "Adam".</p>

      <p>The OAI service is already running, and for the first time our
      library catalog can retrieve and import bibliographical records from our
      digitization services automatically.</p>


      <div style="width: 90%; margin-left:0.5em;margin-right:0.5em;" id="tab1">
	<table>
	  <caption>Table 1. Various formats used for dissemination and
	  syndication of our data through the various XML web services mentioned
	  in <a href="#fig2">Fig. 2</a>.</caption>
	  <tr>
	    <th style="border:none;" border="0">function</th>
	    <th style="border:none;" border="0">format</th>
	    <th style="border:none;" border="0">example service</th>
	  </tr>
	  <tr>
	    <td style="border:none;" border="0">dissemination of metadata</td>
	    <td style="border:none;" border="0"><a href="http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/">MODS</a>, oai_dc via 
	    <a href="http://www.openarchives.org">OAI</a></td>
	    <td style="border:none;" border="0">
	      <a href="http://www.kb.dk/cop/oai?verb=GetRecord&amp;identifier=oai:kb.dk:Samlingsbilleder/100&amp;metadataPrefix=oai_dc">http://www.kb.dk/cop/oai?verb=GetRecord&amp;identifier=oai:kb.dk:Samlingsbilleder/100&amp;metadataPrefix=oai_dc</a>
	    </td>
	  </tr>
	  <tr>
	    <td style="border:none;" border="0">syndication and search</td>
	    <td style="border:none;" border="0"><a href="http://cyber.law.harvard.edu/rss/rss.html">RSS 2.0</a> and <a href="http://www.opensearch.org/">opensearch</a></td>
	    <td style="border:none;" border="0"><a class="feed-link" type="application/rss+xml" href="http://www.kb.dk/images/billed/2008/sep/kistebilleder/en/?query=Adam*&amp;itemsPerPage=40">http://www.kb.dk/images/billed/2008/sep/kistebilleder/en/?query=Adam*&amp;itemsPerPage=40</a></td>
	  </tr>
	  <tr>
	    <td style="border:none;" border="0">subject navigation</td>
	    <td style="border:none;" border="0">opml</td>
	    <td style="border:none;" border="0">
	      <a href="http://www.kb.dk/cop/navigation/images/billed/2008/sep/kistebilleder">http://www.kb.dk/cop/navigation/images/billed/2008/sep/kistebilleder</a>
	    </td>
	  </tr>
	  <tr>
	    <td style="border:none;" border="0">content navigation (via tables
	    of contents)</td>
	    <td style="border:none;" border="0">opml</td>
	    <td style="border:none;" border="0">no edition available yet</td>
	  </tr>
	  <tr>
	    <td style="border:none;" border="0">REST Web service description<br/>
	    Rudimentary collection level description</td>
	    <td style="border:none;" border="0"><a href="http://www.opensearch.org/Specifications/OpenSearch/1.1#OpenSearch_description_document">OpenSearchDescription</a></td>
	    <td style="border:none;" border="0"><a href="http://www.kb.dk/cop/description/images/billed/2008/sep/kistebilleder">http://www.kb.dk/cop/description/images/billed/2008/sep/kistebilleder</a>
	    </td>
	  </tr>

	  <tr>
	    <td style="border:none;" border="0">Configuration service</td>
	    <td style="border:none;" border="0"><a href="http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.5.0/docs/api/java/util/Properties.html">Java
	    properties in XML</a>. See also <a href="http://java.sun.com/dtd/properties.dtd">the DTD</a>.</td>
	    <td style="border:none;" border="0"><a href="http://www.kb.dk/cop/configuration/images/billed/2008/sep/kistebilleder">http://www.kb.dk/cop/configuration/images/billed/2008/sep/kistebilleder</a></td>


	  </tr>


	</table>
      </div>

      <h2>Presentation layer</h2>

      <p>The part of the system which users will actually see and use is best
      described as a mash-up engine. The basis is yet-another template
      system. I think that it is fair guess that each major web development
      platform already has more of those than they need. My problem was that I
      needed a recursive one.</p>

      <p>The template is a XML document with include statements in certain
      places. The engine then retrieves data from the web services, transform
      the them and put the product in place with the XML DOM api. There will
      now be new include statements, which were the product of the previous
      set of data inserted. There are usually a handful of recursions before
      the page is ready for delivery. We have two skins or templates running,
      <a href="http://www.kb.dk/images/billed/2008/maj/danmarksbilleder/">Danmarksbilleder</a>
      and Default used for the services mentioned above. Apart from different
      look and feel, Danmarksbilleder uses an older version of the database
      and another set of web services. See my previous <a href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/07/opml/">posting</a>.</p>

      <p>There are currently no plans to make new HTML skins. However, I'm
      about to write one that generates Metadata Encoding and Transmission
      Standard (METS) documents. But that's another story.</p>

      <hr/>

      <p><small>I'm trying to place my blog as being from <a href="http://bloggkartan.se/registrera/14477/lund">Lund</a> on the <a href="http://bloggkartan.se">blog map</a>.</small></p>

    </div>
  </content>
  <dc:date>2009</dc:date>
  <category label="xws" term="XML web services"/>
  <category label="metadataprocessing" term="Metadata processing"/>
  <updated>2009-09-27T12:23:52+01:00</updated>
  <published>2009-09-23T18:03:30+01:00</published>
  <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/08/opensearch/</id>
  <!-- $Id$ -->
</entry><entry xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>On Divorce and Unemployment Benefit Societies</title>
  <link href="/entries/2009/08/trends/"/>
  <summary>Here I analyse of some data retrieved from Google Insight
  Search. This little study is inspired by the study performed by Hyunyoung
  Choi &amp; Hal Varian, Google Research, were they were able to show that it
  is possible to make short-term forcasts of economic behavours using search
  statistics.</summary>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

      <p>Hyunyoung Choi &amp; Hal Varian, Google Research, have claimed that
      it is possible to make <a href="http://googleresearch.blogspot.com/2009/07/posted-by-hal-varian-chief-economist.html">short
      term economic forcasts</a> using analysis of search terms entered into
      the Google search engine. In particular, they have shown that there is a
      positive correlation between the search interest for terms related to
      the filing for unemployment benefits and the number of people who
      actually file for unemployment benefits. This number has previously been
      shown to be a very good predictor of a future increase in
      unemployment.</p>

      <p>The search interest for terms in the <a href="http://www.google.com/insights/search/#cat=706&amp;geo=US&amp;cmpt=q">Welfare
      &amp; Unemployment category</a> appear to be a predictor of the number
      of people filing for benefits. I read these papers &amp; blog entries
      with great interest. The search data are easily accessible. You retrieve
      them through a search form, and you can get them in CSV, so they can be
      loaded into your favorite statistics program via excel or any
      work-alike.</p>

      <div style="float: left; width: 50%; margin-left:0.5em;margin-right:0.5em;">
	<a href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/08/trends/kassa_series.png">
	  <img src="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/08/trends/kassa_series.png" width="100%" alt="Fig. 1. Time series for search interest for the Swedish term  'a kassa' (in red) and the corresponding Danish 'a kasse' (in green) with the same meaning."/>
	</a>
	<p>
	  <small>Fig. 1. Time series for search interest for the Swedish term
	  "a kassa" (in red) and the corresponding Danish "a kasse" (in green)
	  with the same meaning.</small>
	</p>
      </div>

      <p>Having read Choi &amp; Varian's brilliant <a href="http://reseabrch.google.com/archive/papers/initialclaimsUS.pdf">little
      paper</a> (well, I'm neither economist nor statistician, but I think
      it's good), I just had to test this data source myself.</p>

      <p>My idea was to track down effects of the recession on everyday life
      and changes in peoples views of things. It is indeed easy to find such
      correlations. <a href="http://www.google.com/insights/search/#q=john%20maynard%20keynes&amp;cmpt=q">John
      Maynard Keynes</a> has experienced a formidable revival during the last
      six months or so. I had expected to see some shift in interest, where
      Karl Marx should gain Adam Smith would loose. <a href="http://www.google.com/insights/search/#q=Adam%20Smith%2CKarl%20Marx&amp;cmpt=q">I
      think that there is such a trend as well.</a>.</p>

      <h2>Cross country correlation</h2>

      <p>In Denmark and Sweden we have to become members in a unemployment
      benefit society, i.e., we have to pay for an insurance policy against
      unemployment in order to get a sizeable unemployment allowance. There is
      a governmental dole as well, but that one is really so diminutive that
      it will hardly keep you from the street. Hence, we hardly get any
      benefit or allowance as some kind of charity from the other tax
      payers. You have to pay in advance through your membership in an
      <strong>a kass<em>a</em></strong> in Sweden or an <strong>a
      kass<em>e</em></strong> in Denmark.</p>

      <div style="float: right; width: 50%; margin-left:0.5em;margin-right:0.5em;">
	<a href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/08/trends/kassa.png">
	  <img src="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/08/trends/kassa.png" width="100%" alt="Fig. 2. The search interest for the Danish search term 'a    kasse' (y axis) plotted against the corresponding Swedish 'a kassa'    the same week. The green line represent the least square fit. There    is quite some scatter but the positive correlation is highly    significant"/>
	</a>

	<p>
	  <small>Fig. 2. The search interest for the Danish search term 'a
	  kasse' (y axis) plotted against the corresponding Swedish 'a kassa'
	  the same week. The green line represent the least square fit. There
	  is quite some scatter but the positive correlation is highly
	  significant (n=177, t=4.252 and P<sup>***</sup>&lt;0.00004,
	  two-tailed).</small>
	</p>

      </div>

      <p>Now, these two words does not appear in any other language, and I can
      safely look up the <a href="http://www.google.com/insights/search/#q=a%20%20kassa%2Ca%20kasse&amp;cmpt=q">search
      interest</a> in Google Insight for Search and be fairly sure that these
      terms are not used elsewhere. The result is depicted in Fig. 1. Note
      that for a better part of 2004 one or both columns were zero. I've
      regarded those as missing values and removed them. The same was true for
      a few datapoints representing the future. I have plotted the data as
      delivered, and it seems to me that Google applies some kind smoothing
      such as a spline function. Their graphs are much smoother than mine.</p>

      <p>It seemed to me that major peaks appeared at the same time in both
      countries. To test this I made a linear regression and correlation
      analysis. The correlation is indeed highly significant, which would
      indicate that Swedes and Danes start looking for an unemployment benefit
      society during the same periods in time. Makes sense to me. The two
      countries' economies are tightly coupled and both depend on the same
      global market.</p>

      <div style="float: left; width: 50%; margin-left:0.5em;margin-right:0.5em;">
	<a href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/08/trends/divorce-da-series.png">
	  <img src="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/08/trends/divorce-da-series.png" width="100%" alt="Fig. 3. Search interest for the terms 'a kasse' and    'skilsmisse', i.e., unemployment benefit society' and 'divorce',    respectively in Danish."/>
	</a>
	<p>
	  <small>Fig. 3. Search interest for the terms 'a kasse' and
	  'skilsmisse', i.e., unemployment benefit society' and 'divorce',
	  respectively in Danish.</small>
	</p>
      </div>

      <p>From what I can see, this correlation is OK theoretically. For all
      practical purposes we can regard the Swedish and Danish as taken from
      distinct populations, the only factor they have in common is time, and
      information in media about the international economic development (which
      off course include the development in the neighboring countries).</p>

      <h2>Until death do us part</h2>

      <p>The day after I had convinced myself that the Danes and Swedes
      recognize the risk for being made redundant at the same time, I read in
      a Danish news paper that the rise in unemployment was leading to an
      increase in divorce rate in Denmark. Most people can end their life
      without help of Internet.</p>

      <p>Ending a marriage is a bit more difficult. To divorce you must get in
      contact with a lawyer and applicable authorities. You need to fill in
      and sign a lot of forms. All this is something that require information,
      which users expect to find on the Internet.</p>

      <table border="0" width="40%" style="border:none;float:left;margin-left:0.5em;margin-right:0.5em;">

	<caption style="border:none;background:white;border-bottom:solid  thin;">Table 1. Top ten divorce related searches in Google,
	worldwide</caption>

	<tr style="border:none;background:white;">
	  <th style="border:none;background:white;">Term</th>
	  <th style="border:none;background:white;text-align: right;">Search interest</th>
	</tr>
	<tr style="border:none;">
	  <td style="border:none;">divorce law</td>
	  <td style="border:none;text-align: right;">100</td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
	  <td style="border:none;">how to divorce</td>
	  <td style="border:none;text-align: right;">85</td>
	</tr>
	<tr style="border:none;">
	  <td style="border:none;">divorce records</td>
	  <td style="border:none;text-align: right;">85</td>
	</tr>
	<tr style="border:none;">
	  <td style="border:none"> divorce court</td>
	  <td style="border:none;text-align: right;">80</td>
	</tr>
	<tr style="border:none;">
	  <td style="border:none;">divorce laws</td>
	  <td style="border:none;text-align: right;">75</td>
	</tr>
	<tr style="border:none;">
	  <td style="border:none;">divorce lawyers</td>
	  <td style="border:none;text-align: right;">50</td>
	</tr>
	<tr style="border:none;">
	  <td style="border:none;">jon and kate</td>
	  <td style="border:none;text-align: right;">45</td>
	</tr>
	<tr style="border:none;">
	  <td style="border:none;">divorce rate</td>
	  <td style="border:none;text-align: right;">45</td>
	</tr>
	<tr style="border:none;">
	  <td style="border:none;">divorce papers</td>
	  <td style="border:none;text-align: right;">45</td>
	</tr>
	<tr style="border:none;">
	  <td style="border:none;">divorce lawyer</td>
	  <td style="border:none;text-align: right;">45</td>
	</tr>
      </table>

      <p>Table 1 shows Google's top ten list for divorce oriented search
      terms. Jon and Kate are obviously a reality TV series in the US, so this
      one reflects a voracious appetite for gossip rather than a need for
      information.</p>

      <p>Then there is a group of users who are interested in statistics, such
      as divorce rate. This won't help you to get a divorce and is purely
      factual. The same true for divorce law, but here we reach the border
      line between pure fact and pure HOWTO. It is good to know the law if you
      need a divorce, isn't it?</p>

      <p>All in all, I'd say that more than half of
      these terms are searches aiming at divorce HOWTO documents. The same is
      true for Scandinavian search terms.</p>

      <div style="float: right; width: 50%; margin-left:0.5em;margin-right:0.5em;">
	<a href="/entries/2009/08/trends/divorce-da.png">
	  <img src="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/08/trends/divorce-da.png" width="100%" alt="Fig. 4. Correlation analysis between search interest for      'skilsmisse' (divorce) and 'a kasse' (unemployment benefit society)      in Denmark. There is a weak but significant positive correlation"/>
	</a>
	<p>
	  <small>Fig. 4. Correlation analysis between search interest for
	  "skilsmisse" (divorce) and "a kasse" (unemployment benefit society)
	  in Denmark. There is a weak but significant positive correlation
	  r=0.162793, n=194, t=2.28622, P<sup>*</sup>&lt;0.05 (two-tailed test).</small>
	</p>

      </div>

      <p>These considerations make it interesting enough to attempt the method
      I used for correlation above, but now for "divorce" and "unemployment
      benefit society" within each of the two countries. The Danish statistics
      is in Fig. 3-4 and the Swedish in Fig. 5-6.</p>

      <p>Danish search interest for unemployment benefit societies seemed
      lower than in Sweden (Fig. 1). Also, the Danish search interest for
      divorce "skilsmisse" is higher than for unemployment benefit societies
      "a kasse" (Fig. 3), whereas in Sweden the reverse is true. We Swedes are
      search less for "skilsmässa" than we do for "a kassa" (Fig. 4).</p>

      <p>These correlations, if real, have not, for me at least, any obvious
      interpretation. A few <a href="http://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/factoid">factoids</a> as a
      background. I list them without references -- this is not a scientific
      report, but a blog entry. They my recollections from radio news and the
      daily newspapers:</p>

      <div style="float: left; width: 50%; margin-left:0.5em;margin-right:0.5em;">
	<a href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/08/trends/divorce-sv-series.png">
	  <img src="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/08/trends/divorce-sv-series.png" width="100%" alt="Fig. 5. Search interest for the terms 'a kasse' and    'skilsmisse', i.e., unemployment benefit society' and 'divorce',    respectively in Swedish."/> 
	</a>
	<p>
	  <small>Fig. 5. Search interest for the terms 'a kasse' and
	  'skilsmisse', i.e., unemployment benefit society' and 'divorce',
	  respectively in Swedish.</small>
	</p>

      </div>

      <p><strong>i.</strong> Denmark had a lower unemployment before the
      current recession than had Sweden. This is still true. We have
      good reasons to look for a good unemployment benefit society.</p>

      <p><strong>ii.</strong> In Sweden the unemployment is biased such as it
      affects larger degree affects males than females. This is due to the
      crisis within the automobile industries we imported from the other side
      of the Atlantic.</p>

      <p><strong>iii.</strong> The Danish divorce rate 2.92 per 1000
      inhabitants) is higher than the one in Sweden (2.24). <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Divorce_demography">Both figures from
      2004</a>.</p>

      <p>It could be possible to understand the different correlations in Figs
      4 and 6 in the light of these three factoids. It would help if there is
      an asymmetry between males and females, such that the latter are a bit
      more mercyful towards their unhappy unemployed spouses than are the
      former. I.e., if Swedish women think somewhat like: <em>Well, I want to
      leave the bastard, but I don't have to do it this week when he's so
      miserable. I'll search for "skilsmässa" in Google later on.</em></p>

      <div style="float: right; width: 50%; margin-left:0.5em;margin-right:0.5em;">
	<a href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/08/trends/divorce-sv.png">
	  <img src="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/08/trends/divorce-sv.png" width="100%" alt="&gt;Fig. 6. Correlation analysis between search interest for    'skilsmässa' (divorce) and 'a kassa' (unemployment benefit society)    in Sweden. There is a significant negative correlation"/> 
	</a>
	<p>
	  <small>Fig. 6. Correlation analysis between search interest for
	  "skilsmässa" (divorce) and "a kassa" (unemployment benefit society)
	  in Sweden. There is a significant negative correlation r=-0.30391, n=241,
	  t=-4.93168, P<sup>***</sup>&lt;0.0000 (two-tailed test).</small>
	</p>

      </div>

      <h2>Concluding remarks</h2>

      <p>First and formost I wish to point out that the analyses in this blog
      entry are made by someone who has forgotten most, if not all, the theory
      behind statistical inference. I've not performed any serious statistical
      analysis for more than fifteen years. In addition the fact that my
      knowledge about statistical inference has decayed to below a statistics
      101 level, I've never worked with proper time series analysis. I fear that
      not any of my tests here would hold a critical analysis by a
      professional. To make sense, the divorce analysis require some kind of
      time lag. You don't become member of an unemployment benefit society the
      same week your spouse get fed up with you because of your bad
      unemployment temper. The latter comes later.</p>

      <p>Anyway, the purpose of this note wasn't to make a really serious
      analysis <em>per se</em>, but to explore Google's claims that one could
      use search data for serious work. I think they are right. These data are
      available for free; you can test an idea in a few days and then decide
      what more experimental &amp; survey kind of data you'll need to make a
      test your hypotheses.</p>

      <h2>PS</h2>

      <p>There are more to say about this.</p>

      <p>Unemployment is no fun. The fact that unemployment can break marriges
      doesn't worry me too much. However, some people <a href="http://www.businessweekly.co.uk/2009071635221/academia-and-research/rise-in-unemployment-linked-to-suicide-rate.html">cannot
      live with unemployment</a>. That is much worse.</p>

      <p>Obviously there are companies out there subscribing to terms related
      to suicide, depression, drug abuse, alcoholism and the like as
      adwords. A superficial look at the ads appearing in relations to such
      searches doesn't convince me that people who search for help this way
      necessarily get the best professional help available.</p>

      <p>There is a lot to do in this area. There are a many of governmental
      and charitable organizations that do great work. Serious mental problems
      should not be treated by quacks, and the subscription to adwords related
      to such terms should, in my view, not be available to just anyone. I'm
      not even sure that I think it is a good idea that pharmaceutical
      industries should sell their drugs this way.</p>

    </div>
  </content>
  <dc:date>2009</dc:date>
  <category label="essays" term="Essays"/>
  <updated>2009-08-10T08:47:07+01:00</updated>
  <published>2009-08-04T17:58:28+01:00</published>
  <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/08/trends/</id>
  <!-- $Id$ -->
</entry><entry xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>An Irish Stew</title>
  <link href="/entries/2010/01/crossroad/"/>
  <summary>Is Internet at a crossroad?</summary>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

      <p>An earlier version of this entry had the title: <em>Social media,
      Google adwords and the curation of digital refuse</em>. However, it
      would be misleading call this document a version of the text I planned
      to write.</p>

      <p>I just couldn't get the various threads in place and write a single
      text with a neat take home message. Instead, the result is a relatively
      shallow annotated URIography, rather than a deep analysis of some
      current trends in the evolution of the Internet and the western
      societies. Sorry.</p>
      
      <h3>Power Sites</h3>

      <p>A site which <q cite="http://www.tbray.org/ongoing/When/201x/2010/01/19/Power-Web-Site">is
      designed as the primary Web property for a person, place, or thing is a
      power site</q>, <a href="http://www.tbray.org/ongoing/When/201x/2010/01/19/Power-Web-Site">says
      Tim Bray</a>, <q>if the person, place, or thing has a Wikipedia entry
      but, in popular search engines, the site ranks above that Wikipedia
      entry.</q></p>

      <p>Tim Bray's own blog is a power site, my stuff isn't. I have no
      Wikipedia entry ;-). Power sites are assets these days, if you put
      adverts on the, that is.</p>


      <h3>Power Universities and Researchers</h3>

      <p>Lorcan Dempsey, whose blog is also a Power Site, discusses a number
      of social technology sites <a href="http://orweblog.oclc.org/archives/002011.html">for research
      information</a>, complete with friends and ranking etc.</p>

      <p>I <strong>like</strong> facebook for scientific papers. Do you
      <strong>like</strong> too?.</p>

      <p>The <a href="http://ouseful.wordpress.com/">Ouseful blog</a>
      discusses <a href="http://ouseful.wordpress.com/2010/02/13/virtual-revolution-google-economics/">google
      economics and page ranks</a>, while <a href="http://www.timeshighereducation.co.uk/story.asp?sectioncode=26&amp;storycode=408908&amp;navcode=105">The
      Times Higher Education</a> has ranked universities for years. That is a
      not enough, obviously, since <a href="http://science.thomsonreuters.com/globalprofilesproject/gpp-opinion/">Thomson
      Reuters</a> and <a href="http://informatics.indiana.edu/scholmet09/announcement.html">NSF
      follow suit.</a>.</p>

      <h3>Content farming</h3>

      <p>During the year 2009 we saw the advent of the <a href="http://www.readwriteweb.com/archives/content_farms_impact.php">content
      farms</a>. It is fairly easy to rapidly aggregate content by archiving
      mailing lists, RSS feeds etc. Adding Google Ads you get a business model
      as well. There's good reason to be worried, in particular for Google. A
      few other voices:

      <a href="http://www.readwriteweb.com/archives/how_google_can_combat_content_farms.php">Combat
      content farms</a>, <a href="http://techcrunch.com/2009/12/13/the-end-of-hand-crafted-content/">The
      rise of fast food content is upon us, and it’s going to get ugly</a> and
      <a href="http://www.buzzmachine.com/2009/12/14/content-farms-v-curating-farmers/">curating
      farmers</a>.</p>

      <h3>Books and parasites</h3>

      <p>To my knowledge, Jacob Nielsen was the first to describe the <a href="http://www.useit.com/alertbox/search_engines.html">parasitic
      nature of the search engine's business model</a>. The dilemma is that
      without the search engine, noone would find your pages and with the
      search engine noone will click on ads on your pages. More recently there
      has been discussions on how people will be able to survive as
      journalists and authors on a market where content farms and real news
      sites generate about as much revenue. See Charles Stross' <a href="http://www.antipope.org/charlie/blog-static/2010/01/the-monetization-paradox-or-wh.html">The
      monetization paradox (or why Google is not my friend)</a>.
      </p>

      <h3>Pointless babble</h3>

      <p>Tim O'Reilly &amp; Sarah Milstein have written <a href="http://oreilly.com/catalog/9780596802820">The Twitter Book</a>. I
      haven't read it, but then I have to confess I'm no Twitter Power
      user. I'm not even a user.</p>

      <p>Bill Heil and Mikolaj Piskorski <a href="http://blogs.hbr.org/cs/2009/06/new_twitter_research_men_follo.html">describe
      recent results from their research on Twitter</a>. They are really
      interesting and some of them are surprising, such as that the top 10% of
      prolific Twitter users accounted for over 90% of the tweets. These
      numbers are very much more aggregated than for social internet sites in
      general, where the top 10% accounts for about 30% of the activity. The
      same study shows that men follows men to a very large extent, and also
      that woman follows men more than other women but that they are more
      <q>equal</q> in their preferences. (see also <a href="http://www.businessweek.com/innovate/NussbaumOnDesign/archives/2009/06/twitter_hype_or.html">twitter
      hype or</a>, businessweek.com).</p>

      <p>One study shows that many <q>people still perceive Twitter as just
      mindless babble of people telling you what they are doing
      minute-by-minute</q> and that the tweets is written in <q>self-promotion
      with very few folks actually paying attention</q> (<a href="http://www.pearanalytics.com/blog/2009/twitter-study-reveals-interesting-results-40-percent-pointless-babble/">Pointless babble</a>)</p>

      <h3>There is a single theme</h3>

      <p>I feel that there is a single theme in all this. There are problems
      here. There are needs for business models and new methods for
      monetization. We need that as well, we in the library business. Perhaps
      a public service model could make a difference?</p>



    </div>
  </content>
  <dc:date>2010</dc:date>
  <category label="internet" term="Internet"/>
  <published>2010-01-29T21:23:40+01:00</published>
  <updated>2010-02-14T18:07:24+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2010/01/crossroad/</id>
  <!-- $Id$ -->
</entry><entry xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>Reflections on a Library at Dusk</title>
  <link href="/entries/2010/01/dusk/"/>
  <summary>During my soon five years at The Royal Library, I've seen its
  exterior in all kinds of weather conditions. Here I give you some images
  showing the spectacular black granite fasade at dusk.</summary>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
      <div style="margin: 0.5em; float: left; width:40%;">
	<a href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/galleri/200908-200912/smaller/20091201108.jpg" border="0" title="library at dusk">
	  <img src="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/galleri/200908-200912/smaller/20091201108.jpg" width="100%" alt="library at dusk"/>
	</a>
      </div>

      <p>This is The Royal Library, Copenhagen, also known as The Black
      Diamond.  I've seen its exterior in all kinds of weather conditions
      during the five years I've been working there. I'll give you some images
      showing the spectacular black granite fasade at dusk.</p>

      <p>I have taken all of them with my mobile, from the stop of bus
      66. While waiting for the bus, I can see the library if I turn towards
      the east. Towards the south I can see the harbour, which is a strait
      separating the island of Amager from Copenhagen. Here you'll recognize
      the reflections of the water in the harbour. You can also see the
      Langebro bridge and the large Ny Kredit building. These are structures
      situated west from the library, behind my back.</p>

      <div style="margin: 0.5em; float: right; width:40%;">
	<a href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2010/01/dusk/20100120204.jpg" title="rush hour reflected in a library">
	  <img src="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2010/01/dusk/20100120204.jpg" width="100%" alt="rush hour reflected in a library"/>
	</a>
      </div>

      <p>There is a red dot in the black granite. It is the reflections of the
      back light of a car driving westwards from the bus stop towards the
      bridge. If you look really careful you'll see a green traffic light
      mirror itself close the the red dot.</p>

      <div style="margin: 0.5em; float: left; width:40%;">
	<a href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/galleri/200908-200912/smaller/20091130106.jpg" border="0" title="library under the rainbow">
	  <img src="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/galleri/200908-200912/smaller/20091130106.jpg" width="100%" alt="library under the rainbow"/>
	</a>
      </div>


      <p>I've been really fascinated by these reflections for some time
      now. Here is another image which is cropped to show the traffic. There
      is red traffic lights just outside the library, and green at the
      Langebro bridge. You can see a distinct green dot in the black
      granite. There's quite a few eastbound cars taking the opportunity to
      mirror themselves in the black granite while waiting.</p>

      <h2>Somewhere under the rainbow</h2>

      <p>A classical rainbow contains most visible colours. This one, however,
      is taken at dusk. Hence there is more red in it than you're used to. To
      be honest, this image is taken east of the bus stop. You see, I had to
      position myself such that the pot of gold should be found by Our
      Saviour's Church. If you look carefully, you should be able to see the
      tip of its cork screw shaped tower just where the rain bow hits the
      ground.</p>


    </div>
  </content>
  <dc:date>2010</dc:date>
  <category label="essays" term="Essays"/>
  <published>2010-01-27T18:33:06+01:00</published>
  <updated>2010-01-28T08:06:52+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2010/01/dusk/</id>
  <!-- $Id$ -->
</entry><entry xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>Amazon, Adobe &amp; Apple</title>
  <link href="/entries/2010/02/ibooook/"/>
  <summary>My attitude towards eBooks has always been negative. Why should we lock content into proprietary formats. The sitution has changed.</summary>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

      <p>Three reflexions inspired by the three</p>

      <h3>I</h3>

      <p>Adobe has grown from being the owner of postscript and the electronic
      font foundry of the 1990's. It is still going strong on the traditional
      markets but have a lot of inpact on just about anything related to media
      consumption and production.</p>

      <p>Apple don't support flash. Apple don't support the *.epub copy
      protection promoted by Adobe.</p>

      <div style="float: left;width:70%;text-align:center;">
      <script type="text/javascript" src="http://www.gmodules.com/ig/ifr?url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.google.com%2Fig%2Fmodules%2Fgoogle_insightsforsearch_interestovertime_searchterms.xml&amp;up__property=empty&amp;up__search_terms=tablet+pc&amp;up__location=empty&amp;up__category=0&amp;up__time_range=empty&amp;up__compare_to_category=false&amp;synd=ig&amp;w=320&amp;h=350&amp;lang=sv&amp;title=Google+Trender&amp;border=%23ffffff%7C3px%2C1px+solid+%23999999&amp;output=js">

</script>
      <p><small>Fig. 1. The search interest for "tablet pc" in Google. It has
      been declining until very recently :-)</small></p>
      </div>

      <h3>II</h3>

      <p>Amazon thinks that eBooks should be cheap, say $9.99. Just as Apple
      thinks that 99 cent is OK for a track. Publishers in general and
      MacMillan in particular doesn't like that and suggests $14.99.</p>

      <p>Apple likes that.</p> 

      <p>Torrent users doesn't like that.</p> 

      <h3>III</h3>

      <p>I don't think that iPad will have any effect on eBook prices in the
      long run. However, the tablet PC will, finally, gain in popularity. And
      so will eBooks.</p>

      <p>The eBooks will make 40 year old books a commercial asset, which will further
      decrease the libraries market share.</p>

    </div>
  </content>
  <dc:date>2010</dc:date>
  <category label="internet" term="Internet"/>
  <updated>2010-02-17T20:16:45+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2010/02/ibooook/</id>
  <!-- $Id$ -->
</entry><entry xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>The proliferation of redundant meaning</title>
  <link href="/entries/2010/02/semanticdrift/"/>
  <summary>I first used the term semantic drift about 10 years ago. It was a
  real danger then, it still is but the proliferation of synonymous
  vocabularies is worse still.</summary>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

      <div style="float:left;width:60%;margin:0.5em;">
	<a href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2010/02/semanticdrift/graph.png">
	  <img src="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2010/02/semanticdrift/graph.png" style="width:100%;" alt="frequency occurrences of the term 'semantic drift'"/>
	</a>
	<p><small>Fig. 1. The usage of the term <q>semantic drift</q> in web
	documents. Note the logarithmic scale on the Y-axis: There is a
	tenfold increase between 2007 and 2008. By the first of January 2010
	there had appeared 19600. These use of the term in the context of
	semantic web is not very common. For instance, <q>semantic drift</q>
	and <q>semantic web</q> <a href="http://www.google.com/search?hl=en&amp;q=%22semantic+drift%22+%22semantic+web%22&amp;aq=f&amp;aqi=&amp;oq=">827
	hits</a> whereas the latter on its own yields more than three
	millions hits.</small></p>

	<p><small>The increase in popularity occurs in bursts. It seems to me
	that the term get a new meaning in each burst, but I've only looked at
	a small number of texts.</small></p>

      </div>

      <p>You hear a term, and you may think that it sounds cool and therefore
      you import it into your active vocabulary. About ten or twelve years ago
      <q>semantic drift</q> was such a term for me. <q>Semantic change, also
      known as semantic shift or semantic progression describes the evolution
      of word usage</q> (<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Semantic_drift">Wikipedia</a>).</p>

      <p>I'm an evolutionary biologist by training, for me <em>genetic</em>
      drift and evolution through natural (Darwinian) selection have
      <em>two</em> different meanings -- drift is the evolution which is due
      to random change which arise, mainly but not exclusively, through
      mutation between <em>synonymous</em> genes -- they differ but the effect
      is the same.</p>

      <p>I used the term <q>semantic drift</q> <a href="http://lists.w3.org/Archives/Public/www-rdf-interest/2000Oct/0121.html">publicly
      year 2000</a>. I used it for a couple of years, but I don't think I've
      used it since 2003. The term has since then gained some popularity in
      many communities (see Fig. 1). From what I've found out, the term first
      appeared in a metadata or semantic web context in an <a href="http://www.dlib.org/dlib/July95/07weibel.html">article by Stuart
      Weibel 1995</a>.</p>

      <div style="float:right;width:180px;margin:0.5em;">
	<img src="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/2000/delft/dumb_down.gif" alt="dumb down" width="178px" height="238px"/>
	<p><small>Fig. 2. The so-called dumb down principle. The only way to
	cope with the semantic diversity.</small></p>
      </div>

      <p>The discussion I adhere to above (the hitherto only documented
      occation where I mention semantic drift) was on w3.org's RDF mailing
      list, and was about the meaning of the metadata element title. More
      precisely, we were discussing what it meant that the DC title changed
      name space URI between version 1.0 (<a href="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.0/title">http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.0/title</a>)
      and version 1.1, (i.e., <a href="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/title">http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/title</a>)?</p>

      <p>There was a reader of DCMI documents who didn't understand why we did
      that change. In retrospect I think we didn't understand that either
      ourselves. We had made a mistake and we couldn't really acknowledge
      that.</p>

      <p>This is the history behind the version number 1.1 in DC. At the time
      I presented a study of meta-tags in around 5 million HTML documents
      during my life as search engineer <a href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/2000/delft/examples/metadata_statistics.html">1996-2000</a>. This
      was the time when I felt the need for Fig. 2. I drew it for illustrating
      what I was doing when I was handling metadata. The reason for using dumb
      down is that even if your service you're building is equipped with an
      advanced search form, you won't be able to sell it to a customer who
      claim that usability is important if it contains more than around ten
      fields.</p>

      <p>I have recently been thinking about these issues, frightened by
      dbpedia.org's vocabularies. See for instance <a href="http://dbpedia.org/page/August_Strindberg">August Strindberg's
      entry</a>. <a href="http://dbpedia.org/page/Inferno_(Strindberg_novel)">Inferno</a> is
      one of his works. From what I can tell, dbpedia.org is mainly using
      their own vocabularies, and <a href="http://xmlns.com/foaf/spec/">foaf</a>. I cannot find dc:creator as
      a property of Inferno, instead they use <a href="http://dbpedia.org/ontology/author">dbpedia-owl:author</a>. I hope
      they had a nice time defining their ontologies. I, however, feel
      that I need my funnel (Fig. 2) more than ever.</p>


    </div>
  </content>
  <dc:date>2010</dc:date>
  <category label="internet" term="Internet"/>
  <category label="metadata" term="Metadata"/>
  <updated>2010-02-21T09:52:02+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2010/02/semanticdrift/</id>

  <!-- $Id$ -->
</entry><entry xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>The URN:NBN is dead and resurrection is meaningless</title>
  <link href="/entries/2010/02/persid/"/>
  <summary>I'm one of those who try to base all decisions on facts. Politics
  belong to the strategic field, and in that field the only thing I can offer
  is advice.</summary>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
      <p>I'm one of those who try to base all decisions on facts. Politics
      belong to the strategic field, and in that field the only thing I can
      offer is advice.</p>

      <p>As a scientist and a software developer I've repeatedly considered
      the problems related to addressing on the Internet. I've written at
      length about <a href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/2003/urnar_och_digitala_bibliotek">URNs
      and digital libraries</a> and <a href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/08/cooluris/">Cool
      URIs</a>. I'm going to continue to do that, because there are people in
      the library communities who just fail to understand that the URN stuff
      is a complete waste of time and money on something which is to little
      benefit and that may, in my view, be potentially harmful. Most recently
      it is the <a href="http://www.surffoundation.nl/wiki/display/persid/Partners">PersID
      project</a>.</p>

      <p><strong>Please don't pull resources from scarce library budgets in
      support for an idea which died six or seven years ago!</strong></p>

      <h3>Single points of failure</h3>

      <p>The success of Internet is due to the fact that there are very few
      single points of failure. The same is true for the Worldwide web and the
      protocols that support it. The URN:NBN systems require HTTP based
      resolution services. <strong>That introduces such single points of
      failures.</strong></p>

      <h3>URN:NBN systems are lying</h3>

      <p>The <strong>H</strong>yper<strong>T</strong>ext
      <strong>T</strong>ransfer <strong>P</strong>rotocol provide means for
      servers to inform software clients that a resource has been moved. This
      is called redirection and comes in two shapes: Moved permanently and
      Moved temporarily. The redirects should be used for exactly what the
      protocol says. Anything else is abuse of the intention of the
      protocol.</p>

      <p>Unfortunately redirects is the perhaps most abused part of the HTTP
      protocol, and URN:NBN resolvers and similar systems are the worst
      culprits. They are permanently sending temporary redirects. <strong>That
      is, they are lying.</strong></p>

      <h3>It is always best to tell the truth</h3>

      <blockquote cite="http://www.w3.org/Provider/Style/URI">
	What makes a cool URI?<br/>
	A cool URI is one which does not change.<br/>
	What sorts of URI change?<br/>
	<em>URIs don't change: people change them.</em>
      </blockquote>

      <p>wrote <a href="http://www.w3.org/Provider/Style/URI">Tim
      Berners-Lee</a> 1998. He knows what he's talking about, because he
      actually invented the Worldwide web.</p>

      <p>The take-home message of his essay is that if you have things you
      care of, you should assign URIs to them that are such that you will be
      able to maintain for years to come.</p>

      <p><strong>If you change the URI, then you don't care enough.</strong>
      And you have definitely not put enough intellectual effort into the
      dissemination of your resources. To put it another way: You have not
      considered the fact that your URI structure is a part your application
      and essential to the reusability of your date. To invent a special
      infrastructure, such as URN:NBN for this is to hide away these basic
      facts.</p>

      <h3>The interactive semantic web requires cool URIs</h3>

      <p>Things have changed a lot since 1998. It was only Tim Berners-Lee and
      others in the working groups of w3.org and IETF that could forsee Web
      2.0 and Web 3.0. You can recognize many of the pioneers from the fact
      that they usually claim that nothing has changed. And they're right,
      nothing technical has changed since 1998, other than that peoples
      understanding of what can be achieved using the web can do has gone from
      version 1.0 to 2.0 and is now on its way to version 3.0.</p>

      <p>Those who argue that we should go for URN:NBN have not understood.</p>

      <p>As a matter of fact, I'd say that they never understood the release
      version 0.9. I'm sorry.</p>

      <p><strong>In the web of data, the aspects of a resource that are worth
      persistent identification is in the hand of its users, since it is the
      users who do the linking.</strong></p>

      <p>Why on earth should we assign a URN:NBN to Romeo &amp; Juliet, if the
      users want to quote the balcony scene?</p>

      <p>Why on earth should you assign a URN:NBN to an article, when I want
      to address Figure 3?</p>

      <p>User annotation need a persistent annotation anchor, and that could
      be a part of an image.</p>

      <p>Yes, we need persistence. But please, not technology advised by
      people who never understood web 0.9</p>


    </div>
  </content>
  <dc:date>2010</dc:date>
  <category label="structuralwebdesign" term="Structural web design"/>
  <category label="internet" term="Internet"/>
  <updated>2010-02-23T07:31:22+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2010/02/persid/</id>
  <!-- $Id$ -->
</entry><entry xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>Podcast: Mor minns</title>
  <link href="/entries/2010/02/mor_minns/"/>
  <summary>Min mor har tre år kvar till 100. Jag menar att hon är en helt
  fantastisk kvinna, med ett knivskarpt intellekt. Hon fick aldrig gå mer än
  sju år i skolan som barn, men i 60-årsåldern tog hon i princip
  gymnasiekompetens. I denna serie läser hon dikter och berättar ur minnet
  eftersom hon är nästan blind.</summary>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

      <p>Syster Lundberg föddes den 27 februari 1913 och hon är min mor. Jag
      menar att hon är en helt fantastisk kvinna, med ett knivskarpt
      intellekt. Hon fick aldrig gå mer än sju år i skolan som barn, men i
      60-årsåldern tog hon i princip gymnasiekompetens.</p>

      <p>I denna serie läser hon dikter och berättar ur minnet eftersom hon är
      nästan blind. Det är inte helt lätt att få henne att berätta, men gamla
      psalmer är lättare.</p>

      <div>
	<ul>
	  <li>Använd <a href="itpc://sigfrid-lundberg.se/podcasts/mor_minns/mor_minns.rss">iTunes</a></li>

	  <li><label for="podcast"><a href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/podcasts/mor_minns/mor_minns.rss">XML/RSS-flöde</a></label>
        <input id="podcast" title="Länk till RSS-flöde" size="31" value="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/podcasts/mor_minns/mor_minns.rss" onclick="this.focus();this.select();" type="text"/></li>
	</ul>

      </div>

      <div style="float:right;width:40%;margin:0.5em;">
	<img src="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/galleri/200902-200904/smaller/cimg1154.jpg" style="width:100%;" alt="Syster Lundberg, snart 97"/>
      </div>


      <h3 id="haerenkaellarinner">I. Här en källa rinner</h3>

      <p>Sannolikt ur <a href="http://runeberg.org/sondag/0086.html">Svensk
      söndagsskolsångbok för hem, skolor och barngudstjänster</a></p>

      <p><a href="http://storage.sigfrid-lundberg.se/sound/dikten_haer_en_kaella_rinner.mp3">http://storage.sigfrid-lundberg.se/sound/dikten_haer_en_kaella_rinner.mp3</a>
      (938 KB)</p>

      <h3 id="nydag">II. Ny Dag/Fåglarna som bådar gryningen flyger</h3>

      <p>Dikten Ny Dag är egentligen en sång ur en kantat av Anita Nathorst
      (text) och Oskar Lindberg (musik), skriven till Fredrika Bremer
      Förbundets 50-årsfest 1934 och publicerad i <a href="http://www.ub.gu.se/kvinn/digtid/06/1934/hertha1934_4.pdf">förbundets
      tidsskrift Herta</a>. Mor var med och sjöng den i Husmodersföreningens
      kör någon gång på 60-talet.</p>

      <blockquote>
	<p>De fåglar, som bådar gryningen,<br/>
	flyger med lätta slag.<br/>
	Skall deras mjuka vingar<br/>
	nås av en klarare morgondag?</p>

	<p>Vi har gått vilse i hårda år.<br/>
	Vågar vi ana en mjukare vår,<br/>
	räcka varandra händerna<br/>
	tvärs över haven och länderna?<br/>
	Vågar vi, mitt i vårt ödes strid,<br/>
	-- stanna och lyssna och lysa den frid<br/>
	världen behöver och langtar till<br/>
	mer än den anar och vet och vill?<br/>
	Makt -- är den eld, som förtär oss,<br/>
	Kärlek -- är guden, som bär oss.</p>
      </blockquote>

      <p><a href="http://storage.sigfrid-lundberg.se/sound/dikten_faaglarna_flyger.mp3">http://storage.sigfrid-lundberg.se/sound/dikten_faaglarna_flyger.mp3</a>
 (938 KB)</p>

      <h3 id="denvaen">III. Var är den vän som överallt jag söker?</h3>

      <p>En av Johan Olof Wallin vackraste psalmer. <a href="http://runeberg.org/psalmbok/1932/0325.html">Svenska Psalmboken
      481</a></p>

      <p><a href="http://storage.sigfrid-lundberg.se/sound/dikten_hur_skon.mp3">http://storage.sigfrid-lundberg.se/sound/dikten_hur_skon.mp3</a> 
      (894 KB)</p>

    </div>
  </content>
  <dc:date>2010</dc:date>
  <category label="essays" term="Essays"/>
  <updated>2010-02-21T17:07:10+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2010/02/mor_minns/</id>
  <!-- $Id$ -->
</entry><entry xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>Why you need a persistence strategy</title>
  <link href="/entries/2010/02/youdontneed/"/>
  <summary>Here I go through some of the arguments why you need to implement a
  persistence strategy. We also conclude that the hypertext link is the single
  thing that makes the Worldwide web to a web. Hence it is a serious thing. If
  you're working within the digital library world you should be devoted to the
  hypertext link.</summary>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

      <p>Alma Mater (the university that saw me mature from a teenager to a Ph
      D) has a web site. It used to implement a graphical profile which stated
      that all links should be listed at the end of a document. The
      documentation actually also claimed that hypertext links inside text
      bodies was poor usability. This is just plain bullshit. The hypertext
      link is the the single thing that makes the Worldwide web to a web. If
      some usability expert dislikes Wikipedia I bet it isn't because of all
      the hypertext links.</p>

      <p>Libraries have over the centuries provided experiences and
      information. Scholars have read and <a href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/08/quotations/">quoted the
      material we offer</a>. This has changed. <strong>Today the most
      important challenge for libraries today is to provide anchors for
      hypertext links.</strong></p>

      <p>Libraries who think that mission is accomplished when they've solved
      the problem of efficient document delivery belong to the past. You have
      to provide means for patrons to link to the arbitrary anchors in
      hypertexts, to polygons in images or time segments in video
      recordings.</p>

      <p>Document delivery is important. You cannot use documents unless they
      are not delivered. Neither can you create arbitrary hypertext links into
      it. However, it is the fact that you are not done when your patron has
      the document in his or her browser which is the single most important
      reason why URN:NBN, DOI or HANDLEs are obsolete.</p>

      <p>It isn't you who should link to your documents. It is the library
      patrons who should do that. If they want to link to page five, they
      should be able to do so, and the link created should be as persistent as
      any German URN:NBN.</p>

      <p>And then. If you're not convinced:</p>

      <h3>1. I need PID to connect documents to archived copies</h3>

      <p>The problem is that people don't use PIDs in their texts, since they
      never see them. They follow links, are redirected by the resolver and
      link to what they get. When you remove your original hypertext anchor,
      many of your digital patrons links will rot.</p>

      <p>The truth is that you don't need to use PIDs for this. If you use
      HTTP as intended you redirect your users when moving documents to the
      archive. Users will never suffer. If you use PIDs they'll experience the
      404.</p>

      <h3>2. The DOI system is very good. It works</h3>

      <p>Yes, it works but it is not good. It is as bad as any other redirect
      based PID system. It works though, but that is because the consortium
      forces its members to care about links. That is very
      <strong>good</strong>, but the DOI system isn't.</p>

      <p>The truth is that you don't need DOIs for that. You need a link
      management policy.</p>

      <h3>3. PID's work when people change their domains. Cool URIs don't</h3>

      <p>Not really. Since people don't use PIDs in their documents, this
      doesn't help here either -- see point 1 above.</p>

      <p>The truth is that you should not change your domain. It is not
      regarded good practice among people who care about content. However, if
      you have to, use redirects (Moved permanently, status 301).</p>

      <p>If you have to change, keep the old one for a very long time. Someone
      may buy using your brand for selling porn or something else you don't
      approve.</p>

    </div>
  </content>
  <dc:date>2010</dc:date>
  <category label="structuralwebdesign" term="Structural web design"/>
  <category label="internet" term="Internet"/>
  <updated>2010-02-25T07:07:57+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2010/02/youdontneed/</id>

  <!-- $Id$ -->
</entry></feed>
