<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<entry xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>Atom contains all you need to annotate &amp; navigate</title>
  <link href="/entries/2010/04/atomlink/"/>
  <summary>Atom syndication format contains everything you need to build 
  good annotation and navigation systems</summary>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

      <h3 id="atomnavigation">Navigate</h3>

      <p>M. Nottingham &amp; R. Sayre, 2005. The Atom Syndication Format
      <a href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc4287">http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc4287</a></p>


      <p>The RFC 4287 specifies the Atom syndicaton format and states the
      following about</p>

      <blockquote cite="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc4287#section-4.2.7">
	<em>[t]he "atom:link" element [which] defines a reference from an entry or
	feed to a Web resource.  This specification assigns no meaning to the
	content (if any) of this element.</em> (<a href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc4287#section-4.2.7">Section
	4.2.7</a>)
      </blockquote>

      <p>The reference mentioned is given in the <kbd>kref</kbd>
      attribute. The RFC does, clearly, not assign any semantics to the
      relation embodied by the tag. However, it continues discussing the
      <kbd>rel</kbd> attribute (those of you who know the elements of
      &lt;html:link/&gt; realizes that the two tags are very similar):</p>

      <blockquote>
	<em>atom:link elements MAY have a "rel" attribute that indicates the
	link relation type.  If the "rel" attribute is not present, the link
	element MUST be interpreted as if the link relation type is
	"alternate". [...] If a name is given, implementations MUST consider
	the link relation type equivalent to the same name registered within
	the IANA </em> (<a href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc4287#section-4.2.7.2">Section
	4.2.7.2</a>)
      </blockquote>

      <p>The semantics of the relations are thus from a controlled list which
      is has an international maintenance agency, IANA. In a moment I'll
      discuss that list, but before I'll mention a few more useful attributes
      of the atom:link element: <kbd>title</kbd> and <kbd>hreflang</kbd>. The
      former <q>conveys human-readable information about the link</q> and the
      latter <q>describes the language of the resource pointed to by the href
      attribute</q>.</p>

      <p>Now, the vocabulary to be used for the <kbd>rel</kbd> attribute is
      maintained by <a href="http://www.iana.org/">Internet Assigned Numbers
      Authority</a> (IANA) and published in a document <a href="http://www.iana.org/assignments/link-relations/link-relations.xhtml">Atom
      Link Relations</a>. Each entry on this list has to be documented (which
      is usually done in an RFC). Here are obvious ones, such as:</p>

      <ul>
	<li><kbd>up</kbd></li>
	<li><kbd>first</kbd></li>
	<li><kbd>previous</kbd></li>
	<li><kbd>next</kbd></li>
	<li><kbd>last</kbd></li>
      </ul>

      <p>Hence, here you have anythin you need for navigating just about any
      content that may be modelled as a tree. And much more.</p>

      <h3 id="atomannotations">Annotate</h3>

      <p>J. Snell, 2006. Atom Threading Extensions
      <a href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc4685">http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc4685</a></p>

      <p>The Atom infrastructure for comments, discussions and annotations is
      described in RFC4685. The mechanism is simple:</p>

      <blockquote cite="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc4685#section-3">
	<em>The "in-reply-to" element is used to indicate that an entry is a
	response to another resource.  The element MUST contain a "ref"
	attribute identifying the resource that is being responded to.</em>
	(<a href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc4685#section-3">RFC 4685,
	Section 3</a>)
      </blockquote>

      <p>The <kbd>ref</kbd> <q cite="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc4685#section-3">attribute specifies
      the persistent, universally unique identifier of the resource being
      responded to</q>. In practice it will refer to the content of the
      <kbd>id</kbd> element of the annotated research, which is described in
      <a href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc4287#section-4.2.6">RFC 4287</a>.</p>

      <p>So, you just add a reply-to link to your entry, and the entry has
      become an annotation. The rest is programming. <strong>;-)</strong></p>

      <hr/>
      <p>This entry is part of my series <a href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2010/04/readings/">Readings on
      digital objects</a></p>

    </div>
  </content>
  <dc:date>2010</dc:date>
  <category label="digitalobjects" term="Digital objects"/>
  <category label="xws" term="XML web services"/>
  <updated>2010-04-28T13:15:31+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2010/04/atomlink/</id>
  <!-- $Id$ -->
</entry>
