<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<entry xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>Movable type and the typographer's last words</title>
  <link href="/entries/2015/01/movabletype/"/>
  <summary>Equipment from my fathers workshop.</summary>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

      <div style="margin: +1%; width:45%;float:left;">
	<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/sigfridlundberg/6061372765" title="A as in Ariella">
	  <img src="https://farm7.staticflickr.com/6082/6061372765_1faea33ed8_z.jpg" style="width:100%;" alt="A as in Ariella"/>
	</a>
	<p><small>Capital A in the font Ariella 36p.  Ariella was used for
	printing flyers and stuff.</small></p>
      </div>

      <p>Waldermar Lundberg, my father, was born 1915. He was a printer and
      typographer and established a small workshop around 1947. The images
      here show some of the equipment he kept after his retirement 1975. He
      continued to work with printing and bookbinding until his death
      2007.</p>

      <br style="clear:both;"/>

      <div style="margin: +1%; width:45%;float:right;">
	<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/sigfridlundberg/6061968168"
	   title="Berling Antikva. Semi-bold."><img
	   src="https://farm7.staticflickr.com/6081/6061968168_675848600d_z.jpg"
	   style="width:100%;" alt="Berling Antikva. Semi-bold."/></a>
	<p><small>The top case contains Garamond 10p, the rest is Berling 12p
	up to 24p in step of four.</small></p>
      </div>

      <p>All types were stored in rack cabinets like this. My father had a
      fairly complete set of Berling Antiqua, designed by <a
      href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Karl-Erik_Forsberg">Karl-Erik
      Forsberg</a> (1914-1995) in the 1950s and produced by <a
      href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Berling_Type_Foundry">Berling type
      foundry</a> here in Lund until 1980, when the company ended its more
      than 170 years in the graphical industry. The Berling Type Foundry was
      established in Copenhagen 1750 and continued its business there until
      1783. It was then reestablished in Lund 1837.</p>

      <p>Hand composing is significantly more complicated than typing touch on
      a computer or type writer. It is more like it than you would expect,
      though. You have to know where the types are, and they are <em>not</em>
      alphabetical order. Think of a QWERTY keyboard, but you have a large
      number of different space keys. Width equal to the width of l, n and m
      is just a start. There were spaces thin as paper. Think of the work to
      compose whole books having justified margins!</p>

      <p>I worked several summers mid 1960s decomposing matrixes in the composing
      room, and I even did some smaller composing jobs. I think I could do it
      again.</p>

      <br style="clear:both;"/>

      <div style="margin: +1%; width:45%;float:left;">
	<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/sigfridlundberg/6061385949" title="Movable type"><img src="https://farm7.staticflickr.com/6088/6061385949_0267486e98_z.jpg" style="width:100%;" alt="Movable type"/></a>
      </div>

      <p>Type pieces for large print was stored standing in rows. This could
      be the home for Ariella 36p.</p>

      <br style="clear:both;"/>

      <div style="margin: +1%; width:45%;float:right;">
	<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/sigfridlundberg/6061501777" title="Printing presses"><img src="https://farm7.staticflickr.com/6076/6061501777_381f9242a3_z.jpg" style="width:100%;" alt="Printing presses"/></a>
      </div>

      <p>Prior to his retirement my father had ten to 15 employees and an at
      times flourishing business. Among other things he was the second largest
      Swedish printer of time cards during the 1960s, and had also a not
      insignificant portion of the Norwegian market.</p>

      <p>After his retirement he worked in this basement workshop for about
      thirty years. He had various printing presses including a fairly large
      modern offset press during a brief period. He kept these two old vintage
      tabletop printing presses until his death. He inherited one from a
      colleague and the other had been in his possession since the 1940s.</p>

      <p>My brother, Torsten, and I donated one of the presses and a rack
      cabinet to a local museum. The rest of the equipment we sold to a young
      talented graphical designer <a
      href="http://www.markussjoborg.se/">Markus Sjöborg</a> who has a small
      business in Malmö. He makes good use of this and other equipment he
      finds out there.</p>


      <br style="clear:both;"/>

      <div style="margin: +1%; width:45%;float:left;">
	<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/sigfridlundberg/6061535459" title="The Typographer's Last Words"><img src="https://farm7.staticflickr.com/6078/6061535459_2a1c67343c_z.jpg" style="width:100%;" alt="The Typographer's Last     Words"/></a>
      </div>

      <p>This matrix is for printing a text on a book spine in one of the
      printing presses. They are the last words typeset by my father.</p>

    </div>
  </content>
  <dc:date>2015</dc:date>
  <category label="typography" term="Typography"/>
  <category label="photography" term="Photography"/>
  <updated>2015-01-13T22:01:09+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2015/01/movabletype/</id>
</entry>
