<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<entry xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>Why you need a persistence strategy</title>
  <link href="/entries/2010/02/youdontneed/"/>
  <summary>Here I go through some of the arguments why you need to implement a
  persistence strategy. We also conclude that the hypertext link is the single
  thing that makes the Worldwide web to a web. Hence it is a serious thing. If
  you're working within the digital library world you should be devoted to the
  hypertext link.</summary>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

      <p>Alma Mater (the university that saw me mature from a teenager to a Ph
      D) has a web site. It used to implement a graphical profile which stated
      that links should be listed at the end of a document. The documentation
      actually also claimed that hypertext links inside text bodies was poor
      usability. This is just plain bullshit. The hypertext link is the the
      single thing that makes the Worldwide web to a web. If some usability
      expert dislikes Wikipedia I bet it isn't because of all the hypertext
      links.</p>

      <p>Libraries have over the centuries provided experiences and
      information. Scholars have read and <a
      href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/08/quotations/">quoted the
      material we offer</a>. This has changed. <strong>Today the most
      important challenge for libraries today is to provide anchors for
      hypertext links.</strong></p>

      <p>Libraries who think that when they're done when they've solved the
      problem of efficient document delivery belong to the past. You have to
      provide means for patrons to link the a arbitrary anchor in hypertexts or to
      polygons in images or a time segments in video recordings.</p>

      <p>Document delivery is important. You cannot use documents if they're
      not delivered, and neither can you create arbitrary hypertext
      links. However, it is the fact that you're not done when your patron has
      the document which is the single most important reason why URN:NBN, DOI
      or HANDLEs doesn't work.</p>

      <p>It isn't you who should link to your documents. It's your users who
      should do that, and if they want to link to page five, they should be
      able to do so, and the link created should be as persistent as any ISBN
      and hopefully more correct.</p>

      <p>And then. If you're not convinced</p>

      <h3>1. I need PID to connect documents to archived copies</h3>

      <p>The problem is that people don't use PIDs in their texts, since they
      never see them. When you remove your original hypertext anchor many of
      your digital patrons links will rot.</p>

      <p>The truth is that you don't need to. If you use HTTP as intended and
      redirect your users when moving documents to the archived they will
      never suffer.</p>

      <h3>2. The DOI system is very good. It works</h3>

      <p>Yes, it works but it is no good. It is as bad as any other redirect
      based PID system. But it works, and that is because the consortium
      forces its members to care about links. That is very good, but the DOI
      system isn't.</p>

      <p>The truth is that you don't need DOIs for that. You need a link
      management policy.</p>

      <h3>3. PID's work when people change their domains. Cool URIs don't</h3>

      <p>Not really. Since people don't use PIDs in their documents, this
      doesn't help here either -- see point 1. above.</p>

      <p>The truth is that you don't need to change your domain. And if you
      do, use redirects. If you leave your domain, you'll regret it. Someone
      will buy it for selling porn or something. Believe me.</p>

    </div>
  </content>
  <dc:date>2010</dc:date>
  <category label="structuralwebdesign" term="Structural web design"/>
  <category label="internet" term="Internet"/>
  <updated>2010-02-25T07:07:57+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2010/02/youdontneed/</id>
</entry>
