<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<entry xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>Thinking when the spring is approaching</title>
  <link href="/entries/2010/03/thinking/"/>
  <summary>Winter is just the worst part of the year. Where approaching the
  end of it.</summary>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

      <div style="float:right;width:33%;margin-right:0.5em;margin-left:0.5em;">
	<a href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2010/03/thinking/20100218231.jpg" title="The Thinker" ><img src="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2010/03/thinking/smaller20100218231.jpg" alt="The Thinker" width="100%"/></a>
	<p>
	  <small>Fig. 1. There is no doubt what the thinker has been thinking
	  about this winter. Or that is what I think.</small>
	</p>
      </div>

     <p>It has been a long and harsh winter here in Scandinavia. I am one of
     those who hate the cold darkness which characterizes my part of the
     world. Many of us have been thinking about the weather (Fig. 1).</p>

     <p>Since christmas I've been involved two projects, one of which is
     currently approaching deliverable. Unfortunately it has been delayed but
     on the other hand I've got the opportunity to learn <a
     href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2010/03/aformwithajoin/"
     title="A Form with a Join">Xforms</a>. I think that both the library and
     myself will benefit from it.</p>

     <div style="float:left;width:33%;margin-right:0.75em;margin-left:0.5em;">
       <a href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2010/03/thinking/20100130216.jpg" title="Public Transport Burdened by Ice">
	 <img src="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2010/03/thinking/smaller20100130216.jpg" width="100%" alt="Public Transport Burdened by Ice"/>
       </a>
       <p><small>Fig. 2. All public transport has had far too much
       problems. And far too few trains has carried too many passengers, and
       too much ice.</small></p>
     </div>

     <p>The other project, a redesign of our Digital Object Management System
     (DOMS), is approaching a journey to Stanford together with some good
     colleagues.</p>

     <p>Those of us who <a
     href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/07/commuting/">commute</a>
     has had problems during the winter (Fig. 2). Regardless of how we travel,
     most of us look forward to the spring (Fig. 3).</p>

      <div style="float:right;width:45%;margin-right:0.5em;margin-left:0.5em;">
	<a href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2010/03/thinking/20100207227.jpg" title="Socially unacceptable vehicle in snow" ><img src="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2010/03/thinking/smaller20100207227.jpg" alt="Socially unacceptable vehicle in snow" width="100%"/></a>

	<p><small>Fig. 3. But so has all Socially Unacceptable Vehicles. This
	vehicle is buried. In snow. The owner looks forward to spring. So do
	I.</small></p>
      </div>

      <h2>New projects</h2>

      <p>I have two really stimulating projects which will keep me occupied
      for the better part of the coming year. The most important one for me is
      that I've been given the opportunity to spend one quarter of my time on
      basic research into digital library objects.</p>

      <p>The idea is to start from the <a
      href="http://scholar.google.com/scholar?hl=en&amp;q=soda%20model%20dumb%20archive&amp;aql=&amp;oq=&amp;um=1&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;sa=N&amp;tab=ws">Smart
      Object Dumb Archive</a> (SODA) model. It is an old model, but there is
      not many alternatives.  There are a number of new approaches that look
      very much like SODA, such as the successful <a
      href="http://www.idpf.org/">.epub format</a> and the formats used within
      <a href="http://www.upnp.org/">Universal Plug and Play</a>. UPnP
      distributes both metadata and digital objects such as music and film
      within a local area network.</p>

      <p>The second project is still just planning but here I will contribute
      to a new critical edition of Ludvig Holbergs collected work.</p>

    </div>
  </content>
  <dc:date>2010</dc:date>
  <category label="essays" term="Essays"/>
  <category label="images" term="Images"/>
  <updated>2010-03-09T07:28:40+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2010/03/thinking/</id>
  <!-- $Id$ -->
</entry>
