<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<entry xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>The predigital library</title>
  <link href="/entries/2009/08/diglib/"/>
  <summary>What is the strategic goal for a library web site? Could it be to
  put the library on the web, or is it basically to the library's resources
  visible to users anywhere on the globe?</summary>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

      <p><q cite="https://web.media.mit.edu/~nicholas/Wired/WIRED6-12.html">The
      digital revolution is over</q> wrote <a href="https://web.media.mit.edu/~nicholas/Wired/WIRED6-12.html">Nicholas
      Negroponte already 1998</a>. According to <a href="https://escherman.wordpress.com/2008/03/12/the-digital-revolution-is-over-nicholas-negroponte-in-1998/">one
      source</a>, whose credibility I have not evaluated, Douglas Adams once
      described Nicholas Negroponte as someone who <q cite="https://escherman.wordpress.com/2008/03/12/the-digital-revolution-is-over-nicholas-negroponte-in-1998/">writes
      about the future with the authority of someone who has spent a great
      deal of time there.</q> The declaration of victory for the digital
      appeared in Negroponte's last regular column in the Wired Magazine. He
      might've thougth: <em>We've won, and now is time for giving one lap top
      to every child on the globe.</em> That would indeed consolidate the
      victory.</p>

      <p style="text-align:center;">
	<br/>*
      </p>

      <p>After the digital revolution, it was natural for the library
      community to create a vision of moving <em>The Library</em> onto the
      Internet. The libraries were rising new buildings all over the globe
      called digital libraries. One particularly good one is <a href="https://cdlib.org/">California Digital Library</a>. CDL was
      founded 1997, i.e., the year before the digital revolution ended. The
      CDL web site is very typical in many ways. In particular its home
      page. It starts with a corporate site, and on it there is a list of
      services <q>powered by CDL</q>. For example:
      <a href="https://calisphere.org/">Calisphere</a>,

      <a href="https://publishing.cdlib.org/ucpressebooks/">eScholarship
      Editions</a>,

      <a href="https://escholarship.org/#home_repository">eScholarship
      Repository</a>,

      <a href="https://www.marktwainproject.org/homepage.html">Mark Twain Project
      Online</a> 

      and 

      <a href="https://oac.cdlib.org/">Online Archive of California
      (OAC)</a>.
      </p>

      <p>There is much more available. I just took those from the top
      page. Most of these services are brilliant, they about the best you can
      find from any library on the globe.</p>

      <p>We see here the main method of moving the library to the Internet:
      The creation of repositories. Just as we have structured the library
      into collections, the major ones may have seperate reading rooms, the
      digital library is split into seperate services. The information
      resources from California Digital Library are spread over many,
      different domains. I'm not critizing my colleagues over there. Rather
      I'm just stating a fact that more or less all digital libraries -- even
      the best ones -- are suffering from the same problems, of which the most
      important one is that <strong>all of us are building a new repository
      whenever we start a new project</strong>.</p>

      <p style="text-align:center;">
	<br/>*
      </p>

      <p>We see now a shift from the repository is the gravitational center
      for the digital library towards the resources themselves. There should
      be no need to go to the digital library, its content should be on the
      Web. There is no need to move the library to Facebook to be where the
      users are. It is sufficient to have the library resources on the Web --
      which isn't the same as having the library there.</p>

      <p>Carl Lagoze et al. uses this shift as a justification for proposing
      the new standard OAI-ORE. When discussing the differences between the
      old OAI-PMH and the new OAI-ORE, they formulate the trend in a very
      clear way:</p>

      <blockquote style="margin-left:+5%;font-style:italic;" cite="http://arxiv.org/abs/0804.2273v1">

	<p>It <span style="font-style:normal;">[OAI-ORE]</span> also reflects
	a recognition of the position of digital libraries vis-à-vis the Web
	that sometimes seem to co-exist in a curiously parallel conceptual and
	architectural space.</p>

	<p>We exist in a world where information is synonymous not with
	<q>library</q> but with the Web and the applications that are rooted
	in it. In this world, the Web Architecture is the lingua franca for
	information interoperability, and applications such as most digital
	libraries must exist within the capabilities and constraints of that
	Web Architecture. Because of the virtual hegemony of Web browsers as
	an information access tool and Google as a discovery tool, failure to
	heed to Web Architecture principles, and therefore requiring somewhat
	special treatment by these <q>monopoly applications</q> (which is
	rarely if ever granted), effectively means falling into an information
	black hole.</p>
	<p style="text-align:right;font-style:normal"><a href="http://arxiv.org/abs/0804.2273v1">http://arxiv.org/abs/0804.2273v1</a></p>
      </blockquote>

    </div>
  </content>
  <dc:date>2009</dc:date>
  <category label="structuralwebdesign" term="Structural web design"/>
  <updated>2009-08-31T07:41:21+01:00</updated>
  <id>https://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/08/diglib/</id>
</entry>
