<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<entry xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>Creative Commons and Dutch Elm Disease</title>
  <link href="/entries/2012/05/elmdisease/"/>
  <summary>A story about some dead trees, a walk with friends in Skåne and a
  natural reserve outside Bristol, UK.</summary>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
      <p>
	<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/sigfridlundberg/5660543200/" 
	   title="P4256945.ORF by Sigfrid Lundberg, on Flickr">
	  <img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5262/5660543200_3495ab74ae_z.jpg" 
	       width="100%" alt="P4256945.ORF"/>
	</a>
      </p>
      <p>I've been an active amateur photographer many years, but more so
      since I about three years acquired a digital system camera and started
      to <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/sigfridlundberg/">share my
      images on Flickr</a>. Besides the actual publication of your photos,
      there is an ongoing conversation on images and photography on Flickr
      which usually means that photographers visits each others streams and
      comment. Today I got the following comment:</p>

      <blockquote>Hi Sigfrid, Thanks for licensing this powerful image under
      Creative Commons. Dutch elm disease wreaked similar havoc here in the
      UK. We have used the image on a community blog about an open space,
      called Clifton and Durham Downs, here in Bristol. You can see the image
      and accompanying story here:<br/>
      <a
      href="http://www.thedowns150.org.uk/2011/12/dutch-elm-disease/">www.thedowns150.org.uk/2011/12/dutch-elm-disease/</a></blockquote>

      <p>I haven't got any comment that made me sad on Flickr, but hardly any
      that made me more glad than the one above.</p>

      <p>My photos are used all over the place, and it makes me happy when I
      see them used for commendable purposes. They even appear on less
      worthwhile sites as well, but that is another story. But this is the
      first time someone actually thanked me for licensing my photos under a
      CC license.</p>

    </div>
  </content>
  <dc:date>2012</dc:date>
  <category label="flickr" term="Flickr"/>
  <category label="creativecommons" term="Creative Commons"/>
  <category label="photography" term="Photography"/>
  <updated>2012-05-08T19:18:41+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2012/05/elmdisease/</id>
</entry>
