<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<entry xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>Does hypertext promote extractive interaction rather than
  immersive?</title>
  <link href="/entries/2010/04/extractive/"/>
  <summary>Extractive and immersive are two forms of interactivity. This note
  claims that the digital library services have successfully implemented
  facilities for extractive media consumption but that it is very difficult to
  help users in the immersive pattern.</summary>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

      <p>There is an academic genre often referred to as <em>New Media
      Research</em>. To what extent this pursuit really deserve the lable
      research I won't go into here. I usually find contributions from this
      area utterly boring. The <a href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/08/diglib/">digital
      revolution ended 1998</a> and hence all new the media are old by now,
      and that includes Twitter and Facebook. Period.</p>

      <p>In addition I find almost all comparisons between old and new medias
      tedious, inasmuchas that I seldom learn something new reading
      them. Similarly, any text starting by claiming that the ICT area is
      under rapid development will remain only partly read. Usually only the
      very first part. Unless the first few sentences contain something
      interesting <strong>and</strong> something that's new to me. Like the <a href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2010/04/gstupid/">article by
      Nicholas Carr I mentioned the other day</a>. Carr argues that we
      nowadays have difficulties immerse in really long texts, which to
      correspond to changes in mentality.</p>

      <p>I picked up two adjectives describing people's media consumption
      patterns: <em>Extractive</em> and <em>immersive</em>. The dichotomy
      seems to come from a paper by <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_Lunenfeld">Peter Lunefeld</a>,
      who, is a student of interactive media, computer games etc. You'll find
      the two adjectives in connection with nouns as "navigation",
      "interaction" or gerunds like "<a href="http://www.blackplasticglasses.com/2010/03/23/digital-reading/">reading</a>". As
      far as reading is concerned, I'll add to my <a href="http://camqtly.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/abstract/34/3/285">
      a paper</a> reading list analyzing the consequences of a spread of
      extractive reading behaviours from a language pedagogy perspective.</p>

      <p>What worries Carr is a shift from immersive to extractive reading and
      its psychological or even neurological consequences. I do both, a
      lot. On a personal level I can vividly recall my reading of the last
      volume in <a href="http://www.stieglarsson.com/Millennium-series">Stieg
      Larsson's Millenium Trilogy</a>. I just read one page more many houndred
      times that night, until the alarm went off, and I stumbled to the
      shower, the breakfeast and off to work trying to look as if I was able
      to do something useful. Such as coding new interfaces for media
      consumption.</p>

      <p>Does the digital revolution make people less able to immerse in books
      like Donald Knuth's <em><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Art_of_Computer_Programming">The
      Art of Computer Programming</a></em> with about 650 pages per volume?
      Seven volumes are planned but four have yet appeared, the one as recent
      as 2005. You need to able to immerse in books like that to devise search
      algorithms, so we may get into trouble with the next generation global
      search engines.</p>

    </div>
  </content>
  <dc:date>2010</dc:date>
  <category label="essays" term="Essays"/>
  <updated>2010-04-19T18:16:45+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2010/04/extractive/</id>
  <!-- $Id$ -->
</entry>
