<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<entry xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
       xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>Why do I keep this site?</title>
  <link href="/entries/2009/06/why/"/>
  <summary>Having had a web site for about 15 years, I start to wonder why I
  keep it in the first place.</summary>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

      <p>A week or two ago I registered this site with Google Analytics. My
      Internet supply provider's statics is virtually useless. Then I've spent
      quite some time cutting and pasting the javascript into my olde
      stuff.</p>

      <p>I haven't cared about this site for about four years and as far as I
      can tell now, this place is hit by a one or two people per day, each of
      which stay less than a minute. Why they come I don't know, and Google
      Analytics won't tell me yet.</p>

      <p>Now, I didn't expect anything else. I use the site as a store for old
      documentation, of which just a few things could possibly be valuable for
      students of Internet history. Most likely, though, they hardly even
      deserve a footnote in the posterity.</p>

      <h3>The origins</h3>

      <p>I started this site autumn 1995. The oldest documents still in the
      public collection is from <a href="/1996">1996</a>. Now, started isn't
      really the right word. I never <em>planned</em> to build a web site
      with old documents. Basically, I started a web server on a development
      machine and devoted an area for project documentation and reports. I
      could then drop a piece of text there and send the URI to my colleagues
      or customers. That is how it started.</p>

      <p>This worked well to begin with, but about five years later the
      rudimentary structure per project was lost. I then made a backup copy,
      and created a structure by year, and copied stuff from the old site into
      it. This is the way it is now.</p>

      <p>I started the current site <a href="/2005">2005</a>, when I left Lund
      university for a new job in Copenhagen. I felt that I just couldn't let
      this material just disappear.</p>

      <p>The site contains quite a few archived files. Counting them gives 241
      HTML files, 21 pdf, 84 xml and so forth. Of these I regard 37 as
      publications of some kind, in the sense that there are links to them
      that may be reached from the home page. It is still just a sample, the
      raw collection contains 2452 HTML files.</p>

      <p>I have no idea if I have benefited from the site, or if the material
      has been useful for someone else. For a few years, notably <a
      href="/2002">2002</a>, <a href="/2003">2003</a> and <a
      href="/2004">2004</a>, I did have an idea that I should make an active
      effort to maintain a web site. Some of the best texts are from that
      period.</p>

      <h3>Publish or let it perish?</h3>

      <p>I earn my livelihood as a developer for the Worldwide Web. But this
      site is not a part of what I do for my living. So, should I have it
      available here or let it perish?</p>

      <p>I pay my ISP 250 SEK per month for this, which include a Linux shell
      prompt available via secure shell and some storage. The storage side of
      it is no big deal; I have already a number of USB hard disks around. I
      have also <kbd>*.zip</kbd> and <kbd>*.tar.gz</kbd> files as attachment
      on my gmail account, which provides huge storage and good value for
      money in comparison with what I get from my ISP. But then, 250 SEK is no
      big deal either.</p>

      <p>So I'll keep it, for the time being. I don't think my stuff
      contribute very much to the digital refuse spread over the net. I've
      added an <a href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/rfc4287">ATOM syndication
      feed</a> for the garbage I decided to keep, a subject browsing based on
      the ATOM categories. Finally I've added some texts from the last few
      years. These are basically of the same kind as the rest of my
      stuff. Reports and papers written for some specific purpose and
      republished here entirely out of context.</p>

    </div>
  </content>
  <dc:date>2009</dc:date>
  <category label="structuralwebdesign" term="Structural web design" />
  <updated>2009-06-27T12:18:00+01:00</updated>
  <id>https://sigfrid-lundberg.se/feed/why.xml</id>
</entry>
