<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<entry xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>On patience and bus stops</title>
  <link href="/entries/2010/11/patience/"/>
  <summary>Waiting at a bus stop can learn us something significant about
  human nature</summary>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

      <!--img src="http://books.google.com/books?id=q2cJAAAAQAAJ&amp;pg=PA119&amp;img=1&amp;zoom=3&amp;hl=en&amp;sig=ACfU3U1uLANXhGxurHshyIN4q1BHy2z_jA&amp;ci=134%2C1267%2C380%2C131&amp;edge=0"/-->

      <p>Waiting is not for everyone. I'm good at it, though. Brilliant, if I
      may say so myself. I've practiced. I'm particularly good at waiting
      for public transports. Such as waiting for trains. Or buses.</p>

      <p><q style="font-style:italic;">Patience</q>, states <a
      href="http://books.google.com/books?id=q2cJAAAAQAAJ&amp;dq=%22art%20of%20waiting%22&amp;pg=PA119&amp;ci=134%2C1267%2C380%2C131&amp;source=bookclip">The
      Mirror</a> (Saturday 19, 1825), <q style="font-style:italic;">is the art
      of waiting.</q> That's true, for sure. But then editor continues: <q
      style="font-style:italic;">Time passes quickly with him who hopes for
      days and lives for the morrow. Hope has such efficacy that it can lead
      us to the end of life through an agreeable path and even beyond life
      itself.</q> Interesting concept. Who would you like share an hour at a
      bus stop with: One who hopes or one that doesn't? In this case hope
      would imply the conviction that the bus will come and pick you up before
      you die, or at least so you arrive home before dinner.</p>

      <p>I think that the The Mirror is wrong. Patience comes from the
      erroneous conviction that time spent waiting is an investment or an
      asset of some kind. The really patient person is the one who after
      waiting for (say) a quarter of an hour, dismisses the option to take a
      cab or walk, because he feels that he will then loose his investment in
      waiting. You've heard, haven't you: <q>Let's wait five minutes
      more.</q></p>

      <p>Mind you, the fallacy is aggravated by the fact that it takes just
      twenty minutes to walk to the station. Suppose it's better to start
      walking.</p>

    </div>
  </content>
  <dc:date>2010</dc:date>
  <category label="structuralwebdesign" term="Structural web design"/>
  <updated>2010-11-26T17:15:36+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2010/11/patience/</id>
</entry>
