<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<entry xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>Peer review and request for comments</title>
  <link href="/entries/2010/11/rfc/"/>
  <summary>Laurent Romary and myself have authored an RFC. That means a
  Request For Comments. I now understand why.</summary>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
      <p><a href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2010/03/appteixml/">Earlier
      this year</a> Laurent Romary and myself authored an Internet Draft,
      which is the first step towards a Request For Comments (RFC). Now the
      text has been trough the review process and we have made all the
      revisions required. So, finally it has been approved by the <a href="http://www.iesg.org">IESG</a>'s review process. I do now
      understand the RFC concept.</p>

      <p>Internet was created by people connected to the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Darpanet">DARPA net</a> family of
      projects with the first serious experimental work starting around
      1968. The people who did it were affiliated to various US universities
      and a few companies capable mean, you send your idea on how Internet can
      be made better to your fellow researches in ARPA net.</p>

      <p>It seems that these people communicated their findings by storing and
      circulating them as oddly formatted text files on the very
      infrastructure that were the subject for their research. And now more
      than forty years later there still is this mix of individuals from
      academic and corporate research environments from all over the
      world. Friendly geeks who want that the Internet should be good place
      for its users. So, when you submit a draft you <em>do</em> get the
      comments you requested. You get a lot of them and in our case they were
      all constructive and friendly. The process is <a
      href="http://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-lundberg-app-tei-xml/">open</a></p>

      <p>That's why its called an RFC and thats why they Internets
      standardization procedures works so well.</p>

    </div>
  </content>
  <dc:date>2010</dc:date>
  <category label="internet" term="Internet"/>
  <updated>2010-11-25T18:31:04+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2010/11/rfc/</id>
  <!-- $Id$ -->
</entry>
