<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<entry xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>Bell's Books</title>
  <link href="/entries/2010/04/bells/"/>
  <summary>I bought three books at Bell's Books, 536 Emerson Street, Palo
  Alto</summary>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

      <p>I bought three books (Fig. 1) at <a
      href="http://www.bellsbooks.com/">Bell's Books</a>, 536 Emerson Street,
      Palo Alto. This is a large, well kept (mostly antiquarian) bookshop with
      knowledgeable staff. I can recommend it wholeheartedly.</p>

      <div style="float:right;width:60%;margin:0.5em;">
	<a href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2010/04/bells/20100509_001.jpg" alt="Three books acquired at Bell's Books, Palo Alto"><img width="100%" src="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2010/04/bells/smaller20100509_001.jpg" alt="Three books acquired at Bell's Books, Palo Alto"/></a>
	<p><small>Fig. 1. I bought (from left to right) Wallace Stegner's
	<em>Little live things</em>, <em>The man who loved books too much</em>
	by Allison Hoover Bartlett and <em>A hole in the water</em> by Mae
	Briskin.</small></p>
	<p><small>I bought Stegner based on the first sentence in the book,
	Briskin because I like the title and Hoover Bartlett's book because
	I've actually met a book thief.</small></p>
      </div>

      <p>How do people choose the books they read? In spite of the fact that
      I'm a very digital person, I choose a lot of the books I read based on
      the cover, typography, the feeling when you hold it and even their
      smell. Mostly, however, I choose certain authors, or read a bit in the
      beginning of the text, or the back cover. And yes, I read a lot of
      pocket books, as well.</p>

      <p>Of the three books, I've as yet only read Hoover Bartlett's on the
      Californian book thief.</p>

      <p>I've actually met a large scale book thief. The one operating at the
      Swedish Nation Library, and who dramatically ended his life in a gas
      explosion. Now he'll <a
      href="http://www.svd.se/kulturnoje/nyheter/boktjuvens-dubbelliv-blir-film_2476539.svd">become
      film</a>. We were in the same project group when we were building <a
      href="http://www.ediffah.org/">Ediffah</a>.</p>

    </div>
  </content>
  <dc:date>2010</dc:date>
  <category label="stories" term="Stories"/>
  <updated>2010-05-10T21:29:22+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2010/04/bells/</id>
  <!-- $Id$ -->
</entry>
