<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<entry xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>Camera Lucida and a tale on two mothers</title>
  <link href="/entries/2014/11/cameralucida/"/>
  <summary>I've read Roland Barthes' book Camera Lucida</summary>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

      <div style="margin: +1%; width:50%;float:right;">
	<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/sigfridlundberg/7253867456"
	   title="By Sigfrid  Lundberg, on Flickr">
	  <img
	      src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8149/7253867456_93f69a7595_c.jpg"
	      width="100%" alt="R0013883.JPG"/>
	</a>
	<p><small>The ubiquitous photographers tried to capture whatever
	decisive moments they could experience outside Tivoli, Copenhagen, May
	2012.</small></p>
      </div>

      <p><em>Camera Lucida</em> is about Roland Barthes' thoughts about
      photographs and in particular the photographs he had of his mother after
      her death. It is also about our memories.</p>

      <p>It is just 120 pages, short book. In chapter 47 (out of 48 brief
      texts) he concludes:</p>

      <blockquote>
	<q>The <em>noeme</em> [i.e., the essence] of photography is simple,
	banal; no depth: &#8216;That has been.&#8217; I know our critics: What
	a whole book (even a short one) to discover something I knew at first
	glance?</q>
      </blockquote>

      <p>Barthes is trying to pinpoint the essence of the photograph, not
      necessarily the essence of photography. He arrives at the conclusion that a
      photograph is basically an indication that its subject has existed and
      the photographer was there to see it. All those people who take
      photographs everywhere basically tells everyone that they've been there
      and they saw <em>it</em> whatever that was.</p>

      <p>I think that he is basically correct. Most photographs taken are
      snaps, and the popularity of Instagram and Snapchat are further proof of
      that. In the very last chapter he says something really suprising:</p>

      <blockquote>
	<q>Photography can in fact be an art: when there is no longer any
	madness in it, when its <em>noeme</em> is forgotten and when
	consequently its essence no longer acts on me</q>
      </blockquote>

      <div style="margin: +1%; width:50%;float:left;">
	<a href="/entries/2014/11/cameralucida/2013-03-24_18.02.32.jpg"
	   title="My mother teaches me riding my bike">
	  <img
	      src="/entries/2014/11/cameralucida/2013-03-24_18.02.32.jpg"
	      width="100%"
	      alt="My mother teaches me riding my bike" />
	</a>
	<p><small>I believe my mother taught me riding my bike 1962 when I was
	six years old. This photo should be five or six year younger than
	myself.</small></p>
      </div>

      <p>Basically, Roland Barthes seem to say that art photography is
      boring. That is a very sweeping conclusion, and an extremely subjective
      one. The artsy photos is pure <em>studium</em>, not
      <em>punctum</em>. The former means that the cognitive effect of an image
      is that one looks and perhaps learns and understand something from it,
      and the latter is another is an area in it which triggering a minor
      shock or surprise.</p>

      <p>Arthur Koestler worked on a unified theory of human creativity. One
      of his points is somehow related to Barthes' dichotomy. Koestler
      proposes that human creativity has three domains named after their
      cognitive effects, <strong>haha</strong>, <strong>aha</strong> and
      <strong>ah</strong>. They correspond to creativity within humour,
      discovery and art, respectively. I'd say that <em>punctum</em> contains
      elements of <strong>haha</strong> or <strong>aha</strong> or both, but
      that a good <em>studium</em> is basically <strong>ah</strong>.</p>

      <p>For me it was impossible to read it without thinking about mother, my
      own mother.</p>

      <div style="margin: +1%; width:50%;float:right;">
	<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/sigfridlundberg/7949605842"
	   title="R0015684_v3 by Sigfrid  Lundberg, on Flickr">
	  <img
	      src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8446/7949605842_47dc999d2f_c.jpg"
	      width="100%"
	      alt="R0015684_v3"/>
	</a>
      </div>
    </div>
  </content>
  <dc:date>2014</dc:date>
  <category label="mothers" term="Mothers"/>
  <category label="photography" term="Photography"/>
  <category label="essays" term="Essays"/>
  <updated>2014-11-04T21:39:02+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2014/11/cameralucida/</id>
</entry>
