<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<entry xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>Who defines a PC</title>
  <link href="/entries/2010/06/frontiers/"/>
  <summary>The PC was defined by IBM and Microsoft. Who defines it
  today?</summary>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

      <p>Tablets, eReaders, Smartbooks: You Name the Device and It’s News at
      Computex <a
      href="http://blogs.arm.com/arm-events/tablets-ereaders-smartbooks-you-name-the-device-and-its-news-at-computex/">writes
      Katie Morgan</a>
      of Advanced Risc Machines (ARM). You may not know about it, but just as
      Intel rules the desktop, the British chip design company's ARM
      Architecture rules the pockets.</p>

      <p>According to Wikipedia, 90%+ of all processors in mobile phones and
      embedded devices are equipped with this architecture. This means that
      there's.a fair chance that both your phone, your wireless router and
      your fridge are all ARM systems.</p>

      <p>The mobiles &amp; the tablets are given prominent positions in the news
      feeds, and as I write this there one such item in top of Google News'
      Sci/Tech section. It is about Apple's iPhone, which, by the way, like
      the Android systems, are ARM.</p>

      <p>Intel has tried to establish itself in this area, have not been able
      to do so through can getting an increased market share by winning
      customers from ARM. The tablets is a new segment, and the race to start
      exploit the unchartered land. The chip Intel try to market here is the
      Atom processor which, of course, is x86.</p>

      <p>Google's Android &amp; Chromium are both Linux platforms (hence
      Helsinki &amp; Stanford Universities), whereas iPhone OS is a redecorated
      Berkeley Unix with a Mach kernel. Yes, it is a Mach kernel, as in the
      speed of sound. This makes these gadgets University of California &amp;
      Carnegie Mellon University.</p>

      <p>All of a sudden we see new and sometimes unexpected alliances. Two
      examples:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>Global leaders Intel Corporation and Nokia merge Moblin and Maemo
	to create MeeGo*, a Linux-based …</li>

	<li>ARM, Freescale, IBM, Samsung, ST-Ericsson and Texas Instruments
	Form New Company to Speed the Rollout of Linux-Based Devices</li>

      </ul>

      <p>I read and write mail, manage my calendars, surf and do a better part
      of my wordprocessing with my <a
      href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2010/05/n900/">tablet</a>. I
      also do some authoring on it, which requires programming and XML tools
      such as an XSLT processor.</p>

      <p>Hence, I want a hand-held computer which enables me.to do much the
      same things I've done using my laptop. One could say that this is one of
      many the preliminary answers to the questions the industry is posing to
      the market.</p>

      <p>The vendors have obviously radically different views on the future of
      computing. Recently Steve Jobs claimed that the PC as we know it is like
      an old truck and that the future belongs to the tablets. Steve Ballmer
      participated in the same conference and disputed these claims. He seemed
      to be convinced that the desktop PC will.continue to be the workstation
      for a foreseeable future.</p>

      <a href="http://blogs.computerworld.com/16252/were_ballmer_ozzie_in_denial_at_d">http://blogs.computerworld.com/16252/were_ballmer_ozzie_in_denial_at_d</a>

      <p><q>The PC as we know it will continue to morph,</q> he said. <q>The
      real question is what are you going to push.</q> In Microsoft’s case,
      the answer is more machines that run flavors of Windows. <q>To a man with
      a hammer everything looks like a nail; we have a hammer,</q> Mr. Ballmer
      joked.</p>

      <a href="http://bits.blogs.nytimes.com/2010/06/03/ballmer-the-pc-will-continue-to-thrive/">http://bits.blogs.nytimes.com/2010/06/03/ballmer-the-pc-will-continue-to-thrive/</a>

    </div>
  </content>
  <dc:date>2010</dc:date>
  <category label="hardware" term="Hardware"/>
  <category label="software" term="Software"/>
  <updated>2010-06-10T07:29:24+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2010/06/frontiers/</id>
  <!-- $Id$ -->
</entry>
