<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<entry xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>Do you hate XML?</title> 
  <link href="/entries/2010/07/hate_xml/"/>
  <summary>Does developers really dislike XML? If they do, why and how much</summary>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

      <p>I've spent much of the last ten or twelve years working with problems
      related to interoperability and portability of data and metadata. During
      these years I've been forced to work with XML. Early on I evangelized
      about XML with the fervor of a taleban. I suppose that I contributed to
      the four or five of XML hype that started at the turn of the century and
      culminated 2004 - 2005.</p>



      <div style="float:left;width:65%;margin-right:0.5em;margin-left:0.5em;">
	<a href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2010/07/hate_xml/hate_xml.png">
	  <img src="/entries/2010/07/hate_xml/hate_xml.png" 
	       width="100%" 
	       alt="Hate XML web pages"/>
	</a>
	<p>
	  <small>Figure 1. The change in the occurrence of web pages
	  containing the text <strong><q>hate xml</q></strong>. Because of the
	  way Google works, the date searches mostly hits blog entries and
	  other syndicated material, where date and other metadata are
	  known. There earliest occurence is from 2001. There is a steep
	  increase in occurence a few year after the Applied XML Developer's
	  Conference 2004. After that it seems to level off.</small>
	</p>
	<p>
	  <small>The data points represents hits for two year periods graphed
	  against the first of january the second year in each period.</small>
	</p>
      </div>

      <p>When you have grasped a technology you cannot keep up strong
      emotions, at least not positive ones. Possibly you can become more
      negative as time goes by. Or that is my personal experience.</p>

      <p>I cannot recall that I've ever written somewhere that I hate someone
      or even something.  I feel that hatred is emotional and irrational. It
      may be a difference between languages and cultures; it can be a question
      of semantic inflation. When we Scandinavians say that we hate something,
      we mean it.  I'm not sure that that's the case in the anglo-american
      sphere.  However, it may also be a question of age; when you're
      middle-aged you may not think it's appropriate to hate, or you may not
      think that it's appropriate to describe your dislikes and annoyances as
      hatred.</p> <p>Already year 2000 a friend of mine described his relation
      to XML as <q>angle bracket fatique</q>, which is to be understood as
      <q>I hate typing XML</q></p>


      <div style="float:right;width:65%;margin-right:0.5em;margin-left:0.5em;">
	<a href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2010/07/hate_xml/report_hate_xml.png"><img src="/entries/2010/07/hate_xml/report_hate_xml.png" 
	width="100%" 
	alt="Search interest for &quot;hate xml&quot; in Google 2004-2010"/></a>
	<p>
	  <small>Figure 2. Search interest in Google for the term
	  <strong><q>hate xml</q></strong>. There are hardly any connection
	  between the change in occurrence of the <q>hate xml</q>-emotions and
	  search interest. People seem search for the term a few years after they
	  wrote about it.</small>
	</p>
      </div>

      <p>Year 2004, <a
      href="http://www.sellsbrothers.com/">sellsbrothers.com</a> convened an
      <a
      href="http://www.devsource.com/c/a/Techniques/Programming-Guidance-from-the-Uumlbergeeks/">Applied
      XML Developer's Conference</a>. I cannot recollect that I heard of that
      conference at the time, but there was one contribution which got quite
      some attention around in the blogosphere. It was by Chris Anderson (AKA
      <a href="http://www.simplegeek.com/">SimpleGeek</a>) who gave the
      presentation <q>Developers Hate XML</q>. I haven't found the slides on
      the net. However, <a href="http://www.jeff-barr.com/?p=80">Jeff Barr</a>
      summarizes as follows</p>

      <blockquote>
	<em>Chris’s big beef with XML is that XML must be processed in
	isolation, using special purpose tools and languages such as XSLT. In
	order to use these special things, <strong>developers must become
	domain experts</strong></em> [my emphasis] <em>in a rich and complex
	space that is essentially unrelated to the application itself.</em>
      </blockquote>

      <p>I think Chris (and Jeff) points out something important here. Many
      developers are interested in programming and computing, but not
      necessarily application areas. To parse and make something meaningful
      out of, say, bibliographical records or encoded text requires that you
      are actually interested in those areas. The same is true for fluid
      dynamics and natural language processing. Interest in partial
      differential equations and lingustics, respectively, will help.</p>

      <p>I cannot see any difference here between XML and SQL in this
      respect. Any tools for object-relational modeling is subject to the same
      problems. The developers that do the modelling has to become domain
      experts.</p>

    </div> 
  </content>
  <dc:date>2010</dc:date>
  <category label="xmltechnologies" term="XML technologies"/>
  <updated>2010-07-29T16:34:22+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2010/07/hate_xml/</id>
</entry>
