<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
                  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>Sigfrid Lundberg's Homepage</title>
    <author>
      <firstname>Sigfrid</firstname>
      <surname>Lundberg</surname>
    </author>
    <revhistory>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>$Revision$</revnumber>
        <date>$Date$</date>
        <authorinitials>$Author$</authorinitials>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </articleinfo>

  <abstract>

    <para>My name is Sigfrid Lundberg, and this is my homepage, i.e., it is
    kind of an article about myself.</para>

  </abstract>

  <sect1 id="activities">
    <title>Activities</title>

    <para>I earn my livelihood as an Internet programmer, and as such I
    attempt to help people finding their ways about on the web by implementing
    various kinds of search engines. I do this together with friends and
    colleagues at <ulink url="http://www.lub.lu.se/">Lund University
    Libraries</ulink> and before that at <ulink
    url="http://www.lub.lu.se/netlab/">NetLab</ulink> (see also info on <ulink
    url="http://www.ariadne.ac.uk/issue32/netlab-conference/">NetLab's
    birthday party</ulink> and a note on the <ulink
    url="http://www.ariadne.ac.uk/issue32/netlab-history/">history of
    NetLab</ulink>).</para>

    <sect2 id="web_indexing">
      <title>Web indexing</title>

      <para>Initially, I worked exclusively with robot based search indexes.
      Here at NetLab we implemented the <emphasis>combine</emphasis>
      harvesting robot, which <ulink url="http://www.lub.lu.se/combine/">you
      may get for free</ulink>. The work is done as a part of the <ulink
      url="http://www.desire.org/">Desire project</ulink>.</para>

      <para>We used the Combine for a number of purposes. Among those were to
      build the Nordic Web Index. <ulink
      url="http://hem.bredband.net/sigfridlundberg/1996/nwi/nwi.pdf">We
      released the NWI 1996</ulink>, about a month after Digital released
      <ulink url="http://www.altavista.com">Alta Vista</ulink>. Thus we were
      among the first search engines to support European character sets (with
      nasty characters like å, ä, ö, ü and the like). During its life time,
      NWI usually had a higher coverage of the Nordic web than its commercial
      competition. The NWI was also one of the very first web indexes that had
      extensive support for <ulink url="http://www.dublincore.org/">Dublin
      Core Metadata</ulink>. We gave a
      <ulink url="http://www7.scu.edu.au/programme/fullpapers/1900/com1900.htm">
      presentation</ulink> on this work at the 7th Internation World wide web
      conference.</para>

      <para>For quite some time I used the Combine for a lot of different
      projects, such as the now defunct Safari research information service
      (again, I wrote a <ulink
      url="/SigfridLundberg/1998/safari/cris.pdf">presentation of the
      service</ulink>, but I'm sorry, it is in swedish).</para>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="preservation">

      <title>Digital preservation and publication</title>

      <para>Now my interests has shifted from the rather specific problems of
      indexing the web towards digital preservation, digital publishing and
      the searching of tagged text in general, and in particular SGML/XML
      documents. I do not feel that there is any difference between making
      available historical and current material (which would be preservation
      and publication, respectively). The main difference is the tense. What
      we do today (present tense) will in the future be a preservation problem
      (future tense).</para>

      <para>The best example of my work in this area is the <ulink
      url="laurentius.html">S:t Laurentius</ulink> <ulink
      url="http://laurentius.lub.lu.se/">digital manuscript
      library</ulink>.</para>

      <para>I have written a <ulink
      url="http://laurentius.lub.lu.se/search/presentation/laurentius.pdf">
      conceptual description of the search engine</ulink> we built for our
      manuscript collection.</para>

      <para>The most importan current project within this area is <ulink
      url="/2004/arkiv_bibliotek/">Ediffah</ulink>, which aims at implementing
      a search engine for EAD finding aids for archives in Swedish library
      collections.</para>

    </sect2>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="publishing">

    <title>Electronic publishing</title>

    <sect2 id="publishing_on_the_web">
      <title>Putting stuff on the Web</title>

      <para>Today electronic publishing usually means publishing stuff on a
      web server. A better part of my time is spent on building infrastructure
      for creating facilities for just that, including cataloging of such
      stuff and delivering it to end users in a structured way. I've recently
      made two services for use within Lund university, <ulink
      url="http://theses.lub.lu.se/undergrad/">Xerxes</ulink> and <ulink
      url="http://theses.lub.lu.se/postgrad/">Scripta Academica
      Lundensis</ulink>, aimed for publishing and dissemination of
      undergraduate and postgraduate electronic theses and dissertations.
      </para>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="printing_n_publishing">

      <title>Printing and publishing</title>

      <para>One of my passions is electronic typesetting, and in particular of
      scientific texts -- with equations, graphs, references, footnotes,
      quotations and you name it. Since I left science, I've had little
      opportunity to exercise that passion. However with the current XML boom,
      it is possible for me to make use of this old knowledge, in a new
      context.</para>

      <para>For texts I write myself, I use <ulink
      url="http://www.tei-c.org/">the TEI XML dtd</ulink> which I may then
      transformed into other formats (e.g., HTML) using <ulink
      url="http://www.w3.org/Style/XSL/">XSLT</ulink>. For printed output I
      translate it into troff source, which I format using with <ulink
      url="http://www.jclark.com/bio.htm">James Clark</ulink>'s <ulink
      url="http://groff.ffii.org">groff</ulink> package, a free re-engineered
      version of troff, the UNIX (TM) typesetting system. Throught the years,
      I have written a lot of XSLT scripts, *roff macros, dozens of perl
      scripts that work with *roff for various purposes:</para>

      <para>I have prepared a <ulink
      url="../Laurentius/laurentius.tar.gz">worked example</ulink> on how to
      format a TEI document for printing, using XSLT and groff. Provided that
      you have perl with XML::LibXSLT, a modern groff (version 1.18), TeX
      fonts, dvips and ps2pdf installed, you should be able to run this and
      get a laurentius.pdf from the laurentius.xml. Most of these things is
      available as standard on a decent Linux workstation.</para>

      <para>I once wrote a <ulink url="ROFF/gnuplot_gpic_driver.shar">gnuplot
      driver</ulink> for producing graphs using *roff. Supports gpic and pic
      (vanilla UNIX version). My original driver seems obsolete now, but the
      current pic gnuplot driver doesn't seem to work with 3D graphds.</para>

    </sect2>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="random_bits">

    <title>Random bits</title>

    <para>I've had the pleasure to participate in most of <ulink url="
    http://www.dublincore.org/">the DCMI workshops</ulink>. The first one was
    the <ulink url="http://www.ariadne.ac.uk/issue9/caption/">Metadata
    workshop</ulink> in Canberra March 1997 (I'm fattest one of the two waring
    shorts).</para>

    <para>"IT i kulturens tjänst" <ulink
    url="kultur_naet_sverige.html">recenserad</ulink></para> 

    <para><ulink url="publications.html">A not entirely up to date list of
    mostly peer reviewed publications</ulink> and an obsolete <ulink
    url="meriter.html">CV like object</ulink> (which, available as a slightly
    less obsolete <ulink url="meriter.pdf">CV like pdf</ulink>).</para>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="about">

    <title>About these pages</title>

    <para>This home page is written in XML using the <ulink
    url="http://www.docbook.org/">DocBook DTD</ulink>.  It is delivered using
    a XML application server, <ulink url="http://www.axkit.org">AxKIT</ulink>
    which transforms it for use in a browser.  The application server is
    running on an <ulink url="http://www.apache.org/">Apache
    webserver</ulink>.  AxKit is a part of the <ulink
    url="http://www.apache.org/">Apache Software Foundation</ulink>'s <ulink
    url="http://xml.apache.org/">XML initiative</ulink>.</para>

    <para>Other documents here are written using the <ulink
    url="http://www.tei-c.org/">Text Encoding Initiative XML dtd</ulink>. I do
    still ocassionally code HTML, but find that extremely boring.</para>

  </sect1>

</article>





