<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<entry xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>Shooting M mount</title>
  <link href="/entries/2012/01/gxrm/"/>
  <summary>I have been shooting M mount since November last year.</summary>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

      <div style="float: left; width: 240px; margin-left: 0.2em; margin-right: 0.5em;">
	<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/sigfridlundberg/6340958317/" title="100% M by Sigfrid Lundberg, on Flickr">
	  <img src="https://farm7.staticflickr.com/6229/6340958317_9c8b262e6c_m.jpg" width="240" height="180" alt="100% M"/>
	</a>

	<p><small>Figure 1. Some of my current photographic equipment. All of
	it is Leica M-mount. None of it is from Leitz/Leica.</small></p>

      </div>

      <p>
	The Leica brand is so strong that it influences peoples' secret
	wishes. Many buy cameras that look or work alike. This is the Leica
	envy. I too suffer from it. Last year I did something about it. Since
	November last year I've been shooting M mount (See Figure 1). I have
	no <strong>real</strong> Leica stuff. I could possibly afford it but
	then I would have to sacrifice a lot from the other parts in my life
	to get a marginal improvement of my kit.  I've lost all my interest in
	the rangefinder technology, but I admire the lenses. There are high
	quality alternatives to Leica glass. I own lenses from Voigtländer,
	Zeiss and Minolta.
      </p>

      <p>
	I acquired the Ricoh GXR Mount A12, also known as GXR-M. That body has
	some advantages. It is M mount, i.e., I can use these lenses without
	adapter. It is optimized for use together with manual lenses. For
	instance, Ashwin Rao <a href="https://www.stevehuffphoto.com/2011/09/28/the-ricoh-gxr-a12-m-mount-module-review-by-ashwin-rao/">describes
	how he is able to do manual focus</a> fast enough for sports
	photography. That impressed me, and it the factor that settled the
	issue for me. Focus peaking have become even more important for me
	since my eye sight has deteriorated since I ordered it.
      </p>

      <div style="float: right; width: 240px; margin-left: 0.2em; margin-right: 0.5em;">

	<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/sigfridlundberg/6398818559/" title="20111125_001.jpg by Sigfrid Lundberg, on Flickr">
	  <img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7003/6398818559_c72bb06b70_m.jpg" width="240" height="180" alt="20111125_001.jpg"/>
	</a>
	<p><small>Figure 2. I can use Nikon F glass as efficiently as Leica M
	lenses.</small></p>
      </div>

      <p>
	It also has really good image quality.  <a href="https://www.luminous-landscape.com/essays/ricoh_lens_mount_a12.shtml" rel="nofollow">Sean Reid</a> was the one who convinced me that
	anti-aliasing filters are detrimental for image quality.
	Finally, the user interface is very well thought out. See <a href="https://www.luminous-landscape.com/reviews/cameras/ricoh_gxr_a12_field_report.shtml">Luminous Landscape's The field report</a>.
      </p>

      <p>
	The GXR-M is a true exchangeable lens camera. You mount whatever you
	have, possibly using an adapter. I have a Nikon F to Leica M adapter
	(Figure 2). I works nicely, even at infinity for the lenses I've
	tested.
      </p>
 

    </div>
  </content>

  <dc:date>2012</dc:date>
  <category label="images" term="Images"/>
  <category label="photography" term="Photography"/> 
  <category label="hardware" term="Hardware"/>
  <updated>2012-01-18T19:22:19+01:00</updated>
  <id>https://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2012/01/gxrm/</id>
</entry>
