<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<entry xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>100% M</title>
  <link href="/entries/2012/01/gxrm/"/>
  <summary>Having had a web site for about 15 years, I start to wonder why I
  keep it in the first place.</summary>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

      <div style="float: left; width: 240px; margin-left: 0.2em; margin-right: 0.5em;">
	<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/sigfridlundberg/6340958317/" 
	   title="100% M by Sigfrid Lundberg, on Flickr">
	  <img src="http://farm7.staticflickr.com/6229/6340958317_9c8b262e6c_m.jpg" 
	       width="240" 
	       height="180" 
	       alt="100% M"/>
	</a>

	<p><small>Figure 1. Some of my current photographic equipment. All of
	it is Leica M-mount. None of it is from Leitz/Leica.</small></p>

      </div>

      <p>Since November last year I've been shooting M mount (See Figure
      1). There is, however, no <strong>real</strong> Leica stuff. I could
      possibly afford the real thing but then I would have to sacrifice a lot
      of other parts in my life. I do suffer from Leica envy inasmuch as I'd
      love to have some lenses. But I've no interest in a M9. I don't think
      that the rangefinder technology is my cup of tea. Instead the I have
      acquired the Ricoh GXR Mount A12.</p>

      <p>I've presented all the lenses here before. They are Heliar 15mm
      f/4.5, 25mm f/2.8 ZM-Biogon and M-Rokkor 40mm f/2 The small black camera
      is a Ricoh GXR body with Mount A12 sensor. It takes the same lens family
      as Leica M. And it is modern digital mirrorless camera with an
      electronic view-finder.</p>

      <div style="float: right; width: 240px; margin-left: 0.2em; margin-right: 0.5em;">

	<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/sigfridlundberg/6398818559/" 
	   title="20111125_001.jpg by Sigfrid Lundberg, on Flickr">
	  <img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7003/6398818559_c72bb06b70_m.jpg" 
	       width="240" 
	       height="180" 
	       alt="20111125_001.jpg"/>
	</a>
      </div>

      <p>My F- lenses are eagerly awaiting a new
      adapter. Here's some reading for those who are interested:</p>

      <p><a
      href="http://www.stevehuffphoto.com/2011/09/28/the-ricoh-gxr-a12-m-mount-module-review-by-ashwin-rao/"
      rel="nofollow">Ashwin Rao</a> describes how he is able to do manual
      focus fast enough to do sports photography. That impressed me, and that
      was one of the factors that settled the issue for me.  <a
      href="http://www.luminous-landscape.com/essays/ricoh_lens_mount_a12.shtml"
      rel="nofollow">Sean Reid</a> was the one who convinced me that
      anti-aliasing filters are detrimental for image quality.  <a
      href="http://www.luminous-landscape.com/reviews/cameras/ricoh_gxr_a12_field_report.shtml"
      rel="nofollow">Luminous Landscape's The field report</a> convinced me
      about the user interface. </p>


      <p>
	<a
	href="http://www.luminous-landscape.com/essays/ricoh_lens_mount_a12.shtml">Sean
	Reid</a> was the one who convinced me that anti-aliasing filters are
	detrimental for image quality.  <a
	href="http://www.luminous-landscape.com/reviews/cameras/ricoh_gxr_a12_field_report.shtml"
	rel="nofollow">Luminous Landscape's The field report</a> convinced me
	about the user interface.
      </p>

      <p>Having used it over the weekend I can ensure you that I expected a lot of this little black beastm but that its capabilities have exceeded all my expectations.</p>
    



    </div>
  </content>

  <dc:date>2012</dc:date>
  <category label="images" term="Images" />
  <category label="photography" term="Photography" /> 
  <category label="hardware" term="Hardware" />
  <updated>2012-01-17T21:25:23+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2012/01/gxrm/</id>
</entry>
