<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<entry xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>The description and encoding of structure</title>
  <link href="/entries/2009/07/structure/"/>
  <summary>Much metadata is fairly stright forward. A book does have a title
  and an author. That's usually no big deal. We've been able to handle that
  for centuries. A digital book has chapters, and everything you might want to
  know may be in chapter two on page seventyfive. Or someone may tell you the
  solution to your problems after a quarter of an hour in some video on
  YouTube. Now, how do we cope with this?</summary>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

      <p>Many things in life can best be represented as trees. Indeed, life
      itself is a tree of various life forms. We have the animal and plant
      kingdoms, and these main categories are further sub-divided into phylae,
      classes, genera. The animal kingdom is divided into invertebrates and
      vertebrates. The latter include amphibians, reptiles, birds and
      mammals. Human knowledge is also represented as a tree.</p>

      <p>A lot of other things are trees. Hence, philosophers, mathematicins
      and computer scientists have spent efforts on how to understand how to
      model stuff as trees. Within library &amp; information science
      we have used the term classification systems for centuries, I suppose, and
      more recently we have started to talk about ontologies and knowledge
      organization. There are a lot of theory and a lot of standards in this
      area. Systems like <a
      href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Topic_Maps">topic maps</a> (see also
      <a href="http://www.topicmaps.org/">topicmaps.org</a>) and more recently
      Simple Knowledge Organization System <a
      href="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/">SKOS</a>) are available for those
      who need a standard for knowledge organization.</p>

      <p>On a very down to earth level, I tend to think of controlled
      vocabularies as filters and navigators. The latter are trees and may
      contain many terms arranged into a tree of arbitrary depth. The filters
      are more like traditional facets. Think of Yahoo in the nineties. You
      could browse into Tuscany and get a very long list of resources. Then
      there was a bar at the top where you could choose between "Shopping",
      "Eating out", "Accomodation", "Travel" and so forth. These are broader
      categorizations that apply to Firenze as well as Siena or any place you
      may want to visit. We in the Web business call them <em>filters</em>
      or <em>facets</em>.</p>

      <h2>Recognizing and recalling</h2>

      <p>From a user perspective, you have to take into account that there are
      two cognitive processes involved when using services that employ filters
      and navigators. The first one is much more fundamental, and is by
      nurture and possibly nature a part of the human mind: This is to say: Ah
      Tuscany, that is a part of Italy, isn't it. It's like distinguishing
      between a wasp and a bumble bee. On an evolutionary time-scale we've
      benefitted from being able to say, this is edible this is not, or this
      one has a sting and is likely to use it. This is to recognize something
      when you see it. The opposite is a much more difficult cognitive
      process: I want to know something about Tuscany: Ok, I then start
      clicking on Italy. You have to recollect, not only recognize, more to
      begin with. Remembering might not be trivial. To know in advance things
      like that frogs are amphibians and that diabetes is an endocrinological
      disorder. On the other hand, it helps to know such things when doing
      successfully searching in Google as well.</p>

      <h2>Ordered hierarchies of content objects</h2>

      <p>There are structures that are inside a resource, and that require
      navigation as well. As a first approximation we can assume that any
      digital resource, such as digital resource such as an electronic book is
      an ordered hierarchy of content objects. That view has been questioned,
      and it is for instance claimed that just an ordinary text consists of
      many, <a
      href="http://www.stg.brown.edu/resources/stg/monographs/ohco.html">overlapping
      hierarchies</a>.</p>

    </div>
  </content>
  <dc:date>2009</dc:date>
  <category label="structuralwebdesign" term="Structural web design"/>
  <category label="metadata" term="Metadata"/>
  <updated>2009-07-17T17:11:49+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/07/structure/</id>
  <!-- $Id$ -->
</entry>
