<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<entry xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>On focusing on the essentials</title>
  <link href="/entries/2011/05/focus/"/>
  <summary>I acquired a socalled mirrorless interchangable lens camera in
  August last year. Since than I have used it exclusively with manual focus
  vintage lenses. Here I discuss my experience blending old and new imaging
  technologies.</summary>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
      <p>There are issues with using manual focus lenses. One of them is that
      you have to focus. Manually. Thom Hogan puts it like this</p>

      <div style="float: right; width: 240px; margin-left: 0.2em; margin-right: 0.5em;">
	<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/sigfridlundberg/5584797428/"
	   title="Four lenses and a camera by Sigfrid Lundberg, on Flickr">
	  <img src="http://farm6.static.flickr.com/5178/5584797428_26d8d7b5dd_m.jpg"
	       width="240"
	       height="180" alt="Four lenses and a camera"/>
	</a>
	<p>
	  <small>
	    This is what I carry with me in terms of photographic
	    equipment. Gadgets from left to right (links takes you to my
	    corresponding Flickriver sets).

	    (1) <a href="http://www.flickriver.com/photos/sigfridlundberg/tags/nikkorpcauto105mmf25/">Nikkor-PC Auto 105mm f/2.5</a>,

	    (2) Voigtlander F Mount to micro four thirds adaptor

	    (3) Olympus PEN E-P2 with <a
	    href="http://www.flickriver.com/photos/sigfridlundberg/tags/mrokkor40mmf2/">M-Rokkor
	    40mm f/2.0</a> mounted using a Leica M to micro four thirds
	    adaptor

	    (4) <a
	    href="http://www.flickriver.com/photos/sigfridlundberg/tags/nikkoroauto12f35mm/">Nikkor-O
	    Auto 35mm f/2.0</a> and finally

	    (5) <a
	    href="http://www.flickriver.com/photos/sigfridlundberg/tags/heliar15mm45/">Voigtländer
	    Heliar 15mm f/4.5</a>.
	  </small>
	</p>
	<p><small>My <a
	href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/sigfridlundberg/4982142359/">Zoom
	Nikkor</a> often travels with me in my rugsack, and so does my <a
	href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/sigfridlundberg/5450724055/">200 mm
	Nikkor-Q</a>. There is not enough space for them in my camera bag,
	which you see in the background.</small></p>
      </div>

      <blockquote>
	<em>My personal take is that manual focus really only works well in
	two situations: where you have a stationary subject and time; and when
	you use depth of field and a preset focus distance (ala Henri
	Cartier-Bresson's shooting style).</em>
	<a href="http://www.bythom.com/m43lenses.htm">Thom Hogan</a>
      </blockquote>

      <div style="float: left; width: 240px; margin-left: 0.2em; margin-right: 0.5em;">
	<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/sigfridlundberg/5547406852/" title="P3215641.jpeg by Sigfrid Lundberg, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm6.static.flickr.com/5296/5547406852_a510b32eda_m.jpg" width="240" height="192" alt="P3215641.jpeg"/></a>
	<p>
	  <small>The first out-door beer in the spring is most likely the best
	  beer under the sun. Street photography using Voigtländer 15mm
	  Super-Wide Heliar f4.5.</small>
	</p>
      </div>

      <p>I have no problems with Henri Cartier-Bresson's shooting style. I use
      that all the time. I mount my 15mm Heliar using a Leica M adaptor and I
      at aperture 8 I have a depth of field from less than a meter to
      infinity.</p>

      <p>The Flickr group <em>Decisive Moment</em> devoted to photography in
      Cartier-Bresson's style. The guidelines states, among other things
      that</p>

      <blockquote>
	<em>There should be a Background that contributes to the overall
	composition. In most cases this Background is in focus.</em> <a
	href="http://www.flickr.com/groups/decisivemoment/">Decisive
	Moment</a>.
      </blockquote>

      <p>So, what was enforced by necessity, the level of technological
      development between 1930-1950 has become a characteristic of a genre.
      it is not practical if you've
      forgotten your life with manual focus lenses.  You'll find info about
      what lens I've used in the tags. Photography is visual storyteling,
      among other things. The stories I want to tell isn't about photographic
      equipment but about us human beings, our environments, emotions and
      about our time inasmuch as one can learn anything about that from what I
      see in my own life.</p>

      <div style="float: left; width: 240px; margin-left: 0.2em; margin-right: 0.5em;">
	<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/sigfridlundberg/5148714650/" 
	   title="PB052824.JPG by Sigfrid Lundberg, on Flickr">
	<img src="http://farm5.static.flickr.com/4053/5148714650_22dcf55b4d_m.jpg" 
	     width="240" 
	     height="180" 
	     alt="PB052824.JPG"/></a>
      </div>


      <p>Still I'm very interested in old photographic equipment, but only to
      the extent they are useful for telling stories about what I see.</p>

    </div>
  </content>
  <dc:date>2011</dc:date>
  <category label="structuralwebdesign" term="Structural web design"/>
  <updated>2011-05-04T07:30:44+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2011/05/focus/</id>
  <!-- $Id$ -->
</entry>
