<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<entry xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>Too many buses, too many passengers</title>
  <link href="/entries/2015/02/congestion/"/>

  <summary>Inspired by the envy percieved when seeing all buses
  go with high frequency, except those lines I'm using</summary>

  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

      <blockquote><em>In public transport, bus bunching, clumping, convoying, or
      platooning refers to a group of two or more transit vehicles (such as
      buses or trains), which were scheduled to be evenly spaced running along
      the same route, instead running in the same location at the same time.
      This occurs when at least one of the vehicles is unable to keep to its
      schedule and therefore ends up in the same location as one or more other
      vehicles of the same route at the same time.</em> (Wikipedia article: <a
      href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bus_bunching">Bus
      bunching</a>)</blockquote>

      <div style="margin: +1%; width:45%;float:left;">
	<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/sigfridlundberg/16257004660" title="L1011996 by Sigfrid  Lundberg, on Flickr">
	  <img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7318/16257004660_86a5d2aec1_z.jpg" style="width:100%;" alt="L1011996"/>
	</a>
      </div>

      <p>Two route 9A buses standing in the way for each other outside
      Copenhagen Central.</p>

      <p>The A-buses are meant to go so often that no schedule is needed. The
      most frequent one is 5A. One morning last week there were five vehicles
      in at the bus station outside Copenhagen C (OK, I counted both
      northbound and southbound buses). Suppose that many 5A passengers
      elsewhere had to wait long for their transport.</p>

      <br style="clear:both;"/>

      <div style="margin: +1%; width:45%;float:right;">
	<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/sigfridlundberg/16256699368" title="L1011844_v1 by Sigfrid  Lundberg, on Flickr">
	  <img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8652/16256699368_83f3440d0a_z.jpg" style="width:100%;" alt="L1011844_v1"/>
	</a>
      </div>

      <p>Two route 3 buses are about to arrive at the Lund C bus stop in one
      minute.</p>

      <p>In Lund, routes 3 and 6 are following very tight schedules. This
      evening the former shows exactly the same symptom as the Copenhagen A
      routes.</p>

      <br style="clear:both;"/>

      <div style="margin: +1%; width:45%;float:left;">
	<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/sigfridlundberg/16442630961" title="L1011985 by Sigfrid  Lundberg, on Flickr">
	  <img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7353/16442630961_8b2ef0b46d_z.jpg" style="width:100%;" alt="L1011985"/>
	</a>
      </div>

      <p>The opposite is true for route 1 in Lund. This is how crowded it can
      be. No fun to wait for fifteen minutes and then not get a seat.</p>

    </div>

  </content>

  <dc:date>2015</dc:date>
  <category label="photography" term="Photography"/>
  <updated>2015-02-09T19:20:51+01:00</updated>
  <id>https://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2015/02/congestion/</id>
</entry>
