<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<entry xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>Add footnotes to my pages -- a prototype text annotation
  interface</title>
  <link href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/footnotes/"/>
  <summary>I've had a javascript based forum with thread for each entry. That
  seemed boring to me. Why should users be restricted to commenting entire
  articles. Why not letting them add footnotes to arbitrary positions in a
  text. In this entry I experiment with this feature.</summary>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

      <p>There is a link at the top of this page. It says "Show anchors". It's
      not a very user friendly description of what it does, but I cannot
      figure out a better term right now. If you click on it, there will
      appear a link after most words in the text. These are the annotation
      anchors.</p>

      <p>When visible, the anchors appears as a clickable asterisk '*', and
      click on one of them activates the usual <a
      href="http://disqus.com">disqus.com forum</a>. This is by some client
      side DOM programming.</p>

      <p>Submitting a footnote works, but the script never get the
      acknowledgement from the disqus.com server. I don't know why, but it
      seems that the form doesn't like to live in an iframe.</p>

      <p id="anchor55576b680.592539918884886">My server retrieves the
      annotations from the disqus.com web services and print a list of notes
      at the end of the page. This is done server side, shuch that the
      discussions within the footnotes will be visible by search engines. The
      place of the annotation is marked as a note with a link to the
      notes. You may read the annotation when your mouse is over the link.</p>

      <p>Is this a good idea? Do you like it? Should all my pages have user
      supplied foot notes?</p>
      
      <h2>How is it done</h2>

      <p id="anchor55018b510.584488500647474">In order to add footnotes to a
      text, we need to be able to address individual positions in it. These
      positions are what I'd like to call annotation anchors. I've already
      briefly discussed the problem on how to create identifiers (see a <a
      href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/08/quotations/">A
      quotation is much more than an extract</a>). For this entry I've
      extended the xslt script such that it can <a
      href="http://exslt.org/str/functions/tokenize/">tokenize</a> html text
      embedded in atom entry documents. It can also add anchors (id
      attributes) on each individual word (produced by the tokenize function)
      in the whole text. We also implement a javascript which expose these
      anchors to users, and allow them to comment more or less arbitrary point
      in the text.</p>

      <p id="anchor55402b10.359095368701543">There is a <strong>big</strong>
      drawback in this procedure; once you have processed your text and the
      anchors are there, then you <strong>must not</strong> change them. Each
      word has become a resource on the internet. Please view the source of
      this document, before you use the stylesheet <kbd><a
      href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/footnotes/atom_anchor_id.xsl">atom_anchor_id.xsl</a></kbd>.</p>

      <pre>
	&lt;span id="anchor54764">Would&lt;/span>
	&lt;span id="anchor54766">you&lt;/span>
	&lt;span id="anchor54768">like&lt;/span>
	&lt;span id="anchor54770">to&lt;/span>
	&lt;span id="anchor54772">edit&lt;/span>
	&lt;span id="anchor54774">this&lt;/span>
	&lt;span id="anchor54778">text?&lt;/span>
      </pre>

      <p>See what I mean? I cannot author prose like that in my XML
      editor. You wouldn't suffer as much using WYSIWYG tools, but on the hand
      it would presumably destroy the ID-strings.</p>

      <p>When preparing this text, I felt that I had to prepare some
      annotations of my own, and in order to do that I compiled the text,
      published it, made my annotation and then pasted the ID back into the
      source XML in order to be able to continue writing. Formbased proof
      reading of an existing digital text wouldn't be any problem, though.</p>

      <h2>Javascript &amp; DOM scripting</h2>

      <p>You can find the possible anchors by clicking on the link
      <strong>Show anchors</strong>, and hide them again by clicking on
      <strong>Hide anchors</strong> at the same place (there is a
      toggle). There are two javascript functions handling the toggling. The
      possibly most interesting, but also, the most vulnerable, feature is the
      generation of javascript by <a
      href="http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/footnotes/make_javascript.xsl">XSLT
      from RSS</a> for handling the readable notes. The code entering the
      notes into the text looks like this:</p>

      <pre>
      &lt;script type="text/javascript">
	    var usedAnchorIds = new Array();
	    var noteTexts     = new Array();
	    
	    usedAnchorIds[0]="anchor55402b10.359095368701543";

	    noteTexts[0]='I had problems obtaining unique id strings from the'
	    +'generate-id() function in XSLT. (siggelundberg, Fri, 18 Sep 2009'
	    +'17:46:27 -0000)';

	    usedAnchorIds[1]="anchor55018b510.584488500647474";

	    noteTexts[1]='This is an arbitrary point in my text. I find this'
	    +'really suitable for adding a footnote. (siggelundberg, Fri, 18 Sep
	    +'2009 03:27:16 -0000)';

	    printNotes(usedAnchorIds,noteTexts);

    &lt;/script>
      </pre>

      <p>The rest of the features are readily visible on this page. You have
      to reaload the page to see the new footnote -- if I implement this I'll
      will refresh those asynchronously.</p>

    </div>
  </content>
  <dc:date>2009</dc:date>
  <category label="structuralwebdesign" term="Structural web design"/>
  <category label="xmlprocessing" term="XML Processing"/>
  <updated>2009-09-09T21:13:49+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://sigfrid-lundberg.se/footnotes/</id>
  <!-- $Id$ -->
</entry>
