<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<entry xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>A form with a join</title>
  <link href="/entries/2010/03/aformwithajoin/"/>
  <summary>A form is a document that can be used for the entry of data. A join
  is a construct in query languages such SQL. A join allows you to lookup data
  in one part of a database based on a query in an other part. Joins are very
  general, and may appear in other contexts. Such as the XML forms language.</summary>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

      <p>A <strong>form</strong> is a document that can be used for the entry
      of data. A join is a construct in query languages such SQL. A
      <strong>join</strong> allows you to lookup data in one part of a
      database based on a query in an other part. Joins are very general, and
      may appear in other contexts. Such as XQuery, XSLT and XML forms
      language, XForms. I've recently written my first extensive application
      in that language.</p>

      <p>Having worked with XML processing for more than ten years, I'd say
      that I thought that I would easily be able to relate to a new XML
      technology by extrapolating from my earlier experiences. This has
      hitherto been the case. For instance, learning Xerces in java when I've
      used dom4j in java and XML::LibXML in perl was i piece of cake.</p>

      <p>One could expect that if you know XML technologies and HTML forms you
      would easily grasp XForms. Having realised that this wasn't the case I
      thought that having learned XPath and XSLT I would easily grasp
      XForms. That was true, but only partly.</p>

    </div>
  </content>
  <dc:date>2010</dc:date>
  <category label="xmlprocessing" term="XML processing"/>
  <category label="metadataprocessing" term="Metadata processing"/>
  <updated>2010-03-05T18:11:43+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2010/03/aformwithajoin/</id>
  <!-- $Id$ -->
</entry>
