<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<entry xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <author>
    <name>Sigfrid Lundberg</name>
  </author>
  <title>A form with a join</title>
  <link href="/entries/2010/03/aformwithajoin/"/>
  <summary>A form is a document, or part of one, that can be used for the
  entry of data. A join is a construct in query languages such SQL. A join
  allows you to lookup data in one part of a database based on a query in an
  other part. Joins are very general, and may appear in other contexts. Such
  as the XML forms language.</summary>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

      <p>A <strong>form</strong> is a document, or a part of one, that can be
      used for the entry of data. A <strong>join</strong> is a construct in
      query languages such SQL. A join allows you to lookup data in one part
      of a database based on a query in an other part. Joins are general, and
      may appear in other contexts than SQL. Such as XQuery, XSLT and XML
      forms language, XForms. I've recently written my first extensive
      application in that language. It required a larger effort than I had
      expected.</p>

      <p>Having worked with XML processing for more than ten years, I had
      thought that I would easily be able to relate to a new XML technology by
      extrapolating from my earlier experiences. This has hitherto been the
      case. For instance, learning Xerces in java when I've used dom4j in java
      and XML::LibXML in perl was a piece of cake. If you have used the
      venerable Expat callback based parser, the idea behind SAX or Stream API
      for XML (StaX) are quite obvious.</p>

      <p>One could expect that if you know XML technologies and HTML forms you
      would easily grasp XForms. Having realised that this wasn't the case I
      thought that having learned XPath and XSLT I would easily grasp
      XForms. That was true, but only partly. A small part.</p>

      <h3>UI and Events</h3>

      <p>An XForm script, just as an XSLT one, can read XML documents and act
      upon them. The result is very different. XSLT generates another
      document, usually an XML one. The XForm generates a form, a graphical
      user interface. And it is usually one that can be used for editing
      XML. A user interface is event driven, an there are a whole lot of <a
      href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DOM_events">events to keep track
      of</a>.</p>

      <div style="float: right; width:50%;">
      <pre>
&lt;data> 
  &lt;lookup>
    &lt;values xml:id="id1">
      &lt;value>one a&lt;/value>
      &lt;value>one b&lt;/value>
      &lt;value>one c&lt;/value> 
    &lt;/values>
    &lt;values xml:id="id2"> 
      &lt;value>two a&lt;/value>
      &lt;value>two b&lt;/value> 
      &lt;value>two c&lt;/value>
    &lt;/values> 
    &lt;values xml:id="id3">
      &lt;value>three&lt;/value> 
    &lt;/values>
  &lt;/lookup> 
  &lt;keys> 
    &lt;key lookup="id1">first&lt;/key> 
    &lt;key lookup="id2">second&lt;/key>
    &lt;key lookup="id3">third&lt;/key>
  &lt;/keys> 
&lt;/data>
      </pre>

      <p><small>Fig. 1. An XML snippet where there is a list of keys that via
      a reference (a so-called IDREF) in an attribute called lookup refer to
      nodes in another part of the document. The references are anchored using
      xml:id attributes. The relation between the keys and the values is one
      to many.</small></p>

      </div>


      <p>What is a brilliant feature in XSLT might not work at all in a GUI,
      so if you're a lover of the functional programming style recursive
      processing in XSLT you'll be disappointed. XForms isn't XML transformed
      into forms, it is language for writing GUIs for XML.</p>

      <p>Typically one can write really nifty GUIs in XForms. You'll find a
      lot of examples online, for instance by following links from the <a
      href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/XForms">Wikipedia article</a>.  There
      are various implementations, server side ones as well as those running
      client side. I opted for the one implemented as a <a
      href="https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/824">Firefox
      plug-in</a>.</p>

      <h3>Joins and XML documents</h3>

      <p>My project is about editing quite complicated documents, namely
      really heavy beasts in <a
      href="https://music-encoding.org/">Music Encoding
      Initiative XML</a>. We are building a MEI application while the inititive
      are revising the specification and, among other things, move from a DTD
      to <a href="https://relaxng.org/">RelaxNG</a>. A wise move.</p>

      <p>I might return to the project itself at a later stage, but here I
      want to tell you about XForms itself. And about joins. Consider the
      fragment in Fig. 1. If you want to be able to edit the values in the
      vicinity of the keys, you may need <a
      href="https://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2010/03/aformwithajoin/a_form_with_a_join.xml">a
      form like this</a> (requires XForms in your browser). The essential code
      performing the join can be studied in Fig. 2.</p>

      <div>
	<pre>
      &lt;xf:group ref="instance('data-instance')/keys">
          &lt;xf:repeat nodeset="key"
        	  id="lookup-keys-loop">
               &lt;!-- do things with each key -->
               &lt;xf:repeat 
                       nodeset="instance('data-instance')/lookup/
                       values[<span style="color:red;">@xml:id = current()/@lookup</span>]/value"
                       id="value-loop">
               &lt;!-- do things with value group -->
               &lt;/xf:repeat>
          &lt;/xf:repeat>
       &lt;/xf:group>
	</pre>

	<p style="margin-left:+5%;margin-right:+5%;"><small>Fig. 2. XForms
	snippet that loops around all key elements and for each of them make
	the lookup. That is, here we have the join in red colour. xf is short
	for the XForms namespace, which is http://www.w3.org/2002/xforms. Note
	that this code works inside a single document that looks like the one
	in Fig. 1. You cannot edit a database this way.</small></p>

      </div>


      <div style="float: left; width:50%;">
	 <pre>
   select
      last_name,
      department_name
   from
      employees e 
   left outer join 
      departments d
   on
      e.department_id=d.department_id;
	 </pre>

	 <p><small>Fig. 3. The SQL
	 equivalent to the XForms code in Fig. 2. The SQL assumes that there
	 is a table called employees and another called departments, and that
	 employees table contains department_id as a foreign key. This setup
	 is similar with the key-values (based on IDREF &amp; ID) arrangements
	 in Fig. 1-2.</small></p>

       </div>

       <p>The core is the XPath function <kbd
       style="font-family:courier;">current()</kbd> which returns the current
       context node. This construct can then be combined with input fields,
       text areas etc. The corresponding SQL code could look as in Fig. 3.</p>


       <h3>Get the last inserted ID</h3>

       <p><em><q>It's the same old story, but it's new to me.</q></em>
       Whenever you use a RDBMS, you will sooner or later ask the question: Is
       there a way to <a
       href="https://www.google.com/search?hl=en&amp;q=%22get+the+last+inserted+id%22&amp;aq=f&amp;aqi=g-m1&amp;aql=&amp;oq=">get
       the last inserted ID</a>? This, if any, is indeed a SQL FAQ.</p>

       <p>That is, you'll inserted a line in a table, and now you want to use
       this ID as a foreign key in another table. That is you want to create
       data that can be retrieved using a join. All SQL dialects and APIs
       provide facilities for this.</p>

       <p>Unfortunately, you don't have such functions in neither XForms nor
       XSLT. In XSLT that is no big deal; you <a
       href="https://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2009/07/xslt_extensions/">can
       program anything</a> in that language. It is worse in XForms. Fig. 4
       shows shows an XForms trigger that executes a number of actions. It
       inserts two nodes, one containing an IDREF and the other the
       corresponding ID (like inserting both a department and an employee in
       the SQL setup in Fig. 3).</p>

       <p>The IDREF/ID values are created on the fly using XPath
       functions. The problem turned out to be to get hold of the value again
       for the second insert.</p>

       <div>
	 <pre>
&lt;xf:trigger>
  &lt;xf:label>Add key and value&lt;/xf:label>
  &lt;xf:action ev:event="DOMActivate">
    &lt;xf:insert nodeset="key"
	 at="last()"
	 position="after" 
	 origin="instance('empty-instance')/keys/key"/>
    &lt;xf:setvalue ev:event="DOMActivate"
	 ref="key[last()]/@lookup" 
	 value="concat('id',digest(string(random(true)), 'MD5', 'hex'))"/>
    &lt;xf:insert nodeset="instance('data-instance')/lookup/values"
	 at="last()" 
	 position="after" 
	 origin="instance('empty-instance')/lookup/values"/>
    &lt;xf:setvalue ev:event="DOMActivate"
	 ref="instance('data-instance')/lookup/values[last()]/@xml:id"
	 value="instance('data-instance')/keys/key[last()]/@lookup"/>
  &lt;/xf:action>
&lt;/xf:trigger>
	 </pre>
	 <p style="margin-left:+5%;margin-right:+5%;"><small>Fig. 4. XForms
	 code that inserts two elements in a document of the kind shown in
	 Fig. 1. The key element contains an IDREF (the attribute lookup)
	 which points the corresponding xml:id among the values. The form
	 operates by copying nodes from an empty instance and inserting them
	 into the data-instance, i.e., the instance being edited by the
	 user. The last setvalue contains the solution to the SQL FAQ:
	 <strong>How do I get the last inserted ID</strong></small></p>
       </div>

       <h3>Take home message</h3>

       <p>I've learned a lot of XForms and some new XPath functions. The code
       I needed in the Music Encoding initiative example was much more
       complicated than the trigger in Fig. 4.</p>

       <p>The very reason for writing this was that I used more than a week on
       this join and the corresponding ID/IDREF thing. I hadn't expected
       that complexity.</p>

       <p>But having been through this, I don't think there is any format that
       cannot be edited using XForms 1.1. It is a pity that virtually all text
       books and tutorials out there is XForms 1.0 and six or seven years
       old. This is a very good technology that deserves a breakthrough.</p>


     </div>
  </content>
  <dc:date>2010</dc:date>
  <category label="xmlprocessing" term="XML processing"/>
  <category label="metadataprocessing" term="Metadata processing"/>
  <updated>2010-03-05T18:11:43+01:00</updated>
  <id>https://sigfrid-lundberg.se/entries/2010/03/aformwithajoin/</id>
  <!-- $Id$ -->
</entry>
